<rows>
  <row para_id="1120595" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>NCI-CONNECT (Comprehensive Oncology Network Evaluating Rare CNS Tumors) aims to advance the understanding of rare adult central nervous system (CNS) cancers by establishing and fostering patient-advocacy-provider partnerships and networks to improve approaches to care and treatment.</p>
<p>Primary CNS cancers are tumors that start in the brain and spinal cord. They account for less than 2% of all cancers diagnosed a year in the United States. There are over 130 different types, all of them rare. NCI-CONNECT is starting with <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120626" sys_contentid="1120626" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1120626" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7317280" sys_variantid="2317">12 tumor types</a>, each with less than 2,000 people diagnosed a year.</p>
<p>Since these 12 tumors are rare, patients and researchers face unique challenges. Patients struggle to find expert care and treatments. Researchers struggle to identify enough patients to conduct research.</p>
<h2>Building Partnerships</h2>
<p>NCI-CONNECT intends to address these challenges and unmet needs by connecting patients, providers, researchers, and community organizations to work in partnership.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Patients: </strong>NCI-CONNECT wants to <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120689" sys_contentid="1120689" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1120689" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7317281" sys_variantid="2317">connect you with our resources</a> and <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=14&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_contentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7317282" sys_variantid="2297">network of healthcare professionals</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Providers</strong>: NCI-CONNECT wants to work with you to identify patients eligible for <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=18&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121709" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7317283" sys_variantid="2297">clinical trials and studies</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Advocates</strong>: NCI-CONNECT wants to <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121675" sys_contentid="1121675" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121675" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7317284" sys_variantid="2297">partner with your organization</a> to share resources and <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120626" sys_contentid="1120626" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1120626" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7317285" sys_variantid="2317">educational information</a>.</li>
</ul>
<div sys_relationshipid="7317286" sys_dependentid="1131240" rxinlineslot="105" contenteditable="false" sys_dependentvariantid="1823" rxselectedtext="" rxanchortext="" unselectable="on" inlinetype="rxvariant" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable">
<figure class="video center size100">	<div id="ytplayer-3VXCRXvVZUI" class="flex-video widescreen" data-video-id="3VXCRXvVZUI" data-video-title="NCI-CONNECT - A Rare Brain and Spine Tumor Network Overview Video">		<noscript>			<p>				<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3VXCRXvVZUI" target="_blank" title="NCI-CONNECT - A Rare Brain and Spine Tumor Network Overview Video">					View this video on YouTube.				</a>			</p>		</noscript>							</div>	</figure></div>
<h2><strong>Goals</strong></h2>
<p>NCI-CONNECT is a collaborative, innovative, and adaptive program with goals to:&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li>Develop a network of national and international institutions to study selected rare CNS tumors.</li>
<li>Collect, analyze, and share data to enable a better understanding of the selected rare CNS tumors and develop standard of care.</li>
<li>Use the network to investigate new therapies and methods to improve patient outcomes.</li>
</ol>
<p><em>NCI-CONNECT is a program within the Rare Tumor Patient Engagement Network (RTPEN), an initiative supported by the <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/research/key-initiatives/moonshot-cancer-initiative">Cancer Moonshot℠</a>. RTPEN aims to advance research and discover new treatments for rare tumors through a collaborative network of national and international institutions that will provide expertise, personalized healthcare, and education to patients with rare tumors. NCI-CONNECT as part of RTPEN focuses on rare central nervous system tumors and is managed at the National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Center for Cancer Research</a> <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Neuro-Oncology-Branch?qt-lab_branch_patient_tabs=4#qt-lab_branch_patient_tabs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Neuro-Oncology Branch</a>.</em></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120669" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>ATRT is a primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7355963" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumor. This means it begins in the brain or spinal cord.</p>
<h2>What is the grade of ATRTs?</h2>
<p>ATRTs are all classified as Grade IV tumors. This means they are malignant (cancerous) and fast-growing.</p>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with ATRTs?</h2>
<p>ATRTs occur in both children and adults and are very rare in both age groups. There have been only 50 reported cases in adults. ATRTs occur slightly more often in males than females.</p>
<h2>What causes ATRTs?</h2>
<p>Most ATRTs are caused by changes in a gene known as SMARCB1 (also called INI1). This gene normally signals proteins stops tumor growth. But in ATRTs, SMARCB1 doesn&rsquo;t function properly and tumor growth is uncontrolled. SMARCB1 can sometimes be found in a person&rsquo;s DNA, which means they are born with it.</p>
<h2>Where do ATRTs form?</h2>
<p>ATRTs can form anywhere in the CNS. They often occur in the brain and often spread to the spinal cord. But ATRTs rarely begin in the spinal cord. ATRTs can form outside the CNS, such as in the kidney, but this is rare. ATRTs develop from several different very young cells called embryonal cells. These cells include rhabdoid, neuroepithelial, epithelial and mesenchymal.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1123769" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7355973">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120631&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123769&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="ATRT Statistical Chart" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Do ATRTs spread?</h2>
<p>ATRTs can be very fast-growing. They often spread to other areas of the CNS through cerebrospinal fluid (CSF).</p>
<h2>What are the symptoms of an ATRT?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to an ATRT depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location and the patient&rsquo;s age. Some possible symptoms include morning headaches, vomiting, changes in activity levels and loss of balance. In infants, you may see an increase in head size. Since ATRTs are fast-growing, symptoms usually get worse quickly.</p>
<h2>What are treatment options for ATRTs?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for an ATRT is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355964" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.</p>
<p>People with ATRTs usually receive further treatments after surgery, which may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355965" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355966" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a> or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355967" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for ATRTs</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121711" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7355971" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121711">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT03173950">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Nivolumab for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>What do ATRTs look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>ATRTs usually appear very large with fluid-filled areas that often brightens with contrast. You can often see areas of bleeding or dead tissue.</p>
<p><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_contentid=1147892" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7355970" /></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=22&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7355969" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121717">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120671" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="who-treats">
<h2>Who treats central nervous system (CNS) tumors?</h2>
<p>People with CNS tumors are usually cared for by a team of healthcare professionals who have special training. In most cases, and depending on your needs, the following providers will be part of your care team:&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Neuro-oncologist</strong>:<strong> </strong>A doctor who specializes in the diagnoses and treatment of CNS tumors and other neurologic complications of cancer.</li>
<li><strong>Oncologist</strong>:<strong> </strong>A doctor who treats cancer, including CNS tumors.</li>
<li><strong>Neurologist</strong>:<strong> </strong>A doctor who manages disorders of the CNS.</li>
<li><strong>Neurosurgeon</strong>: A doctor who diagnoses and surgically manages CNS diseases.</li>
<li><strong>Radiation Oncologist</strong>: A doctor who plans and gives radiation therapy.</li>
<li><strong>Neuroradiologist</strong>: A doctor who diagnoses diseases of the CNS using imaging techniques such as MRI, CT scan, and PET scan.</li>
<li><strong>Neuropathologist</strong>: A doctor who examines CNS tissue to determine diagnosis.</li>
<li><strong>Neuropsychologist</strong>:<strong> </strong>A psychologist who studies the function and structure of the brain and the thinking, memory, and behavior changes that can result from problems in the brain.</li>
<li><strong>Psychologist</strong>: A healthcare professional who evaluates both normal and abnormal mental states and behavior.</li>
<li><strong>Social Worker</strong>: A healthcare professional who helps people cope and resolve problems in their everyday lives by providing guidance and resources.</li>
<li><strong>Genetic Counselor</strong>: A healthcare professional who evaluates risk and management of inherited conditions for people and families.</li>
<li><strong>Nurse Practitioner and Physician Assistant</strong>: A healthcare professional who diagnoses and manages acute and chronic illnesses.</li>
<li><strong>Nurse</strong>: A healthcare professional who cares for people, families, and communities, and oversees the management of care as prescribed by a doctor, nurse practitioner, or physician assistant. Nurses focus on inpatient care, outpatient care, hospice care, or management of research studies, as examples.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>People with a rare CNS tumor should seek a medical diagnosis and disease care and treatment with a team experienced in their disease.</p>
</section>
<section id="monitored">
<h2>How are tumors monitored?</h2>
<p>People with CNS tumors are usually monitored with <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=16&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=903689" sys_contentid="903689" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7317793" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="903689" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">imaging procedures</a>. The most common are magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), which may include a specialized MRI such as spectroscopy. Sometimes computed tomography (CT) scans and positron emission topography (PET) are also used. How often you have imaging studies will be decided by your physician. A neuroradiologist will read your results from your scans and share them with your physician.</p>
</section>
<section id="diagnosis">
<h2>Who reviews tumors to determine an accurate diagnosis?</h2>
<p>A <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000318818&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000318818&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">neuropathologist</a> should review your tumor tissue. The neuropathologist will determine the grade and type of tumor based on how it looks under the microscope. &nbsp;He or she will also describe your tumor based on genetic changes and share the information with your physician.</p>
<h2>How are tumors graded?&nbsp;</h2>
<p>Primary CNS tumors are grouped by how the tumor tissue looks under a microscope and, sometimes, by certain genetic changes that may be present in the tumor. CNS tumors are <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=24&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=690&amp;sys_contentid=14586" sys_contentid="14586" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="690" sys_relationshipid="7317794" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="14586" sys_dependentvariantid="690">graded</a> based on World Health Organization (WHO) criteria as grade I, grade II, grade III or grade IV.&nbsp; Some tumors are low grade tumors (grade I and grade II) and others are high grade (grade III and IV).&nbsp; Treatment and <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045849&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045849&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">prognosis</a> of primary CNS tumors depends on tumor location, tumor type, extent of tumor spread, genetic findings, the patient&rsquo;s age, and tumor remaining after surgery.&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Grade I</strong>: The tumor cells look more like normal cells under a microscope and grow and spread more slowly than grade II, III, and IV tumor cells. They rarely spread into nearby tissues. Grade I CNS tumors may be cured if they&rsquo;re completely removed by surgery.</li>
<li><strong>Grade II</strong>: The tumor cells grow and spread more slowly than grade III and IV tumor cells. They may spread into nearby tissue and may come back as a higher-grade tumor.</li>
<li><strong>Grade III</strong>: The tumor cells look very different from normal cells under a microscope and grow more quickly than grade I and II tumor cells. They&rsquo;re likely to spread into nearby tissue.</li>
<li><strong>Grade IV (high-grade)</strong>: The tumor cells don&rsquo;t look like normal cells under a microscope and grow and spread very quickly.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="tumor-type">
<h2>What is a tumor type?</h2>
<p>CNS tumors are grouped together based on either the type of cell they start from or the location in the CNS. Subtypes are then defined within each tumor type, based on specific tissue characteristics or changes in the DNA. The tissue characteristics include:</p>
<ul>
<li>How the cancer cells look under a microscope.</li>
<li>If there are certain substances in or on the cells.</li>
<li>If there are certain changes to the DNA of the cells.</li>
</ul>
<p>There are over 100 tumor subtypes. It&rsquo;s important to know your tumor subtype, if available, in order to plan treatment and determine prognosis. Ask your physician if your tumor has subtypes and how your tissue can be evaluated.</p>
<h2>Are CNS tumors genetic?</h2>
<p>All cancers are genetic diseases. This means they are caused by certain changes in genes that control the way cells function. These changes often happen when cells grow and divide. Most cancers are caused by changes in the genes in the tissue or organ where they develop. Only 5 to 10% of all cancers are hereditary, which means passed down through a family.</p>
</section>
<section id="heriditary">
<h2>Are CNS tumors hereditary?</h2>
<p>Most CNS tumors aren&rsquo;t <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=35&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=14890" sys_contentid="14890" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7317795" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="14890" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">hereditary</a>. The small percentage of CNS tumors that are hereditary are due to rare syndromes that make someone more likely to have specific cancers. Doctors can find people and families at risk for these conditions by offering genetic counseling and tests. If you are concerned that your family or medical history may increase your chances of developing cancer, talk to a genetic counselor.</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120672" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The brain controls many <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=233&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7090679" sys_folderid="" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">important body functions</a>, such as emotions, vision, thought, speech, and movement. The spinal cord connects the brain to nerves in most parts of the body. This allows the brain to send messages throughout the body. The network of the brain and spinal cord is called the central nervous system (CNS). It is important to know your tumor location in the CNS to understand your symptoms and how your tumor may impact body functions.</p>
<h2>Brain Anatomy and Functions</h2>
<p>The brain is divided down the middle from front to back into two halves called the cerebral hemispheres. Each hemisphere is divided into four lobes: frontal, parietal, occipital, and temporal. Brain tumors located in the lobes are called supratentorial and tumors located in the cerebellum or brainstem are called infratentorial.</p>
<p>Brain tumors, regardless of their location, can cause headaches, seizures and problems with multi-tasking. Learn about specific changes you may experience based on the tumor location below.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1122829" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7121882">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120629&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1122829&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--> <a class="article-image-enlarge no-resize" href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1518&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120629&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1122829&amp;sys_command=edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" sys_variantid="1518" sys_contentid="1122829">Enlarge</a></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Spine Anatomy and Functions&nbsp;</h2>
<p>Spinal cord tumors are described based on where on the cord the tumor is located and each vertebra is numbered from top to bottom. The neck region is called cervical (C), the back region is called thoracic (T), and the lower back region is called lumbar (L) or sacral/cauda equina (S). Tumors are further described by whether the tumor begins in the cells inside the spinal cord (intramedullary) or outside the spinal cord (extramedullary). Extramedullary tumors grow in the membrane surrounding the spinal cord (intradural) or outside (extradural).</p>
<p>Spinal cord tumors, regardless of location, often cause pain, numbness, weakness or lack of coordination in the arms and legs, usually on both sides of the body. They also often cause bladder or bowel problems. Learn about specific changes you may experience based on the tumor location below.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1122830" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7121883">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120629&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1122830&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--> <a class="article-image-enlarge no-resize" href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1518&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120629&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1122830&amp;sys_command=edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" sys_variantid="1518" sys_contentid="1122830">Enlarge</a></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Body function changes can be caused by the tumor itself or from treatment. Talk with your healthcare provider about any of these concerns. He or she can assess your problems and suggest options to help manage them.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120674" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Choroid plexus tumors are primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7355948" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumors. This means they begin in the brain or spinal cord.</p>
<h2>What are the grades of choroid plexus tumors?</h2>
<p>Choroid plexus tumors are grouped in three grades based on their characteristics.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Grade I</strong> choroid plexus papilloma are low grade tumors. This means the tumor cells grow slowly.</li>
<li><strong>Grade II</strong> atypical choroid plexus papilloma are mid-grade tumors. This means the tumors have a higher chance of coming back after being removed.</li>
<li><strong>Grade III</strong> choroid plexus carcinoma are malignant (cancerous). This means they are fast-growing tumors that tend to invade nearby tissue.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with choroid plexus tumors?</h2>
<p>Choroid plexus tumors occur in both children and adults, but are more common in children in the first year of life. Choroid plexus tumors occur slightly more often in males than females.</p>
<h2>What causes choroid plexus tumors?</h2>
<p>The cause of most choroid plexus tumors is not known. Genetic changes have been linked to the formation of some choroid plexus tumors. Rarely, certain gene changes that can be passed down through families have been linked to a higher chance of developing choroid plexus carcinomas.</p>
<h2>Where do choroid plexus tumors form?</h2>
<p>Choroid plexus tumors arise from a structure in the brain called the choroid plexus. It lines the ventricles (fluid-filled cavities) of the brain and its primary function is to produce <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebrospinal fluid</a> (CSF). Choroid plexus tumors almost always form within the ventricles. They can also form in other regions of the CNS.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1123770" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7355959">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120635&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123770&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Choroid Plexus Tumor Statistics" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h2>Do choroid plexus tumors spread?</h2>
<p>Choroid plexus tumors can spread to other areas of the CNS through CSF.</p>
<h2>What are the symptoms of a choroid plexus tumor?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to choroid plexus tumors depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. People with choroid plexus tumors may have increased pressure within the skull due to the production of too much CSF or blockage of its normal flow. This problem is known as hydrocephalus. Signs and symptoms of hydrocephalus may include nausea, vomiting, irritability, headaches, blurred or double vision, a strong desire to sleep, and seizures.</p>
<h2>What are the treatment options for choroid plexus tumors?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for choroid plexus tumors is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355949" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.</p>
<p>Treatments after surgery may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355950" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355951" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355952" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for choroid plexus tumors</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121711&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7355960">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT03173950">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Nivolumab for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>What do choroid plexus tumors look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>Choroid plexus tumors usually appear in the <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045939&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045939&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">ventricles</a> of the brain. They usually have irregular borders and a &ldquo;cauliflower-like&rdquo; appearance. The tumors usually enhance with contrast and sometimes many tumors can be seen in a different region of the CNS. Choroid plexus carcinomas may also have some swelling around them, which can be seen during an MRI. <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045498&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045498&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Hydrocephalus</a> is almost always seen, too.</p>
<p></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1147892&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7355961" /></a><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121717&amp;sys_revision=22&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7355962">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120675" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>An ependymoma is a primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7355996" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumor. This means it begins in the brain or spinal cord.</p>
<h2>What are the grades of ependymomas?</h2>
<p>Ependymomas are grouped in three grades based on their characteristics. Within each grade, are different ependymoma subtypes. Molecular testing is used to help identify subtypes that are related to location and disease characteristics.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Grade I</strong> ependymomas are low grade tumors. This means the tumor cells grow slowly. The subtypes include subependymoma and myxopapillary ependymoma. Both are more common in adults than in children. Myxopapillary tumors usually occur in the spine.</li>
<li><strong>Grade II</strong> ependymomas are low grade tumors and can occur in either the brain or the spine.</li>
<li><strong>Grade III</strong> ependymomas are malignant (cancerous). This means they are fast-growing tumors.&nbsp; The subtypes include anaplastic ependymomas.&nbsp; These most often occur in the brain, but can also occur in the spine.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_contentid=1123774" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1123774" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7356002" /></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1124066" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356044">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1122365&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Gretel" /></div>
<h3>Patient Experience with Ependymoma</h3>
<p>Learn how a patient with an ependymoma in her spine has survived the disease for over 30 years. She shares her treatment experieces and coping tips.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with ependymomas?</h2>
<p>Ependymomas occur in both children and adults.&nbsp; Ependymomas in the lower half of the brain are more common among children. Ependymomas in the spine are more common among adults. Ependymomas occur slightly more often in males than females.</p>
<h2>What causes ependymomas?</h2>
<p>The cause of ependymomas is not known.</p>
<h2>Where do ependymomas form?</h2>
<p>Ependymomas can form anywhere in the CNS. Ependymomas often occur near the <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045939&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045939&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">ventricles</a> in the brain and the central canal of the spinal cord. On rare occasions, ependymomas can form outside the CNS, such as in the ovaries.&nbsp; Ependymomas develop from ependymal cells (called radial glial cells). Ependymal cells are one of three types of glial cells that support the CNS.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1139372" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356045">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139368&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Kimberly Wallgren" /></div>
<h3>Ependymoma Foundation Informs and Inspires a Community</h3>
<p>Kimberly Wallgren shares how her father&rsquo;s cancer inspired a non-profit to educate and connect people living with ependymoma.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Do ependymomas spread?</h2>
<p>Ependymomas rarely spread outside the CNS. But ependymomas can spread to other areas of the CNS through <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebrospinal fluid</a> (CSF).</p>
<h2>What are symptoms of an ependymoma?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to an ependymoma depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. People with an ependymoma in the brain may have headaches, nausea, vomiting and dizziness. People with an ependymoma in the spine may have back pain, numbness and weakness in their arms, legs or trunk, problems with sexual, and urinary or bowel problems.</p>
<h2>What are treatment options for ependymomas?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for an ependymoma is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355997" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.&nbsp;</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1139371" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356046">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139369&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Dr. Terri Armstrong" /></div>
<h3>Improving Everyday Life for People with CNS Cancers</h3>
<p>Dr. Terri Armstrong shares why she chose to study rare brain and spine tumors and how her research is advancing patient quality of life.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p>After surgery, there is no standard treatment for ependymomas. Many people won&rsquo;t need other treatment after surgery. For other people, treatments may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355998" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355999" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a> or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356000" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for ependymomas</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121711&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356047">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCI-2018-02730">Marizomib for Patients with Ependymoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT03173950">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Nivolumab for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>What do ependymomas look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>Ependymomas usually appear as a well-defined mass that often brightens with contrast.&nbsp;</p>
<p></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1147892&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7356048" /></a><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121717&amp;sys_revision=22&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356049">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120676" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Gliomatosis cerebri is a primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7356421" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumor. This means it begins in the brain or spinal cord.&nbsp;<span>This tumor is no longer recognized as a formal diagnosis, rather gliomatosis cerebri refers to a special pattern of <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000044508&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000044508&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">diffuse</a> and extensive growth of glioma cells, invading multiple lobes of the brain. <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045700&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045700&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">Gliomas</a> of different grade<span class="Apple-converted-space">&nbsp;</span></span><span>and cell of origin (<a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000269436&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000269436&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">astrocytes</a>, oligodendrocytes)</span><span>&nbsp;can grow with this pattern, and very little is understood about the molecular basis of the disease. More research is needed to discover the origin of these tumors and to improve their treatment.</span></p>
<h2>What are the grades of gliomatosis cerebri?</h2>
<p>Gliomatosis cerebri are grouped in three grades based on their characteristics.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Grade II</strong> gliomatosis cerebri are mid-grade tumors. This means the tumors have a higher chance of coming back after being removed. They usually have a change in the genes called isocitrate dehydrogenase (IDH).</li>
<li><strong>Grade III</strong> and <strong>IV</strong> gliomatosis cerebri are malignant (cancerous). This means they are fast-growing tumors that often become resistant to treatment.&nbsp;</li>
</ol>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with gliomatosis cerebri?</h2>
<p>Gliomatosis cerebri occur most often in people between the ages of 46 and 53, but can occur at any age.&nbsp; Gliomatosis cerebri occur slightly more often in males than females.</p>
<h2>What causes gliomatosis cerebri?</h2>
<p>The cause of gliomatosis cerebri are not known.</p>
<h2>Where does gliomatosis cerebri form?</h2>
<p>Gliomatosis cerebri commonly arises from glial cells in the brain. Glial cells support and insulate neurons and are the most abundant cells in the brain. When seen under a microscope the tumor cells resemble glial cells and involve many areas of the cerebrum. This is why this is named gliomatosis cerebri.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1123775" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356431">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120639&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123775&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Gliomatosis Statistics" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h2>Do gliomatosis cerebri spread?</h2>
<p>Gliomatosis cerebri can spread to other areas of the CNS through <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebrospinal fluid</a> (CSF). They can spread quickly and deeply into surrounding brain tissue. They do not spread outside the CNS.</p>
<h2>What are symptoms of gliomatosis cerebri?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to a gliomatosis cerebri depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location and patient&rsquo;s age. Some possible symptoms include seizures, fatigue, mood changes, changes in thinking and memory, and headaches.</p>
<h2>What are treatment options for gliomatosis cerebri?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for a gliomatosis cerebri is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356422" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and remove as much of the tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.&nbsp; Surgery is usually limited to a biopsy, as there is not a central mass for removal.</p>
<p>After surgery, there is no standard treatment for gliomatosis cerebris. Other treatments may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356423" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356424" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356425" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location. This tumor type may respond well to radiation therapy, but patients should discuss the full risks and benefits with their healthcare team, as radiation to a large volume of brain tissue puts normal brain tissue at risk for problems.&nbsp; Chemotherapy is also a treatment that may be recommended during radiation, after radiation is completed, or if the tumor recurs after initial treatment. <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045387&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045387&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Temozolomide</a> is a drug that is often used, as this is the therapy for astrocytic type tumors.&nbsp; Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for gliomatosis cerebri</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121711" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7356428" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121711">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT03173950">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Nivolumab for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCI-2018-02512">Nivolumab for Patients with IDH-Mutant Gliomas</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>What do gliomatosis cerebri look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>Gliomatosis cerebri usually appear abnormal in three or more lobes of the brain.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Type 1</strong> shows no obvious mass, but a widespread tumor pattern or a fluffy looking abnormality.</li>
<li><strong>Type 2</strong> shows a widespread fluffy looking tumor pattern, but also a tumor mass.</li>
</ol>
<p>Gliomatosis cerebri is diagnosed based on imaging, instead of pathology like most other tumor types.</p>
<p></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_contentid=1147892" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7356429" /></a><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=22&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7356430" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121717">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120677" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Medulloblastoma is a primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7356099" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumor. This means it begins in the brain or spinal cord.</p>
<h2>What are the grades of medulloblastomas?</h2>
<p>Medulloblastomas are all classified as Grade IV tumors. This means they are malignant (cancerous) and fast-growing.</p>
<p>There are four subtypes that have been identified in children with medulloblastoma.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha;">
<li>WNT-activated</li>
<li>SHH-activated</li>
<li>Group 3 (non-WNT / non-SHH)</li>
<li>Group 4 (non-WNT / non-SHH)</li>
</ol>
<p>In adults with medulloblastoma, these subtypes are not as well-defined as they are in children.</p>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with medulloblastoma?</h2>
<p>Medulloblastoma can occur in both children and adults, but is more common in children. In adults, medulloblastoma typically affects younger adults between 20 and 40 years of age. Medulloblastomas are most common in white people.</p>
<p><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_contentid=1123777" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1123777" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7356105" /></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133445" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356108">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133438&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Chelsea with her parents" /></div>
<h3>Finding Hope in Clinical Trials</h3>
<p>A mother shares her family&rsquo;s 11-year quest to find the best treatments for their daughter&rsquo;s medulloblastoma tumors.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>What causes medulloblastomas?</h2>
<p>The cause of most medulloblastomas is not known. There&rsquo;s a small percent of childhood medulloblastomas that are related to gene changes that can be passed down through families. There&rsquo;s no known cause for adults diagnosed with medulloblastomas.</p>
<h2>Where do medulloblastomas form?</h2>
<p>Medulloblastomas most commonly form in the <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046714&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046714&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebellum</a>, the bottom part of the brain located at the back of the skull. Medulloblastoma is known as an embryonal <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000044827&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000044827&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">neuroepithelial</a> tumor because it forms in fetal cells that remain after birth.</p>
<h2>Do medulloblastomas spread?</h2>
<p>Medulloblastomas are very fast-growing. They often spread to other areas of the CNS through cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). Rarely, medulloblastomas can spread outside the CNS to the bones or the lymphatic system.</p>
<h2>What are symptoms of a medulloblastoma?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to a medulloblastoma depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. People with a medulloblastoma in the cerebellum may have issues with walking, balance, and/or fine motor skills. If the tumor is blocking the CSF, this can lead to increased pressure inside the skull.&nbsp; This can cause headaches, nausea, vomiting, blurred and double vision, extreme sleepiness, confusion, seizures and even passing out. If medulloblastoma has spread to the spine, symptoms may include weakness or numbness in the arms and or legs, a change in normal bowel or bladder habits, and spinal pain.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1132920" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356109">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1132958&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Marta Penas-Prado" /></div>
<h3>Researching Medulloblastoma</h3>
<p>Dr. Marta Penas-Prado discusses her role on the NCI-CONNECT team and her interest in improving the lives of patients with medulloblastoma.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>What are treatment options for medulloblastoma?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for medulloblastoma is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356100" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.</p>
<p>Most people with medulloblastomas receive further treatments. Treatments may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356101" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356102" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, or taking part in <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356103" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>.&nbsp; Surgery is usually followed by radiation to the brain, and even spine since this disease tends to spread in the brain and spine.&nbsp; Because of problems with bone marrow and surrounding organs that occur with brain and spine radiation, proton beam radiation therapy is often recommended. Chemotherapy may also be part of the treatment plan, depending on the subtype and amount the tumor has spread. Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option. It is important to seek expert recommendations from a neuro-oncologist with experience in adult medulloblastoma. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type and tumor location.</p>
<p></p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for medulloblastoma</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121711&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356110">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT03173950">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Nivolumab for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<h2>What does it look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>Medulloblastomas usually appear as a solid mass in the cerebellum, which is the portion of the brain in the back of the head between the <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046484&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046484&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebrum</a> and the <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046491&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046491&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">brain stem</a>. The tumor often brightens with contrast. Once the mass is known to be a medulloblastoma, a MRI of the spinal cord is recommended to see if it has spread.</p>
<p></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1147892&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7356111" /></a><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121717&amp;sys_revision=22&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356112">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120678" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>A meningioma is a primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7356113" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumor. This means it begins in the brain or spinal cord. Overall, meningiomas are the most common type of primary brain tumor.&nbsp; However, higher grade meningiomas are very rare.&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What are the grades of meningiomas?</h2>
<p>Meningiomas are grouped in three grades based on their characteristics. Each grade includes different meningioma subtypes. Molecular testing is used to help identify subtypes that are related to location and disease characteristics.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Grade I</strong> meningiomas are low grade tumors and are the most common. This means the tumor cells grow slowly.</li>
<li><strong>Grade II</strong> atypical meningiomas are mid-grade tumors. This means the tumors have a higher chance of coming back after being removed. The subtypes include choroid and clear cell meningioma.</li>
<li><strong>Grade III</strong> anaplastic meningiomas are malignant (cancerous). This means they are fast-growing tumors. The subtypes include papillary and rhabdoid meningioma. &nbsp;</li>
</ol>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with atypical and anaplastic meningiomas?</h2>
<p>Meningiomas are more common in females, but grades II and III occur more often in males. They are most common in black people, followed by white people, and then Asian-Pacific Islanders. The meningiomas tend to occur in people around 60 years old, with the risk increasing with age.</p>
<h2>What causes atypical and anaplastic meningiomas?</h2>
<p>The cause of meningiomas is not known. Exposure to radiation, especially in childhood, is the only known environmental risk factor for developing meningiomas. People who have a genetic condition, called <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000256540&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000256540&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">neurofibromatosis type 2</a>, are at increased risk for developing meningiomas.</p>
<h2>Where do atypical and anaplastic meningiomas form?</h2>
<p>Meningiomas form along the dura mater, the outermost layer of tissue that covers and protects the brain and spinal cord. The <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000743301&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000743301&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">dura mater</a> is one of three layers that form the meninges. Meningiomas arise from meningeal cells.&nbsp; As a result, they tend to occur along the surface of the brain.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1123778" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356120">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120643&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123778&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Meningioma Statistics" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Do atypical and anaplastic meningiomas spread?</h2>
<p>Meningiomas can spread to other areas of the CNS through <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebrospinal fluid</a> (CSF). Grade II meningiomas can invade surrounding tissue, including nearby bone tissue.&nbsp; Grade III meningiomas have irregular cells and are likely to invade the brain or spread to other organs in the body.</p>
<h2>What are the symptoms of atypical and anaplastic meningiomas?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to a meningioma depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. People with a meningioma may have vision changes, loss of hearing or smell, confusion, seizures, or headaches that are worse in the morning.</p>
<h2>What are the treatment options for atypical and anaplastic meningiomas?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for a malignant meningioma is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356114" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.</p>
<p>Most people with atypical and anaplastic meningiomas receive further treatments. After surgery, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356115" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a> is often recommended to delay the return of grade II and III meningiomas. Treatments may also include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356116" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356117" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option. The role of chemotherapy or clinical trials after radiation therapy is unclear. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for atypical and anaplastic meningiomas</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121711&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356121">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT03173950">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Nivolumab for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>What do atypical and anaplastic meningiomas look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>Grade II and III meningiomas usually appear as an enhancing mass on the outside lining of the brain tissue, which may or may not brighten with contrast.&nbsp; Malignant meningiomas can also invade into the brain tissue.</p>
<p></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1147892&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7356122" /></a><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121717&amp;sys_revision=22&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356123">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120679" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Oligodendroglioma is a primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7356206" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumor. This means it begins in the brain or spinal cord.</p>
<h3>What are the grades of oligodendrogliomas?</h3>
<p>Oligodendrogliomas are grouped in two grades based on their characteristics.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Grade II</strong> oligodendrogliomas are low grade tumors. This means the tumor cells grow slowly and invade nearby normal tissue. In many cases, they form years before being diagnosed as no symptoms appear.</li>
<li><strong>Grade III</strong> oligodendrogliomas are malignant (cancerous). This means they are fast-growing tumors. They are called anaplastic oligodendriogliomas.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Who is diagnosed with oligodendrogliomas?</h3>
<p>Oligodendrogliomas occur most often in people between the ages of 35 and 44, but can occur at any age. Oligodendrogliomas occur slightly more often in males and are rare in children.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1123779" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356219">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120645&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123779&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Oligodendroglioma Statistics" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1124068" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="&lt;div sys_dependentvariantid=&quot;2386&quot; sys_dependentid=&quot;1124068&quot; inlinetype=&quot;rxvariant&quot; rxinlineslot=&quot;105&quot; sys_siteid=&quot;305&quot; sys_folderid=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable&quot; contenteditable=&quot;false&quot; rxselectedtext=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;topic-feature large-4 columns card left&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;feature-card cgvBlogPost&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-hover&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;amp;sys_context=0&amp;amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;amp;sys_contentid=1124068" sys_relationshipid="7356220">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123923&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Brock with his two sons" /></div>
<h3>Father Advocates for His Sons</h3>
<p>Read how a father is advocating to save his two sons with oligodendrogliomas and how his family copes.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<h3>What causes oligodendrogliomas?</h3>
<p>The cause of most oligodendrogliomas is not known. Exposure to radiation and certain gene changes that can be passed down through families have been linked to a higher chance of developing oligodendrogliomas.</p>
<h3>Where do oligodendrogliomas form?</h3>
<p>Oligodendrogliomas are commonly found in the white matter and the outer layer of the brain, called the cortex, but can form anywhere in the CNS. These tumors are called oligodendrogliomas because the cells resemble oligodendrocytes, a type of brain cell that supports and insulates nerve fibers in the CNS.</p>
<h3>Do oligodendrogliomas spread?</h3>
<p>Oligodendrogliomas can spread to other areas of the CNS through <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebrospinal fluid</a> (CSF), but is uncommon. Oligodendrogliomas rarely spread outside of the CNS to other organs.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1130866" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356221">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1130865&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Oligodendroglioma Jered" /></div>
<h3>Survivor Shares Advice</h3>
<p>A brain tumor survivor shares his experience with oligodendroglioma and advice for others.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h3>What are the symptoms of an oligodendroglioma?</h3>
<p>Symptoms related to oligodendrogliomas depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. The most common sign of an oligodendroglioma is a seizure. Around 60% of people have a seizure before being diagnosed. Other symptoms people may have are headaches, problems with thinking and memory, weakness, numbness, or problems with balance and movement.</p>
<h3>What are the treatment options for oligodendrogliomas?</h3>
<p>The first treatment for an oligodendroglioma is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356207" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.&nbsp;Treatments after surgery may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356208" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356209" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356210" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1131785" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356222">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1131786&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Elizabeth Claus" /></div>
<h3>Study of Low-Grade Gliomas</h3>
<p>Neurosurgeon Dr. Elizabeth Claus discusses her International Low Grade Glioma Registry, a study of the evolution of the low-grade glioma genome and the cells driving resistance to treatment.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<p>Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location.</p>
<p>Your oncologist might recommend a combination of medications - <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045378&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045378&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">procarbazine</a>, <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046017&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046017&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">lomustine</a>, and <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045435&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045435&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">vincristine</a>. A chemotherapy called t<a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045387&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045387&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">emozolomide</a> is also being studied in clinical trials.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for oligodendrogliomas</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121711" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7356216" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121711">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCI-2018-02512">Nivolumab for Patients with IDH-Mutant Gliomas</a></li>
</ul>
<h3>What do oligodendrogliomas look like on an MRI?</h3>
<p>Oligodendrogliomas usually appear as a single tumor with well-defined borders. The tumor may enhance with contrast and is most often seen in anaplastic oligodendrogliomas. Oligodendrogliomas tend to have some swelling around them.</p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_contentid=1147892" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7356217" /></a><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=22&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7356218" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121717">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120680" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Pineal region tumors are primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7356153" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumors. This means they begin in the brain or spinal cord.</p>
<h2>What are the grades of pineal region tumors?</h2>
<p>Pineal region tumors are grouped in four grades and subtypes based on their characteristics.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Grade I</strong> pineocytoma are low grade tumors. This means the tumor cells grow slowly.</li>
<li><strong>Grade II or III</strong> pineal parenchymal or papillary tumors of the pineal region are both mid-grade tumors. This means the tumors have a higher chance of coming back after being removed.</li>
<li><strong>Grade IV</strong> pineoblastoma are malignant (cancerous). This means they are fast-growing tumors that tend to invade nearby tissue.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ol>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with pineal region tumors?</h2>
<p>Pineal region tumors occur in children and young to middle age adults. Pineoblastomas are more common during the first 20 years of life. All tumors, except papillary tumors of the pineal region, occur slightly more often in females than males.</p>
<p><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_contentid=1123780" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1123780" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7356159" /></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1135186" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356166">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1135185&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Lawrence with his daughter" /></div>
<h3>Pineal Region Tumor Survivor Experience</h3>
<p>A pineal region tumor survivor shares how he found the best care, treatments and resources to live.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>What causes pineal region tumors?</h2>
<p>The cause of most pineal region tumors is not known. Pineoblastomas can occur in people with the inherited genetic disorder bilateral <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046774&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046774&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">retinoblastoma</a>.</p>
<h2>Where do pineal region tumors form?</h2>
<p>Pineal region tumors form in the pineal region of the brain. This region is located deep in the middle of the brain. Pineal region tumors arise from cells that grow into nerves near the <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046226&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046226&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">pineal gland</a>.</p>
<h2>Do pineal region tumors spread?</h2>
<p>Pineal region tumors can spread to other areas in the CNS through <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebrospinal fluid</a> (CSF).</p>
<h2>What are symptoms of a pineal region tumor?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to pineal region tumors depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. People with pineal region tumors may have increased pressure inside the skull due to a build-up of CSF, known as <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045498&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045498&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">hydrocephalus</a>. Signs and symptoms of hydrocephalus may include headaches, nausea, vomiting, difficulty with eye movements, difficulty with balance, and walking.&nbsp;</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1135599" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356167">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1135598&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Prashant Chittiboina" /></div>
<h3>Advancing Treatments for Pineal Region Tumors</h3>
<p>Read how collaborating across specialties can help neuro-oncologists better understand pineal region tumors.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>What are the treatment options for pineal region tumors?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for pineal region tumors is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356154" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Treatments after surgery may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356155" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356156" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356157" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for pineal region tumors</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121711" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356164" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121711">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT03173950">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Nivolumab for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>What do pineal region tumors look like on a CT scan or MRI?</h2>
<p>Pineal region tumors usually appear as a solid mass that brightens with contrast. On a CT scan, calcium may be present. Pineoblastomas may extend into surrounding brain structures.</p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_contentid=1147892" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7356165" />Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120681" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma (PXA) and anaplastic pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma (APXA) are two types of very rare <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045602&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045602&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">astrocytomas</a>. They are primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7356168" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumors. This means they begin in the brain or spinal cord.</p>
<h2>What are the grades of PXA and APXA?</h2>
<p>The tumors are grouped in two grades based on their characteristics.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Grade II</strong> PXAs are low grade tumors. This means the tumor cells grow slowly.</li>
<li><strong>Grade III</strong> APXAs are malignant (cancerous). This means they are fast-growing tumors.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with PXAs and APXAs?</h2>
<p>PXAs and APXAs can occur at any age, but tend to happen in young adulthood, and affect men and women equally. PXAs and APXAs are more common in people of African descent.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1123781" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356177">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120649&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123781&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Pleomorphic Xanthoastrocytoma (PXA) Statistics" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1142910" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356178">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1142909&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Darien" /></div>
<h3>PXA Tumor Survivor</h3>
<p>Darien shares how he lived with what he thought was an aggressive brain cancer for eight years. Then, he got an accurate low-grade rare tumor diagnosis and made a fresh start.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>What causes PXAs and APXAs?</h2>
<p>The cause of most PXAs and APXAs is not known. People with gene &nbsp;changes that can be passed down through families such as neurofibromatosis type I and familial melanoma/astrocytoma syndrome, are at increased risk for developing PXAs and APXAs.</p>
<h2>Where do PXAs and APXAs form?</h2>
<p>PXAs and APXAs usually occur in one of the four lobes of the brain. The temporal lobe is the most common location. Rarely, PXAs and APXAs can form in the <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046714&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046714&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebellum</a>, brainstem, and spinal cord. PXAs and APXAs are usually located close to the surface of the brain tissue. Scientists believe these tumors arise from cells that grow into glial and nerve cells. PXAs and APXAs can look a variety of ways under the microscope and can be challenging to diagnose, as they share characteristics with other primary brain tumors. Review by an expert neuropathologist is recommended to confirm this diagnosis. Molecular testing will often reveal a <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000561325&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000561325&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">BRAF gene</a> change in these tumors.</p>
<h2>Do PXAs and APXAs spread?&nbsp;</h2>
<p>PXAs are slow-growing tumors that usually don&rsquo;t spread. APXAs are fast-growing tumors that usually invade brain tissue in the lobe of the brain where they started. It&rsquo;s rare for APXAs and PXAs to spread to other areas of the CNS. There are no reported cases of spread outside of the CNS.</p>
<h2>What are symptoms of a PXA or APXA?&nbsp;</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to PXAs and APXAs depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. People with PXAs may have seizures, epilepsy, and chronic headaches. People with APXAs may have seizures, weakness, numbness, and speech and language changes.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1143324" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356179">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1143323&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Dr. Brett Theeler" /></div>
<h3>Neurologist Helps Provide Care to CNS Tumor Patients</h3>
<p>Read how Dr. Brett Theeler is helping treat and educate patients with PXA and APXA tumors, which are among the rarest of rare brain and spine cancers.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>What are treatment options for PXAs and APXAs?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for a PXA and APXA is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356169" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person. PXAs can often be treated by surgery alone.</p>
<p>If they come back after surgery, there is no standard treatment for PXAs and APXAs. Possible treatments at this time may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356170" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356171" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, targeted therapies, or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356172" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. If a BRAF change is present, clinical trials using a drug to target that may also be an option. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for PXAs and APXAs</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121711&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356180">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>What do PXAs and APXAs look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>PXAs often form fluid-filled cysts in a mural nodule, which means a cyst within solid tissue with a dense appearance on MRI.&nbsp; APXAs may appear similar to PXAs, but the way they look varies and makes it difficult to tell apart from other primary CNS tumors. The diagnosis of PXA or APXA can&rsquo;t be made by imaging alone because they look the same as <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045698&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045698&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">glioblastomas</a> and other high-grade brain cancers.</p>
<p></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1147892&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7356181" /></a><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121717&amp;sys_revision=22&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356182">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120682" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>PNETs are primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7356183" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumors. This means they begin in the brain or spinal cord.&nbsp;<span>PNET is a</span><span><span class="Apple-converted-space">&nbsp;</span>term that stands for a group of tumors, and these tumors are currently being reclassified and given other specific names based on their molecular features.</span></p>
<h2>What are the grades of PNETs?</h2>
<p>The group of tumors, formerly known as PNETs, are Grade IV tumors. This means they are malignant (cancerous) and fast-growing.&nbsp;<span>These are tumor types that belong to this group:</span></p>
<ul>
<li>Medulloepithelioma</li>
<li>CNS <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045418&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045418&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">neuroblastoma</a></li>
<li>CNS ganglioneuroblastoma</li>
<li><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000367442&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000367442&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Embryonal tumor</a> with multilayered rosettes and other unspecified embryonal tumors&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with PNETs?</h2>
<p>PNETs occur more commonly in children, but can occur in adults. PNETs are very rare tumors,&nbsp;<span>and their classification is evolving</span><span>.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h2>What causes PNETs?</h2>
<p>The cause of PNETs is not known. Some PNETs are related to genetic changes.</p>
<h2>Where do PNETs form?</h2>
<p>PNETs are commonly found in the brain and rarely, in the brainstem or spinal cord. PNETs is a group of tumors that form from the ectoderm, the outermost layer of cells of an embryo in early development.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1123782" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356191">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120651&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123782&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Primitive Neuro-Ectodermal Tumors (PNET) Statistics" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Do PNETs spread?</h2>
<p>PNETs can spread to other areas of the CNS and organs. When first diagnosed, about one-third of patients&rsquo; tumors have spread.</p>
<h2>What are the possible symptoms of PNETs?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to PNETs depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. People with PNETs may have headaches, seizures, thinking or memory problems, weakness, numbness, or problems with balance and movement. People with PNETs in the spine may have bowel or bladder <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046354&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046354&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">incontinence</a>, and pain in the back and legs.</p>
<h2>What are the treatment options for PNETs?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for PNETs is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356184" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.</p>
<p>People with PNETs usually receive further treatments. Treatments may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356185" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356186" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356187" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. Surgery is usually followed by radiation in patients 3 years old or older, sometimes including the brain and the spine. Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for PNETs</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121711&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356192">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>What do PNETs look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>PNETs usually initially appear as a single mass in the cortex, the outer layer of the brain. PNETs often enhance with contrast and more than one tumor can be identified. Sometimes, there are cysts or fluid collections found within the mass. PNETs may also have some swelling around them.</p>
<p></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1147892&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7356193" /></a><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121717&amp;sys_revision=22&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356194">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1120713" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Coping with a rare tumor diagnosis may make you feel isolated, overwhelmed, afraid or even angry. You may wonder if anyone understands your diagnosis or how you feel. You may be unsure where to find more information or you may need time to understand how your diagnosis will affect your life and loved ones.</p>
<p>During this time, positive coping strategies may help you get through each day so you can continue to live fully. Below are some things you can do that may help you cope in a healthy way, at your own pace.</p>
<h2>Talk about Your Feelings and Needs</h2>
<p>Talking with your healthcare team and your loved ones about your diagnosis and treatment is important. It can help your healthcare team provide the best treatment and allow your loved ones to provide support. Talking can also ease the burden of holding things in and feeling like your needs are not met. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>Try the following tips to help you talk with others.</p>
<p><strong></strong><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120671#who-treats" sys_contentid="1120671#who-treats" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120671" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7371182" sys_variantid="2297"><strong>Healthcare team</strong></a>: Tell your healthcare team how your diagnosis and treatment are making you feel physically and emotionally. The more honest and open you are, the better your health needs can be managed and tailored to you.</p>
<p>And remember, each patient is unique so your healthcare team may not know what you&rsquo;re going through. If questions arise while you&rsquo;re away from your healthcare team, write them down to ask at your next visit or through secure messaging systems provided by your healthcare team. If you have serious or pressing concerns, contact your healthcare team right away.</p>
<p>Be sure to also:</p>
<ul>
<li>Keep copies of your medical records in a folder or place that is easy to access.</li>
<li>Write down symptoms and side effects and when and where they happen to share with your healthcare team. You may also note what makes them better or worse and how you treated them.</li>
<li>Bring someone to your doctor visits who can help record information, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1120712" sys_contentid="1120712" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" sys_dependentid="1120712" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7371183" sys_variantid="1764">ask questions</a> and discuss your care.</li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1137289" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7371184">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137285&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Heart" /></div>
<h3>3 Tips for Caregiver Self-Care</h3>
<p>Being a caregiver to a patient with a brain or spine tumor is an important and challenging role, but caregivers need to focus on their health and wellness too.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Loved ones</strong>: Talking to family and friends about your diagnosis can be difficult. But sharing with people who support you can help you cope. Family and friends may want to help, but aren&rsquo;t sure what to do. Talking about your needs also allows you to ask for help and move forward.</p>
<p>Tips for talking with family and friends include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Before talking to them, think about what you want to share. Decide how much information they should know. And be honest with the information you share.</li>
<li>Tell your close loved ones your course of treatment so they can understand what you will be going through. Then they can help support your physical and emotional needs.</li>
<li>Use web-based tools to ask for help with meals and tasks that you may not be able to do during treatment. Web-based tools allow you to create lists of chores and tasks that people can sign-up to do. &nbsp;</li>
<li>Set-up a way to keep in touch with loved ones and assign a point of contact to send updates. Group emails and blog posts are examples. Then everyone can easily get updates on your journey.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Set Goals</h2>
<p>Set realistic goals for yourself. You can create short- or long-term goals for the areas of your life that you want to manage. And think about what you want to do when you feel well again. Short-term goals are things you want to achieve soon like today, this week, this month or this year. For example, plan to walk for 10 minutes three days a week, write three positive entries in your journal each month or research and plan a weekend trip. Short-term goals can help set the stage for long-term goals.</p>
<p>Long-term goals are things you want to achieve in the future. They&rsquo;re not tasks you can do this month or even this year however, they do require time and planning. For example, research and plan a vacation, think about learning things you always meant to learn and find classes or instructors to teach you.</p>
<p>Whether your goal is short- or long-term, break it down. Use the <strong>SMART</strong> technique to set your goals:</p>
<ul>
<li>Make your goal <strong>S</strong>pecific</li>
<li>How is it going to be <strong>M</strong>easured?</li>
<li>Is it <strong>A</strong>ttainable?</li>
<li>Be <strong>R</strong>ealistic about being able to accomplish this goal</li>
<li><strong>T</strong>imely - How long will you give yourself to complete your goal?&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>An important lesson in goal-setting is to reward yourself through the process. If you got out of bed, walked to the mailbox or wiggled some of your fingers today, be proud. Don&rsquo;t wait until you have achieved a big goal to fully celebrate your accomplishments.</p>
<h2>Keep a Journal</h2>
<p>Writing in a journal can help you express your thoughts and feelings. It&rsquo;s also a way to release any feelings that may be building up. When you don&rsquo;t express your feelings, you may release them in unexpected ways that are hurtful to your loved ones.</p>
<p>Your journal is also a personal record of your journey. You can note a positive event or write a positive message to yourself at the end of each day. You can set a time each day to journal your story in any way you would like.&nbsp;</p>
<p>You can also use your journal time to think about steps you can take to resolve any concerns. Here are steps to work through a concern:</p>
<ol>
<li>Decide if you have control over your concern.</li>
<li>Be as specific as possible on the details of your concern and the issues.</li>
<li>List any possible solutions. No answer is right or wrong.</li>
<li>Write the pros and cons for each solution.</li>
<li>Pick a solution and give yourself time to follow through with it.</li>
</ol>
<p>If the solution doesn&rsquo;t help, you may pick another solution, or choose to list new solutions (following steps 3 through 5 again).&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Be Present</h2>
<p>Your diagnosis may be overwhelming, making it hard to focus on tasks or concerns. To cope, try to experience things as they are, instead of how you want them to be. Doing so is being mindful and present. It helps reduce bad thoughts and trying to control things out of your control. &nbsp;</p>
<p>Ways to be present include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Take part in routine tasks with more awareness. Whether you&rsquo;re eating a meal, talking with a friend or listening to music, pay close attention to what&rsquo;s occurring around you.</li>
<li>Take a moment each day to focus on your senses: sight, hearing, touch, smell, and taste. The sense that comes first is the one you should use in that moment.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<h2>Find Balance in Your Life</h2>
<p>Balance is key to maintaining stability in your life. Prior to your diagnosis, you may have <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=9&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859589" sys_contentid="859589" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="859589" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7371185" sys_variantid="2297">had a routine</a>. You should try to continue that routine, but don&rsquo;t do too much. It&rsquo;s important to have a life you enjoy outside of your doctor visits and treatments.</p>
<p>A routine or schedule can also give you purpose. It can help push you to do what you can, when you can. It can help you deal with feelings of isolation, not knowing how to deal with your diagnosis and concerns about your future.</p>
<p>Also, if your <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=12&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859593" sys_contentid="859593" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="859593" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7371186" sys_variantid="2297">faith or spirituality</a> was an important part of your life prior to your diagnosis, be sure to maintain it.</p>
<h2>Practice Daily Relaxation Techniques</h2>
<p><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1037684" sys_contentid="1037684" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1037684" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7371187" sys_variantid="2297">Relaxation and stress-relieving techniques</a> can help ease anxiety about your diagnosis or treatment. And you can use these techniques throughout your cancer journey. Techniques you can add to your daily routine include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000689577&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000689577&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Guided imagery</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nccih.nih.gov/taxonomy/term/363" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Progressive muscle relaxation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nccih.nih.gov/taxonomy/term/933" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Diaphragmatic breathing</a></li>
</ul>
<p>You can also ask a counselor or therapist to help you find additional coping techniques.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121295" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The signs and symptoms of brain and spine tumors vary greatly and depend on the <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120672" sys_contentid="1120672" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340586" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120672" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">tumor location</a>, size and how fast they grow. Symptoms can be caused by the location of the tumor or from the tumor pressing on brain tissue or the spinal cord and nerves. Brain and spine tumor signs and symptoms also can occur gradually over days or months or they can happen suddenly.</p>
<h2>Symptoms</h2>
<p><strong>Brain tumor symptoms may include:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Morning headache or headache that goes away after <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000390324&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000390324&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">vomiting</a></li>
<li><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045484&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045484&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Seizures</a></li>
<li>Vision, hearing, and speech problems</li>
<li>Loss of appetite</li>
<li>Frequent <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000390302&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000390302&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">nausea</a> and vomiting</li>
<li>Changes in personality, mood, ability to focus, or behavior</li>
<li>Loss of balance and trouble walking</li>
<li>Weakness</li>
<li>Unusual sleepiness or change in activity level</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Spinal cord tumor symptoms may include:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Back pain or pain that spreads from the back towards the arms or legs</li>
<li>A change in <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046500&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046500&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">bowel</a> habits or trouble urinating</li>
<li>Weakness or numbness in the arms or legs</li>
<li>Trouble walking</li>
</ul>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340610">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1123728&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123799&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /></div>
<h3>Outcomes and Risk Study</h3>
<p>Help us improve care for patients with rare CNS tumors by participating in an online survey. The survey will ask you questions about your symptoms, treatments, and quality of life during and after cancer.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<p>You should call your doctor if you have any symptoms that worry you. Your doctor will examine you, ask you questions, and perform a series of tests. The most common test to find out if you have a brain or spine tumor is <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045997&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045997&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">magnetic resonance imaging</a> (MRI). It takes detailed pictures of all parts of your brain or spine.</p>
<h2>Diagnosis</h2>
<p>If your test results show a tumor, it is important for you to find a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=18&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_contentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340587" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">doctor specially trained</a> to treat your brain or spine tumor. You also want to find a doctor you can trust and feel comfortable with. The expertise of your doctor will also help you get an accurate <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046450&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046450&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">diagnosis</a>, so he or she can plan your treatment and coordinate your care with a better chance of success.</p>
<p>To get an accurate diagnosis of your <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120671" sys_contentid="1120671" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340588" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120671" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">tumor type</a>, you will need a <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045164&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045164&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">biopsy</a>. A biopsy is a surgical procedure to remove a piece of tumor tissue. The tumor tissue is usually removed during surgery to remove as much of your brain or spine tumor as possible to treat your cancer and relieve symptoms. And it is critical to find a <a href="https://neuroscience.nih.gov/ninds/ForPatients/NeurosurgeryClinics.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">neurosurgeon</a> with extensive experience to perform your surgery. A <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000318818&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000318818&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">neuropathologist</a> will examine the tumor tissue to provide a diagnosis of your tumor type.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2392" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340611">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right no-image">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<h3>Referrals</h3>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating rare CNS tumors.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Treatment</h2>
<p>Your treating doctor or <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000270728&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000270728&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">neuro-oncologist</a> will use your diagnosis of your tumor to determine the best course of treatment after surgery. Treatments may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340589" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340590" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, targeted therapies or a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340591" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trial</a>.</p>
<p>Finding out you have a rare brain or spine tumor can be overwhelming and challenging for you and your loved ones. To help you find expert care and make treatment and care decisions, use the resources below. The more you learn about your <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120626" sys_contentid="1120626" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7340592" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120626" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">tumor</a>, the more confident you will feel about making the right decisions.</p>
<h2>Guiding Questions</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122214" sys_contentid="1122214" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340593" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122214" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Neurosurgeon</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122213" sys_contentid="1122213" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340594" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122213" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Their Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122212" sys_contentid="1122212" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340595" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122212" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Your Diagnosis</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122216" sys_contentid="1122216" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340596" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122216" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Support</a></li>
</ul>
<p>It is important to the success of your treatment to find a doctor that has experience treating your tumor type. And given brain and spine tumors are rare, there are few centers that have doctors with that level of expertise. Use our network of healthcare professionals to find an experienced doctor near you and get a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=18&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_contentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340597" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">second opinion</a>.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1145684" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340612">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1145698" alt="Dr. Mark Gilbert with patient" /></div>
<h3>Q&amp;A: Understanding Brain Tumor Treatment, Impact, and Research</h3>
<p>Our neuro-oncology providers share answers to important questions about brain tumor care, treatment, impact, and innovative research.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<h2>Treatment Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=60&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=14034" sys_contentid="14034" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7340598" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="14034" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Types of Cancer Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=27&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1122&amp;sys_contentid=905730" sys_contentid="905730" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="1122" sys_relationshipid="7340599" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="905730" sys_dependentvariantid="1122">Side Effects</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=102&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=63867" sys_contentid="63867" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7340600" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="63867" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Clinical Trials Information</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=27&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=15132" sys_contentid="15132" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7340601" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="15132" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Complementary and Alternative Medicine</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>Coping and Support Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120713" sys_contentid="1120713" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340602" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120713" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Coping with a Rare Brain and Spine Tumor Diagnosis</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=29&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=858130" sys_contentid="858130" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340603" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="858130" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Feelings and Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=24&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=858227" sys_contentid="858227" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340604" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="858227" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Adjusting to Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=50&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859801" sys_contentid="859801" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340605" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859801" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Support for Caregivers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Neuro-Oncology-Branch/patient-emotional-support" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Support Groups</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121673" sys_contentid="1121673" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340606" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121673" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Brain and Spine Tumor Organizations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://supportorgs.cancer.gov/default.aspx?missingsession=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Support Services Organizations</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121584" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Gliosarcoma is a primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7356074" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumor. This means it begins in the brain or spinal cord. Gliosarcoma is a rare type of glioma.</p>
<h2>What are the grades of gliosarcomas?</h2>
<p>Gliosarcomas are all classified as Grade IV tumors. This means they are malignant (cancerous) and fast-growing. They are further described as primary or secondary:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Primary</strong>: The tumor is diagnosed from the first surgery or biopsy.</li>
<li><strong>Secondary</strong>: The tumor forms from a pre-existing glioma, usually after radiation treatment.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with gliosarcomas?</h2>
<p>Gliosarcomas occur most often in people between the ages of 40 and 60, but can occur at any age. Gliosarcomas occur slightly more often in males than females.</p>
<h2>What causes gliosarcomas?</h2>
<p>The cause of most gliosarcomas is not known. Previous exposure to radiation and certain gene changes that can be passed down through families have been linked to a higher chance of developing glioblastomas.</p>
<h2>Where do gliosarcomas form?</h2>
<p>Gliosarcomas are commonly found along the surface of the brain, but can form in the spinal cord. They arise from glial cells, the supportive cells in the brain. Gliosarcomas develop with two different characteristics. Some resemble <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000269436&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000269436&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">astrocytes</a>, a star-shaped glial cell and the most abundant cell in the brain. Other gliosarcomas resemble connective tissue cells called sarcomas.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1123776" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7356095">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121582&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123776&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Gliosarcoma Statistics" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Do gliosarcomas spread?</h2>
<p>Gliosarcomas can spread to other areas of the CNS through <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046483&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebrospinal fluid</a> (CSF). Gliosarcomas generally don&rsquo;t spread outside of the CNS to other organs.</p>
<h2>What are the symptoms of gliosarcomas?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to gliosarcomas depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. People with a gliosarcoma may have headaches, seizures, thinking or memory difficulties, weakness, numbness, or problems with balance and movement.</p>
<h2>What are the treatment options for gliosarcomas?</h2>
<p>The first treatment for a gliosarcoma is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356075" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.</p>
<p>Gliosarcomas are aggressive so most people receive further treatments. Treatments may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356076" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356077" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a>, or taking part in <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7356078" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option. Treatments are decided by the patient&rsquo;s healthcare team based on the patient&rsquo;s age, remaining tumor after surgery, tumor type, and tumor location.</p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for gliosarcomas</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121711&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356096">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCI-2018-03715">Sunitinib for Patients with&nbsp;Gliosarcomas</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT03173950">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Nivolumab for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>What do gliosarcomas look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>Gliosarcomas usually appear as a single tumor with vague borders. The tumors may occur near the surface of the brain and be attached to the covering of the brain. The tumor often brightens with contrast and many tumors can occur in different areas of the CNS. Gliosarcomas usually have some swelling around them.</p>
<p></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1147892&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7356097" /></a><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121717&amp;sys_revision=22&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7356098">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121585" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Diffuse midline gliomas are primary <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=241&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1040" sys_contentid="1040" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7355982" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1040" sys_dependentvariantid="990">central nervous system</a> (CNS) tumors. This means they begin in the brain or spinal cord. Diffuse midline glioma is a rare subtype of glial tumors.&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What are the grades of diffuse midline gliomas?</h2>
<p>Diffuse midline gliomas are all Grade IV tumors. This means they are malignant (cancerous) and fast-growing.<strong> <br /></strong></p>
<h2>Who is diagnosed with diffuse midline gliomas?</h2>
<p>Diffuse midline gliomas occur in both children and adults. Diffuse midline glioma tends to occur in children. The number of men and women diagnosed with this type of cancer is equal.</p>
<h2>What causes diffuse midline gliomas?</h2>
<p>The cause of diffuse midline gliomas is not known. People with gene changes that can be passed down through families, such as <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046322&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046322&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Li-Fraumeni syndrome</a> and neurofibromatosis type I, are at increased risk for developing a diffuse midline glioma. Changes in a gene known as the h3K27M mutation, have also been linked to the growth of diffuse midline glioma.</p>
<h2>Where do diffuse midline gliomas form?</h2>
<p>Diffuse midline glioma most often forms in the <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000044515&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000044515&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">pons</a> in the brainstem, <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000044353&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000044353&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">thalamus</a>, spinal cord, and <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046714&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046714&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">cerebellum</a>.&nbsp; It&rsquo;s uncommon for these tumors to occur in other areas of the CNS. The tumors are named, in part, based on the locations where these tumors most often occur.&nbsp; Therefore, tumors in other brain or spine locations thought to be diffuse midline glioma should be reviewed by neuro-oncology providers with experience in treating people with these tumors.</p>
<p>Diffuse midline glioma is a rare type of <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045602&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045602&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">astrocytoma</a> that look similar under the microscope to other more common astrocytomas, such as a glioblastoma. Since it can be hard to tell them apart, they require molecular testing. Some diffuse midline gliomas have changes in <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000318814&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000318814&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">histone</a>-related genes, the most common is h3K27M.&nbsp; Review by a <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000318818&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000318818&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">neuropathologist</a> is recommended to confirm this diagnosis.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1123771" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7355992">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121580&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123771&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Diffuse Midline Glioma Statistics" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Do diffuse midline gliomas spread?</h2>
<p>Diffuse midline gliomas are fast-growing tumors and can spread to other areas of the CNS through cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). The tumor can invade nearby tissue and extend beyond what can be seen on MRI or by the surgeon during surgery. Diffuse midline glioma, however, usually grow and come back in the same location in which they first appeared.</p>
<h2>What are the symptoms of diffuse midline gliomas?</h2>
<p>Symptoms related to diffuse midline glioma depend on the tumor&rsquo;s location. People may have double vision, problems swallowing, weakness on one or both sides of the body, or loss of balance.&nbsp; Diffuse midline glioma in the brain also may cause increased pressure within the skull due to production of too much CSF or blockage of its normal flow, known as hydrocephalus. Signs and symptoms of hydrocephalus may include nausea, vomiting, irritability, headaches, blurred or double vision, a strong desire to sleep, and seizures. People with a diffuse midline glioma in the spine may have progressive weakness, numbness, and problems with bowel and bladder control.</p>
<h2><strong>What are the treatment options for diffuse midline gliomas?</strong></h2>
<p>The first treatment for diffuse midline glioma is <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_contentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355983" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">surgery</a>, if possible. The goal of surgery is to obtain tissue to determine the tumor type and to remove as much tumor as possible without causing more symptoms for the person.&nbsp; The brainstem, thalamus, and spinal cord are sensitive locations in the CNS and surgery in these areas can cause serious loss of function. Diffuse midline glioma may sometimes be treated with radiation therapy alone without a biopsy if the risk of biopsy is thought to be too high.&nbsp; A procedure such as a ventriculoperitoneal shunt, may also be needed to redirect the flow of cerebrospinal fluid if the patient has hydrocephalus.</p>
<p>Diffuse midline gliomas usually require further treatments. Treatments may include <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=114&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912885" sys_contentid="912885" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355984" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912885" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">radiation</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912839" sys_contentid="912839" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355985" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="912839" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">chemotherapy</a><u>,</u> or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7355986" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a>. Surgery is followed by radiation therapy in most cases.&nbsp; Chemotherapy is sometimes given with radiation therapy, or after radiation.&nbsp; However, there is no standard chemotherapy regimen, and each plan should be tailored to each patient.&nbsp; Review of diffuse midline glioma by a team of experts including neuro-oncologists, neuroradiologists, radiation oncologists, and neurosurgeons is important to determine the best treatment plan.&nbsp; Clinical trials, with new chemotherapy, targeted therapy, or immunotherapy drugs, may also be available and can be a possible treatment option.</p>
<p></p>
<h4>Open clinical studies for diffuse midline gliomas</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121711&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7355993">Outcomes and Risk Project for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT02851706">Evaluation of the Natural History and Specimen Banking for Patients with CNS Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/NCT03173950">Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor Nivolumab for Patients with Rare CNS Cancers</a></li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<h2>What do diffuse midline gliomas look like on an MRI?</h2>
<p>Diffuse midline gliomas usually appear as a mass that has spread in the middle area of the brain. The tumor shows degrees of brightness with contrast. In adults, the diagnosis of diffuse middling glioma can&rsquo;t be made by imaging alone because the tumors look similar to glioblastomas and other high-grade brain cancers.</p>
<p></p>
<h2 id="ui-id-3"><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals" title=""><img src="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1147892&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="1147892" inlinetype="rximage" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" style="float: left;" sys_relationshipid="7355994" /></a><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1121717&amp;sys_revision=22&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7355995">Referrals</a></h2>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating this tumor.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121673" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Find support and connect with others impacted by a brain or spinal cord tumor by using the following resources.</p>
<h3><a href="http://www.abta.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">American Brain Tumor Association</a></h3>
<p>The mission of the American Brain Tumor Association (ABTA) is to advance the understanding and treatment of brain tumors with the goals of improving, extending and, ultimately, saving the lives of those impacted by a brain tumor diagnosis. They do this through interactions and engagements with brain tumor patients and their families, collaborations with allied groups and organizations, and the funding of brain tumor research.</p>
<p><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1135595&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=2056&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2056" sys_dependentid="1135595" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7340641">Learn more about this organization &gt;</a></p>
<h3><a href="http://www.cern-foundation.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Collaborative Ependymoma Research Network (CERN) Foundation</a></h3>
<p>The CERN Foundation is committed to improving the care and outcome of people with ependymoma through community support and research efforts. The CERN website is dedicated to informing patients and caregivers about treatment, diagnosis, clinical trials, symptom management, and recurrence. It is a valuable resource for those affected by ependymoma, including patient stories.</p>
<p><span><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1139372&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=2056&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2056" sys_dependentid="1139372" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7340642">Learn more about this organization &gt;</a></span></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2392" sys_dependentid="1121675" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340643">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right no-image">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<h3>Partnerships</h3>
<p>NCI-CONNECT wants to partner with non-profit organizations to engage patients through awareness and education.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h3><a href="https://endbraincancer.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The EndBrainCancer Initiative</a></h3>
<p><span>The EndBrainCancer Initiative is enhancing patient outcomes by expanding FDA-approved treatment modalities and fueling research in the pharma/bio/life sciences, device and diagnostic industries and by closing the existing gap from initial diagnosis to immediate and expanded access to specialists, researchers, advanced and innovative treatments, clinical trials and critical care with the ultimate goal of improving patient outcomes through updating and improving WHO and NCCN Guidelines and clinical practices related to standard of care for brain cancer patients.</span></p>
<h3><a href="https://theibta.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">International Brain Tumour Alliance</a></h3>
<p>The International Brain Tumour Alliance (IBTA) brings together experience and expertise from all over the world with the aim of enhancing the well-being and quality of life of brain tumor patients and their families.</p>
<p><span><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1124058&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=2056&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2056" sys_dependentid="1124058" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7340644">Learn more about this organization &gt;</a></span></p>
<h3><a href="http://www.braintumor.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Brain Tumor Society</a></h3>
<p>The National Brain Tumor Society (NBTS) brings together the best in brain tumor research and supportive patient services. They offer hope to patients, families, and caregivers during every stage of the treatment journey. NBTS invests wisely and strategically in innovative research that will lead to advances and ultimately a cure for people living with a brain tumor.</p>
<p><span><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1142911&amp;sys_revision=6&amp;sys_variantid=2056&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2056" sys_dependentid="1142911" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7340645">Learn more about this organization &gt;</a></span></p>
<h3><a href="https://www.oligonation.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Oligo Nation&nbsp;</a></h3>
<p><span>Oligo Nation is driven by the urgent need for new treatments</span><span>. There hasn&rsquo;t been a new treatment approved for Oligo in 20 years. Oligo Nation&nbsp;works with and support families that want to overcome this disease and&nbsp;raises money for medical research.</span></p>
<p><span><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1124068&amp;sys_revision=7&amp;sys_variantid=2056&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2056" sys_dependentid="1124068" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7340646">Learn more about this organization &gt;</a></span></p>
<p><em>NCI-CONNECT is not responsible for the content on these sites.</em></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121675" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>NCI-CONNECT aims to partner with non-profit organizations who share a common concern for improving the outcomes of patients with rare adult central nervous system (CNS) tumors through awareness and education.</p>
<h2>What does it mean to be a NCI-CONNECT partner?</h2>
<p>Partners are non-profit groups who work with NCI-CONNECT to identify and engage patients with select rare adult CNS tumors by disseminating information about <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340411" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a> and new approaches to improve care and <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121723" sys_contentid="1121723" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340412" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121723" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">treatment</a>.</p>
<h2 style="clear: both;">Why partner with NCI-CONNECT?</h2>
<div sys_relationshipid="7340415" sys_dependentid="1124058" rxinlineslot="105" contenteditable="false" sys_dependentvariantid="2388" rxselectedtext="" rxanchortext="" unselectable="on" inlinetype="rxvariant" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
	<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
		<a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2301&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1124058&amp;sys_command=preview" sys_variantid="2301" sys_contentid="1124058">
							    				<div class="image-hover">
    					<img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123941&amp;sys_command=preview" alt="Kathy Oliver">
    				</div>
				    		    		    			<h3>Caregiver Becomes Advocate</h3>
    					        		        			<p>A brain tumor caregiver shares how her journey supporting her son led to an international brain tumor organization. </p>
        							</a>
    </div>
	</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<p>All primary CNS cancers are rare cancers. They account for less than 2% of all cancers diagnosed a year in the United States. NCI-CONNECT is focusing on <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120626" sys_contentid="1120626" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7340413" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120626" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">12 types</a>, each with less than 2,000 people diagnosed a year.</p>
<p>The low incident rates of these CNS cancers mean patients and researchers face unique challenges. Patients struggle to find expert care and treatments. The cancer research community struggles to identify a sufficient number of patients to conduct meaningful research.</p>
<p>NCI-CONNECT seeks to address these challenges and unmet needs by connecting patients, providers, and advocates. A collaborative network with a harmonized mission can have a great impact on the progress of clinical care and research for the lives of people with brain and spine tumors and their families.</p>
<h2>Ready to join us?</h2>
<p><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121708" sys_contentid="1121708" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340414" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121708" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Sign up to be an NCI-CONNECT partner.</a></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121708" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>A key component of NCI-CONNECT is to develop <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121675" sys_contentid="1121675" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121675" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7170916">partnerships</a> with non-profit organizations whose mission is to advance the understanding and enhance the well-being of adults with <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120626" sys_contentid="1120626" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120626" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7170917">selected rare central nervous system (CNS) tumors</a>.</p>
<p><strong>NCI-CONNECT aims to: &nbsp;</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Engage with patients with selected rare CNS tumors.</li>
<li>Disseminate information about <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7170918">clinical trials</a> to enhance enrollment and information about treatment options.</li>
<li>Educate patients and <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_contentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121717" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7170919">providers</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>A partner organization should:&nbsp;</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Certify it is a non-profit organization.</li>
<li>Have goals that relate to education, awareness, or support for patients with rare CNS tumors.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Expectations</h2>
<p><strong>A partner organization will:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Provide its community information provided by NCI-CONNECT.</li>
<li>Link to NCI-CONNECT information from its website, newsletter, and social media accounts.</li>
<li>Share NCI-CONNECT <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7170920">clinical trials</a>, <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2054&amp;sys_contentid=1121159" sys_contentid="1121159" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2054" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121159" sys_variantid="2054" sys_relationshipid="7170921">publications</a>, and <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120671" sys_contentid="1120671" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120671" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7170922">educational information</a> with its community.</li>
<li>Effectively communicate with NCI-CONNECT.</li>
<li>Be a collaborative and collegial member of the NCI-CONNECT partnership network.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>NCI-CONNECT will:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Provide all necessary information, tools, and resources.</li>
<li>Provide access to its research and clinical experts.</li>
<li>Invite partners to its educational workshops.</li>
<li>Provide partners a NCI-CONNECT membership badge.</li>
<li>Effectively communicate with partners.</li>
<li>Be a collaborative and collegial partner. &nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<h2>Current NCI-CONNECT Partners</h2>
<p>NCI-CONNECT is proud to partner with the following non-profit brain and spine tumor organizations who are committed to raising awareness and educating patients with rare adult CNS tumors.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2066" sys_dependentid="1123816" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7170925">
<figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1124032&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123816&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Partnerships" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.abta.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">American Brain Tumor Association (ABTA)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.cern-foundation.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Collaborative Ependymoma Research Network (CERN) Foundation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://endbraincancer.org/  " target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The EndBrainCancer Initiative (EBCI)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://theibta.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">International Brain Tumour Alliance (IBTA)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://braintumor.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Brain Tumor Society (NBTS)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.oligonation.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Oligo Nation</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>Ready to be our partner?&nbsp;</h2>
<p>Sign up to partner with NCI-CONNECT by <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=955&amp;sys_contentid=1123946" sys_contentid="1123946" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="955" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1123946" sys_variantid="955" sys_relationshipid="7170924">downloading our partner application</a> (pdf). Send your completed application &nbsp;to <a href="mailto:NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov">NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov</a>.</p>
<h2>Want more information?</h2>
<p>Contact us at <a href="mailto:NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov">NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov</a> or 240-760-6530.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121711" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The project intends to answer the one question that plagues most all patients: Why did this happen to me?</p>
<p>We are expanding the work of our successful Ependymoma Outcomes Surveys to improve our understanding of <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045873&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045873&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">risk factors</a> associated with the occurrence of rare central nervous system (CNS) tumors. Research has shown that certain risk factors may increase a person&rsquo;s chances of developing cancer. Factors can include exposure to chemicals or other substances, personal and family medical history.</p>
<p>If you take part in this study, we will ask you to complete an online survey and submit a saliva sample that will be used for genetic testing to evaluate for risk factors. The Rare CNS tumors Outcomes and Risk Study is designed for adults diagnosed with <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120626" sys_contentid="1120626" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1120626" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7315897" sys_variantid="2317">rare CNS tumors</a>. We designed the instructions for participation to be as simple and straightforward as possible.</p>
<p>Efforts such as this would not be possible without the selfless contributions of patients like you.</p>
<h2>To Participate In the Risk Study</h2>
<ol>
<li>Enroll by filling out the <a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/rcnsregform" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rare CNS Tumors Outcomes and Risk Enrollment Form</a>.</li>
<li>You will be sent a consent form through a secure email. The project coordinator will set up a time with you to go over the consent information over the phone after you have had an opportunity to read the form.</li>
<li>Once you complete the consent form and send it back to the coordinator, you will be contacted with instructions to complete the Rare CNS Tumors Outcomes Survey and once completed, the Rare CNS Tumors Risk survey. You will be provided a unique identifying number which you will use to complete the study.</li>
<li>Once the surveys are completed, you will be mailed a copy of your signed consent form for your files and a kit to collect saliva for germline DNA. Germline DNA is the source of DNA for all other cells in the body. Your blood and tissue samples contain genes, which are made up of DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid) which serves as the "instruction book" for the cells that make up our bodies. Sequencing genome will determine the exact order of the base pairs (chemical letters) in your blood. Your sample(s) and survey responses will help us study how genes and suspected risk factors are associated with the occurrence of rare CNS tumors. Instructions on how to collect the sample and a self- addressed postage-paid padded envelope will be provided for you to return the sample back to us.</li>
<li>Aggregate results of the survey will be shared (anonymously on the NCI-CONNECT website and shared with our advocacy partners) when completed and by publication in peer-reviewed journals.</li>
</ol>
<p>Please note: internet access is required for enrollment on the study and completion of all data collection forms. The Enrollment Form, the Rare CNS Tumors Risk Survey and the Rare CNS Tumors Outcomes Survey are housed at a separate and secured website called surveymonkey.com. By clicking on either enrollment forms, you will be directed to this secure third-party site.</p>
<h2>Rare CNS Tumors Outcomes and Risk Form Descriptions</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/rcnsregform" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Enrollment Form:</a>&nbsp;</strong>brief survey designed to capture demographic data. Completion time is approximately five to 10 minutes.</li>
<li><strong>Rare CNS Tumors Risk Survey:</strong> The survey will be completed only once by you or with the help of a proxy if physical limitations prevent you from completing the online forms via SurveyMonkey. Questions include demographic information, <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000642019&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000642019&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">personal medical history</a>, family medical history and environmental exposures. This should take about 52 minutes. If you have any questions about this process, please contact Alvina Acquaye at 240-760-6430.</li>
<li><strong>Rare CNS Tumors Outcomes Survey:</strong> The survey will be completed in addition to the Risk Project survey. The survey takes about 25-35 minutes to complete and covers your treatment history, symptoms, social and clinical information.</li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121717" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p style="text-align: left;">The&nbsp;diagnosis of a rare brain or spinal cord tumor can be overwhelming and patients may feel it is urgent to get started with their care. Patients are encouraged to seek a second opinion for care and treatment options from a doctor who has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122213" sys_contentid="1122213" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7362201" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122213" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">experience treating their brain or spine tumor</a>.</p>
<p>The NCI&rsquo;s Center for Cancer Research,&nbsp;<a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Neuro-Oncology-Branch" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Neuro-Oncology Branch</a> at NIH in Bethesda, Maryland, has doctors and nurses with extensive experience treating rare brain and spinal cord tumors. Patients can visit our Neuro-Oncology Branch Clinic for an evaluation or consultation with our <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Neuro-Oncology-Branch/staff-directory" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">healthcare providers</a>. Consultations for patients with rare brain and spine tumors are free-of-charge.</p>
<p>Our Neuro-Oncology Branch healthcare team provides patients with a comprehensive care plan that, together with their physician at home, will ensure they get the best treatment possible.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1123827" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7362208">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1121155&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1122363&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Mark Gilbert" /></div>
<h3>Provider Connects to Improve Care</h3>
<p>Neuro-oncologist Dr. Mark Gilbert shares how he is connecting healthcare providers to improve care and treatment.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Referral Information</h2>
<p style="text-align: left;">To make an appointment or refer a patient, contact us at:</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong><a href="mailto:NCINOBReferrals@mail.nih.gov?subject=NOB%20Referral">NCINOBReferrals@mail.nih.gov</a> or call 1-866-251-9686&nbsp;or 240-760-6010&nbsp; </strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">(Monday to Friday, 9:00 a.m.&ndash;5:00&nbsp;p.m. ET)</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We request that&nbsp;the patient or family member contact us directly to facilitate the&nbsp;consent process for the visit.&nbsp;Please do not send medical records when requesting an appointment. Our patient care coordinators will provide instructions. &nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Candidates with one of <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120626" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1120626" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7362203" sys_variantid="2317" sys_contentid="1120626">these rare CNS tumors</a> should&nbsp;participate if:</p>
<ul>
<li style="text-align: left;">they are newly diagnosed or have a recurrence and need to make&nbsp;a treatment decision</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">they are interested in a second opinion on follow-up care</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">they are interested in improving their care and the care of&nbsp;future patients</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>What are the costs? </strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Consultations are free-of-charge.</li>
<li>Treatments, tests and other services at NIH are also free after a patient is accepted on study.</li>
<li>NIH does not cover expenses for medical services at other facilities.</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>What items are needed for a consultation? </strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>All available MRI and CT scans related to the brain or spine tumor diagnosis and corresponding radiology reports. Most recent MRI should be within 30 days of the appointment.</li>
<li>Pathology material from the most recent surgery (including biopsies) sent in advance of the appointment. Receiving this material is critical to schedule the appointment. Appointments can be scheduled as early as two weeks after the pathology material is received.&nbsp;</li>
<li>Most recent progress note from the patient&rsquo;s treating physician. Other records, including surgery, radiation, and treatment summaries may be requested to determine trial eligibility.</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Additional Information for International Patients</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>NIH requires that the local treating physician refers the patient for an appointment, so we can work together to ensure they get the best treatment possible.</li>
<li>If the original medical records are not in English, NIH will need additional time to process those records to schedule the appointment.</li>
<li>Travel assistance may be available once the patient arrives at the United States. Please contact us for more information.</li>
<li>The patient may need a visa and/or travel authorization to visit the United States for their first appointment and any follow-up appointments.
<ol>
<li>Visas and travel authorizations are issued by the United States Consulate or Embassy in <a href="http://www.usembassy.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">their country of origin</a>.</li>
<li>Review the <a href="http://www.cc.nih.gov/participate/patientinfo/visa.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NIH patient visa and immigration information</a>.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=955&amp;sys_contentid=1140155" sys_dependentvariantid="955" sys_dependentid="1140155" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7362205" sys_variantid="955" sys_contentid="1140155">View or download the referral flyer</a></strong></p>
<p>Patients referred to the NIH will have the option to participate in a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7362202" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trial</a> at NCI or a Brain Tumor Trials Collaborative (BTTC) center. <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/neuro-oncology-branch/bttc/doctors-institutions" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The BTTC</a> is a network of renowned medical centers throughout the United States that works with NCI-CONNECT to provide clinical studies to patients with rare CNS tumors. This allows patients to access cutting-edge therapies at a center closer to their home.</p>
<p>If patients cannot travel for an appointment, they can still participate in our online <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121711" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7362206" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121711">Outcomes and Risk Study</a> from home. Participating will help advance our knowledge of rare brain and spine tumors.</p>
<h2>NCI-CONNECT Clinic</h2>
<p><span>The</span><strong><span>&nbsp;</span></strong>NCI-CONNECT Clinic<span>&nbsp;brings together adult patients with the same rare brain or spine tumor and their caregivers to receive special services. <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1147238" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1147238" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7362204" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1147238">Learn more about joining the clinic and the services offered</a>.</span></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121723" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Treatment for your brain or spine tumor will depend on your tumor type and location, and your general health.</p>
<h2>Surgery</h2>
<p>If possible, you will have surgery to treat brain or spine tumors and help relieve symptoms. Surgery removes as much of the tumor as possible while not damaging healthy tissue. It is most successful when performed by a neurosurgeon with expertise treating your tumor type. Your neuro-oncologist and <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120671" sys_contentid="1120671" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282344" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120671" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">healthcare team</a> will work with you and your loved ones to create a treatment plan just for you and help coordinate your care.</p>
<p>If you have a brain or spine tumor, you should be under the care of a neuro-oncologist. A neuro-oncologist is specially trained to treat patients with central nervous system (CNS) tumors. If you are being seen by an oncologist or primary care doctor, ask for a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=12&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_contentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282345" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">referral</a> to a neuro-oncologist for a second opinion or for treatment.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7282366">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1123728&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123799&amp;sys_command=edit" /></div>
<h3>Outcomes and Risk Study</h3>
<p>Help us improve care for patients with rare CNS tumors by participating in an online survey. The survey will ask you questions about your symptoms, treatments, and quality of life during and after cancer.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Further Treatment</h2>
<p>After surgery or if you don&rsquo;t have surgery, you may have other treatments depending on your <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120671" sys_contentid="1120671" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282346" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120671" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">tumor type and grade</a>. Low grade tumors (grade I and II) may be completely removed with surgery but may require radiation and/or chemotherapy. High grade tumors (grade III and IV) are more difficult to remove and require additional treatments such as radiation and/or chemotherapy. You may also choose to join a clinical trial to test new treatments.</p>
<p>Clinical trials are research studies that involve people. Clinical trials provide doctors the opportunity to learn about new therapies that could be successful to treat your tumor. NCI-CONNECT has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=13&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282347" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trials</a> you can take part in at the <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Neuro-Oncology-Branch?qt-nob_quicktabs=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NIH</a>.</p>
<p>During treatment you may have physical or cognitive changes that greatly affect your quality of life.&nbsp;This can be challenging for you and your loved ones. Keep a dairy of your treatment symptoms and talk to your doctor about them. Your doctor may change your treatment plan so you can continue to live fully.</p>
<p>We understand making treatment decisions can be overwhelming and symptoms and side effects can take a toll on both your body and your feelings. Use these resources to help you make the best decisions for your care, treatment, and quality of life.</p>
<h2>Guiding Questions</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2392" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7282367">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right no-image">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<h3>Referrals</h3>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating rare CNS tumors.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122218" sys_contentid="1122218" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282348" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122218" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Your Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122211" sys_contentid="1122211" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282349" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122211" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Clinical Trials</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122216" sys_contentid="1122216" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282350" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122216" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Support</a></li>
</ul>
<p>It is important to the success of your treatment to find a doctor that has experience treating your tumor type. And given brain and spine tumors are rare, there are few centers that have doctors with that level of expertise. Use our network of healthcare professionals to find an experienced doctor near you and get a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=12&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_contentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282351" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">second opinion</a>.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1135595" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7282368">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Ralph DeVitto" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1135594&amp;sys_command=edit" /></div>
<h3>Brain Tumor Patient Education and Support</h3>
<p>Read how the first national advocacy organization for brain tumor education and information is expanding its services and collaborating to improve care and treatment.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Treatment Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1090830" sys_contentid="1090830" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7282352" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1090830" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Types of Cancer Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=27&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1122&amp;sys_contentid=905730" sys_contentid="905730" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="1122" sys_relationshipid="7282353" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="905730" sys_dependentvariantid="1122">Side Effects</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=102&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=63867" sys_contentid="63867" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7282354" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="63867" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Clinical Trials Information</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=27&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=15132" sys_contentid="15132" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7282355" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="15132" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Complementary and Alternative Medicine</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>Coping and Support Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120713" sys_contentid="1120713" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282356" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120713" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Coping with a Rare Brain and Spine Tumor Diagnosis</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=29&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=858130" sys_contentid="858130" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282357" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="858130" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Feelings and Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=23&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=858227" sys_contentid="858227" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282358" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="858227" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Adjusting to Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=35&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859577" sys_contentid="859577" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282359" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859577" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Self-Image &amp; Sexuality</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=10&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859583" sys_contentid="859583" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282360" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859583" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Day-to-Day Life</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=50&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859801" sys_contentid="859801" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282361" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859801" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Support for Caregivers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Neuro-Oncology-Branch/patient-emotional-support" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Support Groups</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121673" sys_contentid="1121673" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282362" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121673" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Brain and Spine Tumor Organizations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://supportorgs.cancer.gov/home.aspx?js=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Support Services Organizations</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121725" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>A recurrence is when your tumor begins to grow or has come back. Even when treatment has finished, there is always a chance the tumor will recur. It is not possible for your doctor to know if or when your tumor will recur. Tumors often come back in the same spot as the original tumor. But it is possible for a brain and spine tumor to return in another location in the central nervous system (CNS).</p>
<h2>Symptoms</h2>
<p>Signs and symptoms of a recurrent brain or spine tumor are often the <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121295" sys_contentid="1121295" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340614" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121295" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">same symptoms</a> you had before, but can feel more pronounced. If you have worsening of your symptoms or new symptoms, it is important to talk to your <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120671" sys_contentid="1120671" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340615" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120671" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">healthcare team</a>.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340636">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1123728&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123799&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /></div>
<h3>Outcomes and Risk Study</h3>
<p>Help us improve care for patients with rare CNS tumors by participating in an online survey. The survey will ask you questions about your symptoms, treatments, and quality of life during and after cancer.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Follow-up Care</h2>
<p>It is important to continue to be monitored by a neuro-oncologist after you complete treatment. Monitoring may include physical and neurologic exams and imaging of your brain or spine. By being monitored, your doctor will be able to detect a recurrent tumor and start treatment. Your treatment may include chemotherapy or you may join a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_contentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340617" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">clinical trial</a> to test a new treatment.</p>
<h2>Feelings</h2>
<p>Finding out that your tumor has recurred can cause feelings of shock, anger, sadness, and fear. But this time you have something that you didn&rsquo;t have before - experience. You&rsquo;ve lived through cancer already and you know what to expect. Treatments also may have improved since you were first diagnosed. New drugs or therapies may be more successful and help with your treatment or in managing side effects.</p>
<p>We understand that facing a recurrence can be scary and challenging for you and your family. Use these resources to help guide your treatment decisions, find support, and inspire you through another cancer journey.</p>
<h2>Guiding Questions</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2392" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340637">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right no-image">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<h3>Referrals</h3>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating rare CNS tumors.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122215" sys_contentid="1122215" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340619" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122215" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor or Surgeon if You Have a Recurrence</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122214" sys_contentid="1122214" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340620" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122214" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Neurosurgeon</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122218" sys_contentid="1122218" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340621" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122218" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Your Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122211" sys_contentid="1122211" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340622" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122211" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Clinical Trials</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122216" sys_contentid="1122216" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340623" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122216" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Support</a></li>
</ul>
<p>It is important to the success of your treatment to find a doctor that has experience treating your tumor type. Given brain and spine tumors are rare, there are few centers that have doctors with that level of expertise. Use our network of healthcare professionals to find an experienced doctor near you and get a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=18&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_contentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340624" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">second opinion</a>.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1142911" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340638">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1142908" alt="David Arons" /></div>
<h3>National Non-profit Unites and Empowers the Brain Tumor Community</h3>
<p>Read how a national advocacy organization has helped unify and mobilize a community to advance care and knowledge for brain tumor patients and their families.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2>Treatment Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=60&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=14034" sys_contentid="14034" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7340625" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="14034" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Types of Cancer Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=27&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1122&amp;sys_contentid=905730" sys_contentid="905730" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="1122" sys_relationshipid="7340626" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="905730" sys_dependentvariantid="1122">Side Effects</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=102&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=63867" sys_contentid="63867" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7340627" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="63867" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Clinical Trials Information</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=27&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=15132" sys_contentid="15132" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7340628" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="15132" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Complementary and Alternative Medicine</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>Coping and Support Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120713" sys_contentid="1120713" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340629" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120713" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Coping with a Rare Brain and Spine Tumor Diagnosis</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=29&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=858130" sys_contentid="858130" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340630" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="858130" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Feelings and Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=24&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=858227" sys_contentid="858227" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340631" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="858227" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Adjusting to Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=36&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859577" sys_contentid="859577" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340632" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859577" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Self-Image &amp; Sexuality</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=10&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859583" sys_contentid="859583" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340633" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859583" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Day-to-Day Life</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=50&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859801" sys_contentid="859801" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340634" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859801" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Support for Caregivers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Neuro-Oncology-Branch/patient-emotional-support" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Support Groups</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121673" sys_contentid="1121673" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7340635" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121673" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Brain and Spine Tumor Organizations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://supportorgs.cancer.gov/home.aspx?js=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Support Services Organizations</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1121726" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>When you have completed cancer treatment, ask your doctor for a summary of your care and a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=26&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859665" sys_contentid="859665" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282981" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859665" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">follow-up care</a> plan. Your doctor may refer to this plan as your survivorship care plan.</p>
<h2>Survivorship Care Plan</h2>
<p>Your survivorship care plan should include how often you have follow-up visits and diagnostic tests. At these visits, your healthcare team will examine you, ask you questions about your health, and take a MRI or CT scan. Your healthcare team is watching for any changes for signs that your tumor has come back. They will also help you manage any treatment side effects.</p>
<p>A rare brain or spine tumor can continue to impact your life even after your treatment ends. You may be adjusting to a new normal or living with physical and cognitive changes. You may also constantly fear your tumor will return. Living with worries and anxieties can be challenging for you and your loved ones. We understand and have developed the following resources to help you transition to a new normal.</p>
<div sys_relationshipid="7282982" sys_dependentid="1121711" rxinlineslot="105" contenteditable="false" sys_dependentvariantid="2388" rxselectedtext="" rxanchortext="" unselectable="on" inlinetype="rxvariant" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
	<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
		<a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1123728&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1121711&amp;sys_command=preview" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121711">
							    				<div class="image-hover">
    					<img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1123728&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123799&amp;sys_command=preview" alt="">
    				</div>
				    		    		    			<h3>Outcomes and Risk Study</h3>
    					        		        			<p>Help us improve care for patients with rare CNS tumors by participating in an online survey. The survey will ask you questions about your symptoms, treatments, and quality of life during and after cancer.</p>
        							</a>
    </div>
	</div>
</div>
<h2>Guiding Questions</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122217" sys_contentid="1122217" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282983" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122217" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor When Treatment Ends</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122216" sys_contentid="1122216" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282984" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1122216" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Support</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>Coping and Support Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=35&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859577" sys_contentid="859577" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282985" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859577" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Self-Image &amp; Sexuality</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=10&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859583" sys_contentid="859583" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282986" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859583" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Day-to-Day Life</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=17&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859637" sys_contentid="859637" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282987" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859637" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">A New Normal</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=26&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859665" sys_contentid="859665" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282988" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859665" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Follow-Up Medical Care</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=34&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859757" sys_contentid="859757" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282989" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859757" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Late Side Effects</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859781" sys_contentid="859781" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282990" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859781" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Family Issues</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Neuro-Oncology-Branch/patient-emotional-support" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Support Groups</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121673" sys_contentid="1121673" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7282991" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121673" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Brain and Spine Tumor Organizations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://supportorgs.cancer.gov/home.aspx?js=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Support Services Organizations</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1122211" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7109341">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<h3>Clinical Studies</h3>
<p>NCI-CONNECT has studies available that focus on rare central nervous system tumors.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Here are some questions to ask your doctor to help you determine if a clinical trial is right for you.</p>
<ul>
<li>What is the purpose of the trial?</li>
<li>What phase is the clinical trial?</li>
<li>Why would the clinical trial treatment be better than treatment being used now?</li>
<li>How long do I have to decide whether I want to participate in a clinical trial?</li>
<li>How does the clinical trial treatment work to treat my brain or spine tumor?</li>
<li>What are the criteria used to determine if I am eligible for the trial?</li>
<li>How do you evaluate if the treatment is working?</li>
<li>How often would I need to have <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046361&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046361&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">imaging</a> or MRIs?</li>
<li>How long is the treatment given?</li>
<li>How will I be informed of the results?</li>
<li>If the treatment isn&rsquo;t work, can I stop the trial?</li>
<li>Can I stop participating in the trial at any point I choose?</li>
<li>What procedures are required as part of the clinical trial?</li>
<li>If the clinical trial is a <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000651195&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000651195&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">drug therapy</a>, how is the drug given (pills or IV)?</li>
<li>How often do I have to be seen in the clinic or hospital as part of the trial?</li>
<li>Can I be part of the clinical trial at a location closer to my home?</li>
<li>What are the known <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046580&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046580&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">side effects</a>?</li>
<li>How are side effects managed?</li>
<li>Are there other health risks with participating in the trial?</li>
<li>How could the trial affect my daily life?</li>
<li>What are the costs to me for participating on this trial?</li>
</ul>
<p>We encourage you to print these questions and bring them with you to your appointment.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1122212" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Here are questions to ask about your brain or spine tumor.</p>
<ul>
<li>What is the exact type and <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000774694&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000774694&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">grade</a> of my tumor?</li>
<li>How accurate is my diagnosis?</li>
<li>Did you perform <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045671&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045671&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">DNA</a> or <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046128&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046128&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">genetic testing</a> or will you be? How long will this take?</li>
<li>What is the location of my tumor?</li>
<li>What is the size of my tumor?</li>
<li>Can my tumor spread to other areas of the <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046481&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046481&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">central nervous system</a> (CNS)?</li>
<li>Can my tumor spread outside of the CNS?</li>
<li>What is the success rate for controlling this tumor?</li>
<li>Will I need more tests before treatment begins? If so, which ones?</li>
<li>Do you know what caused this tumor?</li>
<li>Do I need to be concerned about my children&rsquo;s risk for developing this tumor?</li>
<li>Will I need a specialist(s) for my treatment? If so, who would you recommend?</li>
</ul>
<p>We encourage you to print these questions and bring them with you to your appointment.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1122213" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7122559">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1120719&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1123924" alt="Nurses and doctors in the clinic" /></div>
<h3>Referrals</h3>
<p>Find doctors and nurses with experience treating rare CNS tumors.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>These questions can help you decide if a&nbsp;doctor is the right one for you.</p>
<ul>
<li>How much experience do you have caring for people who have brain or spine tumors?</li>
<li>How many brain or spine tumor patients do you treat each year?</li>
<li>How many patients have you treated with my specific diagnosis?</li>
<li>How many years have you treated brain or spine tumor patients?</li>
<li>What is your specialty?</li>
<li>What are your credentials?</li>
<li>Did you participate in a fellowship or specialized training in neuro-oncology?</li>
<li>Are you board-certified?</li>
<li>Do you have any additional certifications?</li>
</ul>
<p>We encourage you to print these questions and bring them with you to your appointment.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1122214" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Here are some questions to ask your <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046269&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046269&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">neurosurgeon</a>. These questions can help you decide if <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=36&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7095838" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="912891">surgery</a> is the best treatment option for you, prepare for surgery, and make sure you&rsquo;re receiving the best possible care.</p>
<ul>
<li>Why do I need surgery?</li>
<li>What is your experience in doing this surgery?</li>
<li>Have you performed surgery on someone with my tumor type before?</li>
<li>If so, how many patients with my tumor type do you perform surgery on each year?</li>
<li>How soon do I need to have surgery?</li>
<li>What are the possible risks of surgery?</li>
<li>What are the benefits of surgery?</li>
<li>Should I get a second opinion?</li>
<li>What other specialists will be a part of my surgical team&nbsp;(anesthesiologist, surgical tech, resident, fellow, primary surgeon or secondary surgeon)?</li>
<li>What other specialists will be part of my team after surgery (neuro-oncologist, medical oncologist, radiation oncologist, advanced practice nurse, nurse navigator, pharmacist, speech therapist, neuropsychologist, social worker, nutritionist, physical therapist)?</li>
<li>How long will the surgery take?</li>
<li>What do I need to do to prepare for surgery (changes in medications, diet, or activity)?</li>
</ul>
<p>We encourage you to print these questions and bring them with you to your appointment.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1122215" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri, sans-serif; font-size: 14.666666984558105px; font-style: normal; font-variant-caps: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; orphans: auto; text-align: start; text-indent: 0px; text-transform: none; white-space: normal; widows: auto; word-spacing: 0px; -webkit-text-size-adjust: auto; -webkit-text-stroke-width: 0px; display: inline !important; float: none;">When your rare brain or spine tumor comes back or begins to grow after treatment, your doctor calls it a recurrence. </span><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri, sans-serif; font-size: 14.666666984558105px; font-style: normal; font-variant-caps: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; orphans: auto; text-align: start; text-indent: 0px; text-transform: none; white-space: normal; widows: auto; word-spacing: 0px; -webkit-text-size-adjust: auto; -webkit-text-stroke-width: 0px; display: inline !important; float: none;">Use these questions to determine the best treatment for a recurrence.</span>
<h2>Ask Your Neuro-oncologist</h2>
<p>Here are some questions to ask your neuro-oncologist to help you determine the best treatment for you.</p>
<ul>
<li>What <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1122218" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1122218" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7235256" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1122218">treatments</a> do I need?</li>
<li>How do I need to do to prepare for treatments (changes in medications, diet, activity)?</li>
<li>Do I need <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=37&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=912891" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="912891" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7235254" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="912891">surgery</a>? If so, what do I need to do to prepare for surgery?</li>
<li>Are there other <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1090830" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1090830" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7235255" sys_variantid="2317" sys_contentid="1090830">treatment options</a> or clinical trials available?</li>
<li>Should I get a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7235252" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121717">second opinion</a>?</li>
</ul>
<h2>Ask Your Neurosurgeon</h2>
<p>Here are some questions to ask your <a href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046269&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">neurosurgeon</a> to help you decide if surgery is the best treatment option to remove your brain or spine tumor, prepare you for surgery, and ensure you are receiving the best possible care.</p>
<ul>
<li>Why do I need surgery?</li>
<li>What is your experience in doing this surgery?</li>
<li>Have you performed surgery on someone with my tumor type before?</li>
<li>If so, how many patients with my tumor type do you treat each year?</li>
<li>How soon do I need to have surgery?</li>
<li>What are the possible risks and complications of having surgery?</li>
<li>What are the benefits of surgery?</li>
<li>Should I get a second opinion?</li>
<li>What other specialists will be a part of my surgical team (anesthesiologist, surgical tech, resident, fellow, primary surgeon or secondary surgeon)?</li>
<li>What other specialists will be a part of my <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120671" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120671" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7235253" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120671">healthcare team</a>&nbsp;(neuro-oncologist, medical oncologist, radiation oncologist, advanced practice nurse, nurse&nbsp;navigator, pharmacist, speech therapist, neuropsychologist, social worker, nutritionist, physical therapist)?</li>
<li>How long will the surgery take?</li>
<li>What do I need to do to prepare for the surgery (changes in medications, diet, activity)?</li>
<li>How long will I be in the hospital after surgery?</li>
<li>How long will it take for me to recover from surgery?</li>
<li>How long after surgery will it take for me to return to normal activities?</li>
<li>What changes should I anticipate will happen after surgery (ability to be independent, work, drive)?</li>
<li>What happens to my tumor tissue and will I have access to it in the future?</li>
<li>What happens if I don&rsquo;t have surgery?</li>
</ul>
<p>We encourage you to print these questions and bring them with you to your appointment.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1122216" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Your medical team can help you better understand your overall care. Here are some suggested questions to ask your doctor.</p>
<ul>
<li>Where do you recommend I get more information about my diagnosis?</li>
<li>What support services are available to me and my family or caregiver?</li>
<li>Do you recommend I return to work at this time?</li>
<li>Do you anticipate that I will be able to return to work in the future?</li>
<li>How do I <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859630" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="859630" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7095847" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="859630">talk to my employer </a>about my diagnosis?</li>
<li>How do I <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=19&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=858227" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="858227" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7095848" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="858227">talk to my family</a> and friends about my diagnosis?</li>
<li>What can I expect during recovery?</li>
<li>Will I need assistive equipment or supervision at home during my treatment or recovery?</li>
<li>Are there financial support services available to me?</li>
<li>Are there travel (e.g., hotel and transportation) support services available to me and my family or caregiver?</li>
<li>Are there counseling or therapy services available to me as part of my care and to my family?</li>
</ul>
<p>We encourage you to print these questions and bring them with you to your appointment.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1122217" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">As a patient, you want to keep a record of your care. Here are some questions to ask your <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120671" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120671" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7095782" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120671">healthcare provider</a> once your treatment ends to help you know what to expect.
<ul>
<li>What treatments and drugs have I been given to treat my brain or spine tumor? And how long did I receive each treatment?</li>
<li>What side effects occurred from treatments?</li>
<li>What are the common long-term and <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000390292&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000390292&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">late effects</a> of the treatment I received?</li>
<li>Which type of doctor should I see for my <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000774384&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000774384&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">follow-up care</a>?</li>
<li>Can you recommend the doctor(s) I should see for my follow-up care?</li>
<li>How often should I have routine visits and brain or spine scans?</li>
<li>What other follow-up tests should I have?</li>
<li>How often will I need these tests?</li>
<li>What symptoms should I watch for?</li>
<li>If I develop any of these symptoms, who should I call?</li>
<li>What should I do to maintain my health and well-being?</li>
<li>Do you offer diet and exercise plans?</li>
<li>What recommendations do you have for me regarding my ability to work and drive?</li>
<li>Are there counselors, social workers or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121673" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121673" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7095783" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121673">support groups</a> that you can recommend for me?</li>
</ul>
<p>We encourage you to print these questions and bring them with you to your appointment.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1122218" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Here are some questions to ask to help you decide on the best treatment for you.</p>
<ul>
<li>What treatment options are available?&nbsp;</li>
<li>What is the <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000044930&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000044930&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">standard treatment</a> for my tumor type?</li>
<li>What are the benefits and risks of each treatment option?</li>
<li>Are there <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7095845" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121709">clinical trials</a> available for my tumor type? If so, where can I find clinical trials information?</li>
<li>When do I need to make a treatment decision? And when would I start treatment?</li>
<li>How long will I be on the treatment?</li>
<li>How will the treatment be administered (oral, IV)?</li>
<li>Where will I receive treatment?</li>
<li>How will you know if the treatment is working?</li>
<li>How often do you recommend I have <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000689578&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000689578&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">imaging tests</a>?</li>
<li>What are common treatment <a class="definition" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046580&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046580&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;">side effects</a>?</li>
<li>How do you manage treatment side effects?</li>
<li>Are there long-term effects of the treatment?</li>
<li>Can I work and carry on with my normal activities during treatment?</li>
<li>What symptoms do I need to report? And what is the best way to report symptoms? &nbsp;</li>
<li>How do I contact your team if I have treatment-related questions during the day, night, and weekends?</li>
<li>Will insurance cover the treatment?</li>
<li>If I want a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7095846" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121717">second opinion</a>, who do you recommend that I see?</li>
</ul>
<p>We encourage you to print these questions and bring them with you to your appointment.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1124208" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>This is the site map for NCI-CONNECT, the Rare Brain and Spine Tumor Network</p>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120626" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1120626" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131168" sys_variantid="2317" sys_contentid="1120626">Tumor Types&nbsp;</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120671" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120671" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131169" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120671">About CNS Tumors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120672" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120672" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131170" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120672">Anatomy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120626" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1120626" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131171" sys_variantid="2317" sys_contentid="1120626">Tumor Types</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120669" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120669" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131172" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120669">Atypical Teratoid Rhabdoid Tumor (ATRT)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120674" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120674" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131173" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120674">Choroid Plexus Tumors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121585" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121585" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131174" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121585">Diffuse Midline Gliomas</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120675" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120675" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131175" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120675">Ependymoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120676" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120676" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131176" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120676">Gliomatosis Cerebri</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121584" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121584" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131177" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121584">Gliosarcoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120677" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120677" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131178" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120677">Medulloblastoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120678" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120678" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131179" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120678">Meningioma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120679" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120679" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131180" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120679">Oligodendroglioma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120680" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120680" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131181" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120680">Pineal Region Tumors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120681" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120681" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131182" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120681">PXA / APXA</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120682" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120682" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131183" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120682">Primitive Neuro-Ectodermal Tumors (PNET)</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1120689" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1120689" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131184" sys_variantid="2317" sys_contentid="1120689">Living with a Tumor</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121295" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121295" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131185" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121295">Newly Diagnosed</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121723" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121723" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131186" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121723">In Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121725" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121725" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131187" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121725">Having A Recurrence</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121726" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121726" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131188" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121726">Finished with Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1120712" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" sys_dependentid="1120712" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131189" sys_variantid="1764" sys_contentid="1120712">Guiding Questions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120713" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120713" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131190" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120713">Coping</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121673" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121673" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131191" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121673">Related Organizations</a></li>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1124079&amp;sys_revision=2&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1124079" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7131202">Stories</a></li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1123421" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1123421" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131193" sys_variantid="2317" sys_contentid="1123421">Refer and Participate</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121709" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121709" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131194" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121709">Clinical Studies</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121711" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121711" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131195" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121711">Risk Study</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121717" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121717" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131196" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121717">Referrals</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121675" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121675" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131197" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121675">Partnerships</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121708" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121708" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131198" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121708">Be Our Partner</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2054&amp;sys_contentid=1121159" sys_dependentvariantid="2054" sys_dependentid="1121159" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131199" sys_variantid="2054" sys_contentid="1121159">NCI-CONNECTIONS</a></h2>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120595" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1120595" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131200" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1120595">About</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121154" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1121154" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7131201" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1121154">Contact Us</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1127193" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The NCI-CONNECT team is dedicated to helping those with rare central nervous system (CNS) tumors within the NCI Center for Cancer Research <span><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Neuro-Oncology-Branch?qt-lab_branch_patient_tabs=4#qt-lab_branch_patient_tabs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Neuro-Oncology Branch</a> (NOB)</span>.</p>
<h2>Co-Leaders</h2>
<br /> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133202" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="&lt;div sys_dependentvariantid=&quot;2086&quot; sys_dependentid=&quot;1133202&quot; inlinetype=&quot;rxvariant&quot; rxinlineslot=&quot;105&quot; sys_siteid=&quot;305&quot; class=&quot;rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable&quot; contenteditable=&quot;false&quot; rxselectedtext=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image-left-medium centered-set&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;centered-element&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;amp;sys_context=0&amp;amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;amp;sys_contentid=1133202&amp;amp;sys_command=edit&quot; alt=&quot;Terri Armstrong&quot; /&gt;&lt;!--Comment--&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;" sys_relationshipid="7340351">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133202&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Terri Armstrong" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Terri Armstrong, Ph.D.</strong></h3>
<h4>Co-Lead, NCI-CONNECT</h4>
<h4>Deputy Chief, NOB&nbsp;</h4>
<p>Dr. Armstrong co-leads all aspects of NCI-CONNECT and, specifically, leads its patient risk and outcomes project. The project is an online survey that looks at the impact a rare CNS tumor diagnosis and treatment has on patients and their families and explores potential clinical and genomic risk factors.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133205" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="&lt;div sys_dependentvariantid=&quot;2086&quot; sys_dependentid=&quot;1133205&quot; inlinetype=&quot;rxvariant&quot; rxinlineslot=&quot;105&quot; sys_siteid=&quot;305&quot; class=&quot;rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable&quot; contenteditable=&quot;false&quot; rxselectedtext=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image-left-medium centered-set&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;centered-element&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;amp;sys_context=0&amp;amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;amp;sys_contentid=1133205&amp;amp;sys_command=edit&quot; alt=&quot;Mark Gilbert&quot; /&gt;&lt;!--Comment--&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;" sys_relationshipid="7340352">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133205&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Mark Gilbert" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Mark Gilbert, M.D.</strong></h3>
<h4>Co-Lead, NCI-CONNECT</h4>
<h4>Chief, NOB</h4>
<p>Dr. Gilbert co-leads all aspects of NCI-CONNECT and, specifically, serves as the protocol principal investigator for its clinical trials. Dr. Gilbert directs the Brain Tumor Trials Collaborative (BTTC), a network of renowned medical centers throughout the United States that provide clinical trials to patients with rare CNS tumors.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --><hr />
<h2>Clinical Staff</h2>
<!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133201" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340353">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133201&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Alvina Acquaye" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Alvina Acquaye</strong></h3>
<h4>Research Associate</h4>
<p>Alvina manages the patient outcomes studies and provides wellness practices to patients. These include strategies to help patients cope with the mental, physical and emotional challenges faced during diagnosis.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133204" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340354">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133204&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Sonja Crandon" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Sonja Crandon</strong></h3>
<h4>Research Nurse Specialist</h4>
<p>Sonja enrolls and manages patients on non-treatment clinical studies, such as the Natural History Study, which gives researchers a better understanding of brain and spinal cord tumors and uncovers areas for further research.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133210" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340355">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133210&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Marta Penas-Prado" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Marta Penas-Prado, M.D.</strong></h3>
<h4>Associate Research Physician</h4>
<p>Dr. Penas-Prado provides clinical care to patients with rare CNS tumors and serves as principal investigator on therapeutic clinical trials. She evaluates patients&rsquo; physical well-being and provides diagnosis, symptom and treatment information. Dr. Penas-Prado provides patients with a comprehensive plan that, together with their physician at home, will ensure they get the best treatment possible.&nbsp;</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133211" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340356">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133211&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Margarita Raygada" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Margarita Raygada, Ph.D.</strong></h3>
<h4>Oncology Genetic Counselor and Geneticist&nbsp;</h4>
<p>Dr. Raygada provides genetic counseling and testing to patients, evaluates family and medical history to help determine if patients and their families are at risk for developing specific cancers or hereditary cancer syndromes, and discusses management plans for cancer screening, prevention, and risk-reduction.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133212" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340357">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133212&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Christine Siegel" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Christine Siegel</strong></h3>
<h4>Nurse Practitioner</h4>
<p>Christine provides clinical care to patients with rare CNS tumors. She evaluates patients and collaborates with the treating physician to evaluate their physical well-being, as well as inform them about their diagnosis, symptoms and treatments.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133213" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340358">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133213&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Kristen Stevens Brown" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Kristen Stevens-Brown</strong></h3>
<h4>Patient Coordinator&nbsp;</h4>
<p>Kristen coordinates the intake process for patients, including scheduling appointments, coordinating travel and gathering all necessary information from the patient to visit the NIH, and then provides visit information.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133228" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340359">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133228&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Kathleen Wall" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Kathleen Wall</strong></h3>
<h4>Clinical Research Nurse</h4>
<p>Kathleen manages patient participation on clinical trials, including assessing if patients are eligible and registering patients for clinical trials.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --><hr />
<h2><strong>Program Staff</strong></h2>
<!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133208" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340360">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133208&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Katie Blackburn" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Katie Blackburn</strong></h3>
<h4>Business Manager</h4>
<p>Katie manages the BTTC clinical trial operations, budgets, and agreements. She also plans meetings, data management, clinical monitoring and payment processing for BTTC centers.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133203" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340361">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133203&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Brittany Cordeiro" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Brittany Cordeiro</strong></h3>
<h4>Advocacy Liaison and Navigator</h4>
<p>Brittany facilitates partnerships with non-profit organizations who share a common concern for improving the outcomes of patients with rare CNS tumors through awareness and education. She also provides referral information and education materials to providers, advocates, patients and their families.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133206" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340362">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133206&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Kathleen Mercure" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Kathleen Mercure</strong></h3>
<h4>Program Manager</h4>
<p>Kathleen oversees programmatic operations, including planning workshops and meetings, managing budgets and information, and aiding leadership to achieve project success.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --> <!-- BEGIN STAFF PERSON -->
<div class="clearfix">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1133209" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7340363">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1127191&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133209&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Kristin Odom" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h3><strong>Kristin Odom</strong></h3>
<h4>Communications Editor</h4>
<p>Kristin manages communication projects, strategies and initiatives, such as the website, newsletter, social media, and other online and print materials, to educate and inform patients, providers, researchers and advocates.</p>
</div>
<!-- END STAFF PERSON --><hr />
<p>NCI-CONNECT welcomes your questions.</p>
<p><span><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=734&amp;sys_contentid=1132184" sys_contentid="1132184" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="734" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1132184" sys_variantid="734" sys_relationshipid="7340337">Contact us</a></span><strong>: </strong></p>
<p><span><strong><a href="mailto:NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov">NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov</a></strong></span><strong> or call 240-760-6530</strong></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1132184" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>NCI-CONNECT welcomes your questions.</p>
<p><strong>Contact us: </strong> <br /><strong><a href="mailto:NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov">NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov</a> or call 240-760-6530</strong></p>
<h2>Receive Updates</h2>
<p>Receive the latest news in rare adult central nervous system cancer research, care, and treatment.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://public.govdelivery.com/accounts/USNIHNCI/subscriber/new" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe </a>to our newsletter.</li>
<li>View the <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2054&amp;sys_contentid=1121159" sys_contentid="1121159" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2054" sys_relationshipid="7340332" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121159" sys_dependentvariantid="2054">NCI-CONNECTions: A Rare Brain and Spine Tumor Blog</a>.</li>
<li>Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/nihbraintumor" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@NIHBrainTumor</a> #NCICONNECT.</li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1141505" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>NCI-CONNECT hosts meetings at NIH throughout the year to bring together worldwide leaders in neuro-oncology clinical care, basic science, and clinical research with <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121675" sys_contentid="1121675" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7363324" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121675" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">advocacy partners</a>. The meetings aim to advance knowledge and collaborations to discover better treatments for people with rare central nervous system (CNS) cancers.</p>
<h3><span>2019 NCI-CONNECT and BTTC Meeting</span></h3>
<p><em>April 29-30, 2019</em></p>
<p><span>The NCI-CONNECT and <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/neuro-oncology-branch/bttc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Brain Tumor Trials Collaborative (BTTC)</a>&nbsp;Annual Meetings brought over 100 attendees across neuro-oncology specialties together to discuss CNS tumor clinical studies.&nbsp;Presentations and discussions included current studies and new clinical trial concepts that, in addition to measuring efficacy, incorporate patient quality of life and outcomes measures. The overall aim in each session was to ensure current and future studies will help effectively advance treatments for patients with gliomas and rare CNS cancers.</span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2056&amp;sys_contentid=1148490" sys_dependentvariantid="2056" sys_dependentid="1148490" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7363329" sys_variantid="2056" sys_contentid="1148490">Read the meeting summary &gt;</a></span></p>
<h3><strong>2018 NCI-CONNECT and BTTC Meeting</strong></h3>
<p><em>June 11-12, 2018</em></p>
<p>The inaugural NCI-CONNECT Meeting was held in conjunction with the BTTC&nbsp;Annual Meeting. The goal of the meetings was to bring together leaders in a collegial and collaborative environment to discuss current and future clinical trials for patients with <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045772&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045772&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">malignant</a> brain tumors, with a particular focus on rare CNS tumors. Attendees shared new clinical trial concepts that had both high levels of scientific merit and also incorporated measures of patient quality of life and outcomes.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/blog/2018/2018-meeting">Read the meeting summary &gt;</a></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1141521" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7363338">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1141542&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Dr. Kenneth Aldape" /></div>
<h3>Ependymoma Meeting</h3>
<p>Neuro-oncology experts worldwide met to advance their knowledge and collaborate to find better treatments for people with ependymoma.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2><strong>Workshops</strong></h2>
<p>NCI-CONNECT hosts and participates in tumor-specific workshops at NIH where experts across institutions studying rare brain and spine cancers and advocates can share knowledge and collaborate. The goal of these workshops is to identify areas of research, develop plans and designs for clinical trials, and facilitate collaboration.</p>
<p>Following each workshop, NCI-CONNECT will share information for healthcare providers and people living with these rare brain and spine cancers.</p>
<h3><strong>Histone Midline Glioma Workshop</strong></h3>
<p><em>September 27, 2018</em></p>
<p>The Histone Mutated <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1121585" sys_contentid="1121585" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7363325" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1121585" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Midline Glioma</a> Workshop was led by NCI-CONNECT. Participants discussed the definition of the disease in adults, current clinical care and treatments, biological targets and clinical trial designs for histone midline gliomas. Among the workshop findings, participants recognized that accurately diagnosing histone midline gliomas is critical for treatment and research, especially in adults where less is known about the tumors. The group concluded that all tumors should be sampled, processed, analyzed, and stored as <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000346525&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000346525&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">standard of care</a> to better understand this rare cancer.</p>
<h3><strong>Oligodendroglioma Workshop</strong></h3>
<p><em>November 19, 2018</em></p>
<p>The <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=11&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120679" sys_contentid="1120679" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7363326" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120679" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Oligodendroglioma</a> Workshop was led by NCI-CONNECT. Participants discussed the molecular pathology of oligodendrogliomas, clinical trial <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000346517&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000346517&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">efficacy</a> <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000346519&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000346519&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">endpoints</a> and preclinic models, and collaborative efforts in data sharing. Participants recognized the need to combine data, resources, and samples to develop better treatments for oligodendrogliomas.</p>
<h3><strong>Ependymoma Workshop</strong></h3>
<p><em>February 20-22, 2019</em><em>&nbsp;</em></p>
<p>The Fourth Biennial <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=12&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120675" sys_contentid="1120675" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7363327" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120675" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Ependymoma</a> Consensus was led by Kenneth Aldape, M.D., chief of NCI&rsquo;s Center for Cancer Research, Laboratory of Pathology. Participants discussed the latest in grading and diagnosing ependymoma, molecular and <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000046128&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000046128&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">genetic testing</a>, and clinical care and treatments for ependymoma. Participants discussed the increasing complexity of diagnosing ependymoma, underscoring the need to work together to further define genetic differences in ependymoma tumors and how they are treated.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/blog/2019/ependymoma-meeting">Read the meeting summary &gt;</a></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1147238" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>You are not alone in your journey with a rare brain or spine tumor.&nbsp;The&nbsp;NCI-CONNECT Clinic brings together adult patients with the same rare brain or spine tumor and their caregivers to receive special services. First visit services include:</p>
<ul>
<li>A review of your diagnosis. Our team will evaluate your tumor tissue prior to your first visit to confirm your tumor type. We will also look for gene changes that could cause cancer and help us treat it.</li>
<li>Consultations with our expert healthcare team. These include:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals/clinic#ui-id-2">Group meetings</a> with a health and wellness expert. You will learn coping and wellness techniques and meet others with your same diagnosis.</li>
<li>Personalized <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor/refer-participate/referrals/clinic#ui-id-3">meeting with a genetic counselor</a> to determine if you or your family are at risk for developing cancer.</li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=9&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1127193" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1127193" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7363632" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1127193">Meeting with our expert healthcare team</a> to answer questions about your diagnosis and discuss treatment and clinical trial options.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=955&amp;sys_contentid=1136968" sys_contentid="1136968" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="955" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1136968" sys_dependentvariantid="955" sys_relationshipid="7363627">View or download the NCI-CONNECT clinic flyer</a></p>
<p><span>To participate in the NCI-CONNECT Clinic, contact us at&nbsp;</span><a href="mailto:NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov">NCICONNECT@mail.nih.gov</a><span>&nbsp;or call 240-760-6530.</span></p>
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<h2>CARES Group Meetings</h2>
<p>Health and wellness counselors teach you ways to improve your health and well-being in CARES (Coping, Advocacy, Relationships, Education, Support).</p>
<p><span><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1120713" sys_contentid="1120713" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1120713" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7363628">Coping</a></span> with a rare brain or spine tumor may make you feel isolated and unsure of how to stay healthy. This can also affect your loved ones. Our CARES health and wellness counselor wants to share some positive coping strategies that may help you get through each day so you can continue to live fully.</p>
<p>During your NCI-CONNECT Clinic visit, you and your loved ones will have a CARES group meeting with a health and wellness expert. You will learn coping and wellness techniques and meet others with your same diagnosis.</p>
<p>During a CARES meeting, you will:</p>
<ul>
<li>Learn techniques to improve your and your caregiver&rsquo;s quality of life.</li>
<li>Learn tips from others with your diagnosis.</li>
<li>Get educational resources.</li>
</ul>
<p>Follow us on Twitter for more coping tips <a href="https://twitter.com/NIHBrainTumor">@NIHBrainTumor</a> #NCICONNECT #careaboutrare.</p>
<p><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=955&amp;sys_contentid=1140156" sys_contentid="1140156" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="955" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1140156" sys_dependentvariantid="955" sys_relationshipid="7363629">View or download the CARES flyer</a></p>
<h2>Genetic Counseling</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1148900" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7363634">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1135615&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1148893&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Dr. Margarita Raygada with a patient" /></div>
<h3>Genetic Counselor Helps Patients Understand Cancer Care</h3>
<p>Dr. Margarita Raygada helps brain and spine tumor patients understand what genetic testing means for their care and family cancer risk and what it means for research.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
<p>Genetic counselors determine if your cancer is hereditary and what that means for you and your family.</p>
<p>During your NCI-CONNECT Clinic visit, you will have a personalized meeting with a genetic counselor. A genetic counselor helps determine if your cancer is hereditary, passed down through a family, and what that means for you.</p>
<p>While very few central nervous system cancers are hereditary, all are caused by genetic changes. Studying these changes helps researchers develop treatments and improve care.</p>
<p>Our genetic counselor will:</p>
<ul>
<li>Meet with you to talk about your personal and family medical history.</li>
<li>Decide if genetic testing is right for you. Researchers will review your saliva, blood and tumor tissue samples to look for genetic changes to find out if your tumor is hereditary.</li>
<li>Discuss genetic test results and how the results affect your and your family&rsquo;s medical care.</li>
<li>Answer any questions you may have.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=955&amp;sys_contentid=1140157" sys_contentid="1140157" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="955" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1140157" sys_dependentvariantid="955" sys_relationshipid="7363630">View or download the genetic counseling flyer</a></p>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
</rows>