<rows>
  <row para_id="1133216" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Rare cancers are those that affect fewer than 40,000 people per year in the U.S. As a group, they make up just over a quarter of all cancers. Because rates of cancer in children are very low, all children&rsquo;s cancers are considered rare. A quarter of all cancer deaths each year are due to rare cancers. Although new treatments are always being developed, finding new treatments for rare cancers is very hard for many reasons. The MyPART network was started to make it easier to find treatments for rare cancers.</p>
<h2>Why are rare cancers challenging?</h2>
<p>Rare cancers are challenging for patients, doctors, and scientists.</p>
<p>For patients:</p>
<ul>
<li>It often takes a long time from the time you think something is wrong to the time when doctors know that you have a rare cancer and what kind of cancer it is.</li>
<li>It is hard to find doctors who know a lot about your cancer and how to treat it.</li>
<li>It is hard to know what to do when doctors don&rsquo;t agree on how to treat your cancer.</li>
<li>You may need to travel far from your&nbsp;home and family to get treatment for your rare cancer.</li>
</ul>
<p>For doctors:</p>
<ul>
<li>You may not know what to tell your patient about what to expect with their rare cancer.</li>
<li>You may not have been trained in how to treat this type of rare cancer.</li>
<li>It is hard to find an expert in the rare cancer who can answer questions or to whom you can refer your patient.</li>
</ul>
<p>For scientists:</p>
<ul>
<li>There may be no information about the rare cancer to give you ideas on which drugs could treat it.</li>
<li>There may be no animal or cell models of the rare cancer in which to test your ideas.</li>
<li>There may not be enough tumor samples from rare cancer patients available for your research.</li>
<li>If you have an idea of a drug that could treat the cancer, it may be hard to find enough patients with the rare cancer to test your idea.</li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133218" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is adamantinoma?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7337502">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Adamantinoma is a rare bone cancer. Most of the time, adamantinoma grows in the lower leg. It often starts as a lump in the middle of the shinbone (tibia) or the calf bone (fibula). Adamantinoma can also occur in the jaw bone (mandible) or, sometimes, the forearm, hands, or feet. An adamantinoma lump can be painful, swollen and red, and can cause movement problems.</p>
<p>Adamantinoma is a serious condition. Treatment is important for survival but it is possible to make a full recovery.</p>
<h2>How common is adamantinoma?</h2>
<p>Adamantinoma accounts for less than 1% of all bone cancers. It is more common in males than in females. Young adults are most frequently affected. Adamantinoma in children is very rare.</p>
<h2>How is adamantinoma diagnosed?</h2>
<p>Adamantinoma can cause symptoms of pain and swelling, and can sometimes be felt by the doctor during a physical exam.&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Imaging</strong>: If you have symptoms of adamantinoma, your doctor will use imaging scans such as X-rays, CT, MRI, and bone scans to look at the size of the tumor, how fast it is growing, and where it is in the body. They will also check for signs that the cancer has spread to other parts of the body.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>To check if the tumor is adamantinoma, your doctor will perform a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. An expert, called a pathologist, will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is.</p>
<h2>How is adamantinoma treated?</h2>
<p>Surgery is the best option for adamantinoma treatment. If the tumor and all cancer cells&nbsp;are removed, there is a good chance of being cured. If some cancer cells are left behind, there is a greater chance of the cancer coming back in the same spot, or a different part of the body. Adamantinomas tend to not respond to other cancer treatments such as chemotherapy.</p>
<p>When possible, the surgeon will take out the tumor and will not touch the healthy parts of the body, but it is sometimes necessary to remove the limb with the adamantinoma tumor.&nbsp;The limb can be rebuilt with surgery to keep function, but the details of this process will be different for each person.</p>
<p>Once the adamantinoma tumor has been taken out by surgery, you will have to keep regular appointments with your doctor in order to catch it early, if it does come back.</p>
<h2>Does adamantinoma run in families?</h2>
<p>No, adamantinoma does not run in families.</p>
<h2>How does adamantinoma form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms, but it can be hard to prove. Because adamantinoma occurs most frequently in young adults after bones stop growing, this may give scientists some clues. But adamantinoma is so rare, very little is known about what causes it.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for people with adamantinoma?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7337500">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate survival rates by how groups of people with adamantinoma have done in the past. Because there are so few adamantinoma patients, these rates may not be very accurate. They also can&rsquo;t consider newer treatments being developed. With this is mind, you have a better chance of being completely cured if all the cancer cells are removed with surgery.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133220" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is chordoma?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7337429">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Chordoma is a slow growing cancer of tissue found inside the spine. Chordoma can happen anywhere along the spine. It is most often found near the tailbone (called a sacral tumor) or where the spine meets the skull (called a clival tumor). Chordoma is also called notochordal sarcoma.</p>
<p>Chordomas form from the left-over cells that were important in the development of the spine before birth. These cells are called notochord cells. When the notochord cells don&rsquo;t disappear after birth, they can turn into chordomas.</p>
<p>Chordomas grow very slowly. Many people don&rsquo;t notice any change in their bodies for years. When they do start to have symptoms, it can take a while for the chordoma to be discovered and diagnosed.</p>
<p>Most people are diagnosed with chordoma in their 50s and 60s. Pediatric chordomas make up 5% of all chordoma diagnoses. Females are diagnosed slightly more often than males in childhood. Males are more often diagnosed as adults.</p>
<h2>How common is chordoma?</h2>
<p>Worldwide, one in one million people are diagnosed with chordoma per year.</p>
<h2>How is chordoma diagnosed?</h2>
<p>Symptoms of chordoma can be very different depending on where in your spine the chordoma starts. When chordoma starts at the base of the skull you may have headaches or double vision. Chordoma near the tailbone can cause pain down your legs and trouble controlling your bladder or bowels.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>When you have symptoms of chordoma, your doctor will take an image of your spine using an MRI to look at the size of the tumor and where it is. They may also use a CT scan to see if the tumor has spread.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>To check if the tumor is chordoma, your doctor will do a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. An expert, called a pathologist, will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is. When viewed under a microscope, chordoma cells look like notochord cells.</p>
<h2>How is chordoma treated?</h2>
<p>When possible, chordomas are removed with surgery. Radiation therapy is sometimes used after surgery, or alone if surgery is not possible. Chordomas can be difficult to treat because they grow on the spine, near important tissues like nerves and blood vessels. It can be hard to get all of the tumor out of your spine without hurting the healthy parts of your body.</p>
<p>New research is being done using immunotherapy to treat chordomas and to find other treatments. Immunotherapy is a cancer treatment that uses the body&rsquo;s immune system to fight the disease.</p>
<p>It is important to talk with a team of specialists to decide what the right treatment is for you. You can contact <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133262" sys_contentid="1133262" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7337427" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133262" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">MyPART</a> to get help finding specialists.</p>
<h2>Does chordoma run in families?</h2>
<p>The risk of passing chordoma on to your children is low, but there are rare cases where many members of the same family have chordoma.</p>
<h2>How does chordoma form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms, but it can be hard to prove. We know that many people with chordoma have a small change in a protein called brachyury, made by the <em>TBXT</em> gene. Changes in other genes have also been found. Scientists are using brachyury to develop immunotherapy for chordoma.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with chordoma?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7337428" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate chordoma survival rates by how groups of people with chordoma have done in the past. Because there are so few people with chordoma, these rates may not be very accurate. They also don&rsquo;t&nbsp;consider newer treatments being developed. Even so, we know that the average survival is around 10 years after diagnosis. Your chances of survival depend on where the tumor is and how much can be removed by surgery. In some cases, complete cures are possible.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/1303/chordoma">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?t=C2947&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">NCI-Supported Clinical Trials</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133222" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is an alveolar soft part sarcoma?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7337484">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Alveolar soft part sarcoma, or ASPS, is a cancer that can come from different types of soft tissue, such as muscle, fat, or nerves. It may also be called alveolar soft tissue sarcoma, alveolar sarcoma of soft parts, or ASP sarcoma.</p>
<p>ASPS usually starts in the leg, although it can also begin in other parts of the body, including the arms, head, or neck. It can be difficult to find in the early stages because it starts as a painless lump. By the time it is discovered, ASPS often has spread to other places in the body, in particular, the lungs.</p>
<p>ASPS tends to spread early because it creates a network of blood vessels through which cancer cells can travel. Your doctor will monitor your whole body for signs of the cancer spreading.</p>
<h2>How common is alveolar soft part sarcoma?</h2>
<p>ASPS is one of the rarest sarcomas. Soft tissue sarcomas make up 1% of all cancers and ASPS makes up only 0.2% to 1% of all soft tissue sarcomas. There are about 80 cases diagnosed per year in the United States.</p>
<h2>How is alveolar soft part sarcoma diagnosed?</h2>
<p>In adults, ASPS is often found as a painless lump in the leg or buttock. It can also be found in the trunk or arms. In children, ASPS can be found in the head and neck, especially around the tongue or eye socket. In both adults and children, ASPS can be difficult to find early.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>If you have symptoms of ASPS, your doctor will use imaging scans such as CT or MRI to look at the size of the tumor and where it is in the body. They will also check for signs that the tumor has spread to other parts of the body.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>To check if the tumor is ASPS, your doctor will perform a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. A pathologist will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is.</p>
<h2>How is alveolar soft part sarcoma treated?</h2>
<p>While ASPS spreads early, it grows much slower than many other sarcomas. This slow growth means that people with ASPS can live for a long time. People with this disease need to be carefully followed by doctors to control the growth and spread of the cancer. Treatment depends on where it starts and where it spreads, which is different for each patient.</p>
<p><strong>Surgery: </strong>Surgery is often used to remove the main tumor without harming the healthy tissue.</p>
<p><strong>Radiation therapy: </strong>Radiation therapy can be used around the time of surgery. The radiation is aimed at the tumor area to prevent it from growing back after it is removed.</p>
<p><strong>Chemotherapy: </strong>Currently, chemotherapy does not work for ASPS.</p>
<p><strong>Targeted therapy</strong>: Targeted therapy is intended to prevent the changes in cancer cells that help them grow, divide, and spread.&nbsp;Because chemotherapy does not work for ASPS, researchers are working to make better treatments, such as targeted therapies that have been shown to shrink ASPS tumors.</p>
<h2>Does alveolar soft part sarcoma run in families?</h2>
<p>ASPS is not known to run in families.</p>
<h2>How does alveolar soft part sarcoma form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms, but it can be hard to prove. We know that in ASPS, chromosomes (the parts of your cells that contain all of your genes) break apart and get put back together in the wrong way. This can cause cells to not function like they should. In ASPS, a gene called <em>TFE3</em> joins with a region called ASPCR1. Doctors will look for this change in chromosomes to confirm that your cancer is ASPS.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with alveolar soft part sarcoma?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7337481" sys_variantid="2297">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate ASPS survival rates by how groups of people with ASPS have done in the past. Given that there are so few ASPS patients, these rates may not be very accurate. They also don&rsquo;t consider newer treatments being developed. With this in mind, about 80% of people whose cancer has not spread are alive five years after they are diagnosed with ASPS. Children with ASPS that has not spread have a better chance of survival than adults. If the cancer has spread to other parts of the body, 10% to 40% of people survive five years after diagnosis, depending on whether they have surgery. There are new treatments and clinical trials that show promise for some of these people.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=36&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=814&amp;sys_contentid=13832" sys_contentid="13832" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="13832" sys_dependentvariantid="814" sys_relationshipid="7337482" sys_variantid="814">National Cancer Institute &ndash; Soft Tissue Sarcoma Page</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/5654/alveolar-soft-part-sarcoma">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?t=C3750%7CC7943&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">National Cancer Institute sponsored clinical trials</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=289&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=5296" sys_contentid="5296" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="5296" sys_dependentvariantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7337483" sys_variantid="990">National Cancer Insititute &ndash; Pediatric Alveolar Soft Part Sarcomas</a></li>
</ul>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133223" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is desmoid tumor?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7344715">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637&amp;sys_command=edit" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Desmoid tumors grow from the connective tissue in your body. They grow from <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000044590&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000044590&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">fibroblast</a> cells, which make up connective tissue and are also important for wound healing. Connective tissue supports and connects your bones, ligaments, and muscles, and helps hold your organs in place. Desmoid tumors are also known as aggressive fibromatosis or desmoid-type fibromatosis.</p>
<p>A desmoid tumor can occur anywhere in the body since connective tissue is found everywhere in your body. Desmoid tumors are often found in the abdomen, as well as the shoulders, upper arms, and thighs.</p>
<p>Desmoid tumors are benign, which means they are not cancer. While the cells of the desmoid tumor do not travel to parts the body like cancer can, they can invade nearby tissue and are often very painful. Desmoid tumors can grow slowly or very quickly. The quicker they grow the more serious they are. Desmoid tumors can be difficult to completely remove with surgery. &nbsp;</p>
<p>Desmoid tumors are most common in people between the ages of 15 and 60 years. They are more common in females than males.</p>
<h2>How common is desmoid tumor?</h2>
<p>For every one million people worldwide, two to four are diagnosed with a desmoid tumor per year.</p>
<h2>How is desmoid tumor diagnosed?</h2>
<p>Some people with desmoid tumors have symptoms,&nbsp;while others do not. Symptoms can include pain, swelling in the area of the tumor, sleep loss, or difficulty moving. For people without symptoms, these tumors can be discovered if the person has an imaging test for another reason.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging:</strong> If you have symptoms of a desmoid tumor, your doctor may use imaging scans such as CT, MRI, or ultrasound to see where the tumor is and its size.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>To check if the tumor is a desmoid tumor your doctor will do a biopsy, taking a small amount of the tumor out with a needle. A pathologist will study the cells under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is. Depending on the tumor's location, it may be difficult for the doctor to take a biopsy.</p>
<h2>How is desmoid tumor treated?</h2>
<p>Treatment for each patient will be unique so you should go to an expert in sarcoma treatment to decide the best approach for your tumor. You can <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133262" sys_contentid="1133262" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133262" sys_relationshipid="7344712" sys_variantid="2297">contact MyPART</a> for help finding experts near you.</p>
<p>Desmoid tumors can be hard to predict. They can shrink and go away on their own, they can remain the same size, or they can grow quickly.</p>
<p>Treatment options to discuss with your doctor include:</p>
<p><strong>Watch and wait:</strong> In some cases, the tumor grows very slowly, or even shrinks without any treatment. It may be safest for your doctor to check your tumor regularly without treating it.</p>
<p><strong>Surgery: </strong>Surgery has been a standard treatment for desmoid tumors in the past but this may be changing. Given that the tumor often returns to the same location after surgery, doctors are looking for other treatment options.</p>
<p><strong>Radiation therapy: </strong>Radiation therapy is a treatment option for some desmoid tumors. Given that radiation therapy can cause other cancers in the future, it is important to discuss alternatives with your doctor.</p>
<p><strong>Chemotherapy: </strong>There is no standard chemotherapy for desmoid tumors but promising new drugs have been shown to shrink these tumors.</p>
<p>It is important to discuss these different options with your doctor and seek second opinions, if possible.</p>
<h2>Do desmoid tumors run in families?</h2>
<p>In 5% to 10% of cases, desmoid tumors may run in families. Those diagnosed with <a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/6482/gardner-syndrome">Gardner syndrome</a>, a rare syndrome that also runs in families, have a high risk of colorectal cancer and desmoid tumor.</p>
<h2>How does desmoid tumor form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how tumors form but it can be hard to prove. We know that some people with a family history of desmoid tumors have a change in a gene called adenomatous polyposis coli, or <em>APC.</em> This change causes too much of a protein called beta-catenin in parts of your cells. Too much beta-catenin can cause cells to grow when they shouldn&rsquo;t. In some desmoid tumors, there is too much beta-catenin, even though <em>APC</em> is normal.</p>
<p><em>APC</em> and beta-catenin are important in many common cancers, such as colon cancer, and scientists are trying to use this information to develop better cancer treatments, which will help people with desmoid tumors.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with a desmoid tumor?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>How fast the tumor grows</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_relationshipid="7344713" sys_variantid="2297">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate desmoid tumor survival rates by how groups of people with desmoid tumors have done in the past. Given that there are so few desmoid tumor patients, survival rates may not be very accurate. They also don&rsquo;t consider newer treatments being developed.</p>
<p>Most desmoid tumors do not impact lifespan but they are very difficult to get rid of and can be painful to live with. Desmoid tumors growing in the abdomen can cause problems, such as blocking your intestines. It is important that your doctor monitor the growth of these tumors carefully.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/1820/desmoid-tumor">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center &ndash; Desmoid Tumor</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?q=desmoid+tumor&amp;t=&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">National Cancer Institute sponsored clinical trials for Desmoid Tumors</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133225" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7337490">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor, or IMT, forms in tissues called mucosal surfaces and mesentery. Mucosal surfaces are found in your eyes, nose, mouth, digestive tract, lungs, and genital and urinary tracts. Mesentery connects the organs in your abdomen. IMT usually starts in the lungs but may begin in the bladder, uterus, larynx, stomach, liver, or intestine. IMT may also be called inflammatory fibrosarcoma or IMFT.</p>
<p>IMT is named for two types of cells in the tumor. IMT forms from a type of cell called a myofibroblast. Myofibroblasts help keep the shape of organs and heal wounds. IMTs also contain a lot of immune cells, making the tumor look &ldquo;inflamed&rdquo; like an infection.</p>
<p>IMT is usually <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045614&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045614&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">benign</a>, meaning that it is not cancer and these tumor cells usually do not travel to other parts the body. However, IMT can invade nearby tissue and cause a lot of problems. IMT can grow in the way of important organs such as the lung or stomach. In very rare cases, IMT can spread to distant organs.</p>
<p>IMTs are mostly found in children and young adults but can occur at any age.</p>
<h2>How common is inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor?</h2>
<p>IMT is very rare and occurs in less than one in one million people. An estimated 150-200 people are diagnosed in the US annually.</p>
<h2>How is inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor diagnosed?</h2>
<p>Although IMT can cause specific symptoms, some people with IMT do not have any. IMT symptoms depend on where the tumor is and its size. Symptoms may include fever, night sweats, weight loss, generally not feeling well, and pain at the site of the tumor.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>If you have symptoms of IMT, your doctor will use imaging scans such as CT, ultrasound, or MRI to&nbsp;determine where the tumor is in the body and its size.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>To check if the tumor is IMT, your doctor will perform a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. A pathologist will study the cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is.</p>
<p><strong>Molecular Diagnostics:</strong> Molecular diagnostics are techniques used to identify a disease by studying molecules, such as proteins, DNA, and RNA, in a tissue or fluid. They are used because IMTs can look like other tumors or infections, and can be hard to diagnose. Your doctor will test your biopsy sample for markers that show whether it is IMT. This helps them decide which treatment is best for you.</p>
<h2>How is inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor treated?</h2>
<p>Treatment of IMT depends on where the tumor is located, which proteins it makes, and whether it has spread to other parts of the body.</p>
<p><strong>Surgery: </strong>IMTs are hard to completely remove by surgery and often come back. It is important to follow up with your doctor to check if the tumor has returned.</p>
<p><strong>Chemotherapy: </strong>If the IMT is faster growing or has returned after surgery, your doctor may use chemotherapy to treat it.</p>
<p><strong>Targeted Therapy: </strong>Some IMTs make proteins that can be targeted by new drugs. Depending on how well your IMT is removed by surgery, your doctor may try one of these targeted therapies.</p>
<h2>Does inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor run in families?</h2>
<p>IMT is not known to run in families.</p>
<h2>How does inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how tumors form, but it can be hard to prove. We know that in some cases of IMT, chromosomes (the parts of your cells that contain all of your genes) break apart and get put back together in the wrong way. This can cause cells to not function like they should. In IMT, a gene called <em>ALK</em> can join with other genes. Your doctor may look for this change in chromosomes to confirm that your tumor is IMT.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the tumor has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7337488" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate IMT survival rates by how groups of people with IMT have done in the past. Given that there are so few IMT patients, these survival rates may not be very accurate. They also don&rsquo;t consider newer treatments being developed. In general, those with IMT that is completely removed by surgery do very well and most people survive past 10 years.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=289&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=5296" sys_contentid="5296" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7337489" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="5296" sys_dependentvariantid="990">National Cancer Institute &ndash; Childhood Soft Tissue Sarcoma Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/7146/inflammatory-myofibroblastic-tumor">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center &ndash; Inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor </a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?t=C6481&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">National Cancer Institute sponsored clinical trials for inflammatory myofibroblastic tumors</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133227" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is synovial sarcoma?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7344719">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637&amp;sys_command=edit" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Synovial sarcoma is a cancer that can come from different types of soft tissue, such as muscle or ligaments. It is often found in the arm, leg, or foot, and near joints such as the wrist or ankle. It can also form in soft tissues in the lung or abdomen. Synovial sarcoma may also be called malignant synovioma.</p>
<p>One third of patients with synovial sarcoma will be diagnosed under the age of 30. It is somewhat more common in males.</p>
<h2>How common is synovial sarcoma?</h2>
<p>Synovial sarcoma accounts for 5% to 10% of soft-tissue tumors.&nbsp;For every&nbsp;one million people, one to two are diagnosed with synovial sarcoma per year in the US.</p>
<h2>How is synovial sarcoma diagnosed?</h2>
<p>The symptoms caused by synovial sarcoma depend on where the tumor forms. Synovial sarcoma is often first noticed as a painless lump. If it is near a nerve, it might cause pain or numbness as it grows.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>If you have symptoms of synovial sarcoma, your doctor will use scans such as X-ray, ultrasound, CT scan, and MRI to take pictures of the tumor.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy:</strong> Your doctor will&nbsp;perform a biopsy, taking a small sample of the tumor with a needle. <a name="_Hlk536023130"></a>A pathologist will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is.</p>
<h2>How is synovial sarcoma treated?</h2>
<p>Treatment for synovial sarcoma depends on whether it has spread. Given that synovial sarcoma can grow for a while before it is found, there is a greater chance that it will spread to other parts of the body.</p>
<p><strong>Surgery: </strong>Surgery is the first choice of treatment for synovial sarcomas. When all of the tumor is removed and there is no sign of cancer anywhere else in the body,&nbsp;there is&nbsp;a better chance of survival. Success of the surgery depends on the size of the tumor and its location in the body.</p>
<p><strong>Radiation therapy: </strong>Sometimes radiation therapy is used before or after surgery to kill cancer cells.</p>
<p><strong>Chemotherapy: </strong>Chemotherapy may be used when synovial sarcoma cannot be completely removed by surgery or when it has spread. You should discuss the benefits and risks of chemotherapy with your doctors.</p>
<h2>Does synovial sarcoma run in families?</h2>
<p>No, synovial sarcoma does not run in families.</p>
<h2>How does synovial sarcoma form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms, but it can be hard to prove. We know that in synovial sarcoma, chromosomes (the parts of your cells that contain all of your genes) break apart and get put back together in the wrong way. This can cause cells to not function like they should. In synovial sarcoma, a gene called <em>SYT</em> is joined to <em>SSX</em> genes. Doctors will look for this change in chromosomes to confirm that&nbsp;it is synovial sarcoma.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with synovial sarcoma?<strong> </strong></h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different, and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_relationshipid="7344716" sys_variantid="2297">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate synovial sarcoma survival rates by how groups of people with synovial sarcoma have done in the past. Given that&nbsp;there are so few synovial sarcoma patients, survival rates may not be very accurate. They also don&rsquo;t consider newer treatments being developed. We know that anywhere from 36% to 76% of people with synovial sarcoma will be alive five years after their first diagnosis. Chances of survival&nbsp;are better if the tumor is completely removed and does not return or spread.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma">National Cancer Institute &ndash; Soft Tissue Sarcoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/7721/synovial-sarcoma">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center&nbsp; - synovial sarcoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?q=synovial+sarcoma&amp;t=&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">National Cancer Institute sponsored clinical trials&nbsp; for synovial sarcoma</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133231" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is fibrolamellar carcinoma?</h2>
<div sys_relationshipid="7370935" sys_dependentid="1133251" rxinlineslot="105" contenteditable="false" sys_dependentvariantid="2388" rxselectedtext="" rxanchortext="" unselectable="on" inlinetype="rxvariant" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
	<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
		<a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1133251&amp;sys_command=preview" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1133251">
							    				<div class="image-hover">
    					<img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637&amp;sys_command=preview" alt="Link to Participate in Trial page">
    				</div>
				    		    		    			<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
    					        		        			<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
        							</a>
    </div>
	</div>
</div>
<p>Fibrolamellar carcinoma, or FLC, is a rare cancer of the liver that usually grows in teens and adults under 40 years old. This type of cancer is different than other types of liver cancer because it happens in people who have healthy livers. Other liver cancers tend to grow in people with livers that have been damaged by alcohol abuse or infection with certain viruses. Fibrolamellar carcinoma may be called by many different names, including eosinophilic glassy cell hepatoma, fibrolamellar oncocytic hepatoma, fibrolamellar hepatocellular carcinoma (FLHCC) or FHCC.</p>
<h2>How common is fibrolamellar carcinoma?</h2>
<p>FLC is so rare that there is little data on how many people have it. It is thought to make up 1% to 5% of all liver cancers. FLC affects both men and women and is thought to occur in about one in five million people in the US. &nbsp;</p>
<h2>How is fibrolamellar carcinoma diagnosed?</h2>
<p>Many people with FLC do not have symptoms when the cancer first starts. Later, when the tumor gets larger, symptoms can include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pain in the abdomen, shoulder, or back</li>
<li>Nausea and vomiting</li>
<li>Appetite and weight loss</li>
<li>Malaise (having less energy or just feeling unwell)</li>
<li>Jaundice (yellowing of the skin)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>If you have symptoms of FLC, your doctor will use imaging scans such as CT, MRI, and ultrasound to look at the size of the tumor and where it is. They will also check for signs that the tumor has spread to other parts of the body.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>To check if the tumor is FLC, your doctor will perform a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. An expert, called a pathologist, will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is.</p>
<h2>How is fibrolamellar carcinoma treated?</h2>
<p><strong>Surgery:</strong> Surgery is used to remove as much of the FLC as possible. This surgery can involve either a resection, where part of the liver is taken out, or a transplant, where the whole liver is taken out and replaced with a donor liver. If the surgeon does a resection, you will be able to live and function well even with part of your liver missing.</p>
<p><strong>Chemotherapy: </strong>&nbsp;When surgery is not possible or when the cancer has spread, chemotherapy will be used to treat the FLC.</p>
<p><strong>Embolization Therapy:</strong> Depending on where the FLC is, embolization therapy can be used. This type of therapy cuts off the blood supply to the part of the liver where the FLC is located. This causes the FLC to die because it can&rsquo;t get oxygen and nutrients.</p>
<h2>Does fibrolamellar carcinoma run in families?</h2>
<p>Because there are so few people with FLC, we do not know if it runs in families.</p>
<h2>How does fibrolamellar carcinoma form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms, but it can be hard to prove. We know that in FLC, a chromosome (the part of your cells that contains your genes) breaks apart and gets put back together in the wrong way. This can cause cells to not function like they should. In FLC, a gene called <em>DNAJB1</em> joins with a gene called <em>PRKACA</em>. This happens in almost all cases, so it may be very important for how FLC forms. Scientists are trying to figure out how this works, so they can invent new therapies. Your doctor may test your tumor for <em>DNAJB1</em> and <em>PRKACA</em> to confirm it is FLC.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with fibrolamellar carcinoma?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=43&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7370933">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate survival rates by how people with FLC have done in the past. Because there are so few cases, these rates may not be very accurate. They also don&rsquo;t consider that&nbsp;newer treatments are being developed.</p>
<p>We do know that surgery is very important for surviving longer. For people with FLC who are treated with surgery, 44% to 68% survive for five years. When people with FLC get other treatment without surgery, 2% to 17% survive for five years.</p>
<p>New understanding of chromosome changes in FLC may help find better treatments for this tumor.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=52&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=814&amp;sys_contentid=14121" sys_contentid="14121" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="814" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="14121" sys_variantid="814" sys_relationshipid="7370934">Liver and Bile Duct Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/9396/fibrolamellar-carcinoma">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center - Fibrolamellar carcinoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?q=fibrolamellar+hepatocellular+carcinoma&amp;t=&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">NCI-Supported Clinical Trials</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133232" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7337453">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor, or SDH-deficient GIST, is a type of digestive tract cancer. It almost always grows in the stomach or small intestine, but sometimes in the large intestine. GISTs are &ldquo;SDH-deficient&rdquo; 5% to 7.5% of the time and usually grow only in the stomach. SDH is short for succinate dehydrogenase, a protein that is important for making energy for your body.&nbsp;Most people with SDH-deficient GISTs are children and some young adults.</p>
<p>People with SDH-deficient GIST are at higher risk for other types of cancer. They are at risk for pulmonary chondromas, a benign tumor in the lung, and paragangliomas, a rare tumor that grows in the nerve cell and can occur anywhere in the body.</p>
<h2>How common is SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor?</h2>
<p>GIST is a common type of tumor of the digestive tract. It is thought that 4,000 to 6,000 people per year are diagnosed with GIST in the United States. SDH-deficient GIST is much rarer, making up 5% to 7.5% of all GISTs. SDH-deficient GIST affects females more than males.</p>
<h2>How is SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor diagnosed?</h2>
<p>Symptoms of SDH-deficient GIST include bleeding in the digestive tract, intense abdominal pain, feeling tired, or feeling full after a small meal. For many people, it can be a difficult and frustrating process to get the correct diagnosis.&nbsp;GIST is hard to diagnose because it looks like other types of stomach cancer.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>If you have symptoms of SDH-deficient GIST, your doctor will use imaging scans such as CT or MRI to look at the size of the tumor and where it is in your digestive tract. Your doctor may also use endoscopy to look at the tumor. Endoscopy is a type of imaging where a small video camera on a long flexible tube is put inside your digestive tract.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy:</strong> To check if the tumor is SDH-deficient GIST, your doctor will perform a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. A pathologist will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is. This may be done at the same time as the endoscopy.</p>
<p><strong>Genetic testing:</strong> Your doctor will use the biopsy to check the <em>SDH</em> genes in your tumor. This will indicate whether you have SDH-deficient GIST or another type.</p>
<h2>How is SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor treated?</h2>
<p>SDH-deficient GIST can be taken out with surgery. It does not respond well to some chemotherapy, the way other GISTs do, but new chemotherapy options are being studied that have shown promise.</p>
<h2>Does SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor run in families?</h2>
<p>Yes. In rare cases, SDH-deficient GISTs can be passed down in families. Carney-Stratakis syndrome is a disease where people develop several types of tumors including SDH-deficient GIST. Many of the families with Carney-Stratakis syndrome carry mutations in SDH that can be passed on to children.</p>
<h2>How does SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms but each form can be hard to prove. We know that SDH can be turned off in many different ways in SDH-deficient GIST. When SDH is turned off, cells can become overactive and behave as if your body is growing or repairing a wound. Scientists are trying to understand how tumors form when cells act in this way.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_relationshipid="7337450" sys_variantid="2297">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate survival rates by how groups of people with SDH-deficient GIST have done in the past. Because there are so few people with SDH-deficient GIST, these rates may not be very accurate. They also can&rsquo;t consider newer treatments being developed.</p>
<p>People can live with SDH-deficient GIST for a very long time, especially if the tumor is taken out in surgery and doesn&rsquo;t spread to other parts of the body.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=122&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=90466" sys_contentid="90466" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="990" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="90466" sys_relationshipid="7337451" sys_variantid="990">National Cancer Institute &ndash; Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treatment page</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/8598/gastrointestinal-stromal-tumors">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center - Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?t=C3868&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">NCI-Supported Clinical Trials - GIST</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133234" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is adrenocortical carcinoma?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7358819">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637&amp;sys_command=edit" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Adrenocortical carcinoma, or ACC, is a cancer of the adrenal glands, which are two small triangular-shaped glands that sit on top of each kidney. The outside of these glands is called the adrenal cortex. The adrenal cortex makes important hormones that help your body control water balance, blood pressure, stress response, and cause the body to have male or female traits. ACCs form in the adrenal cortex.</p>
<p>An ACC may be functioning, which means it makes more hormone than normal, or&nbsp;non-functioning, which means it has no effect on hormone production. A functioning ACC tumor often makes too much of the hormones cortisol, aldosterone, testosterone, or estrogen.</p>
<h2>How common is adrenocortical carcinoma?</h2>
<p>ACC is very rare, affecting around one case diagnosed in one million people in the US. It is more common in females than males.</p>
<h2>How is adrenocortical carcinoma diagnosed?</h2>
<p>ACC can cause pain in the abdomen, high blood pressure, acne, overgrowth of hair, and voice deepening. Other symptoms of ACC are different for females and males, since it can change hormone levels. Females may have an overgrowth in female genitalia and facial hair. Males may have abnormal penis growth or early puberty changes like increased muscle growth and body hair.</p>
<p><strong>Lab Tests: </strong>If you have symptoms of ACC, your doctor will order lab tests of your urine and blood to check your hormone levels.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>Your doctor will use imaging tests such as ultrasound, CT, X-ray, PET, and MRI scans to look at the size of the tumor and whether it has spread to other parts of your body.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>To check if the tumor is ACC, your doctor may perform a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. <a name="_Hlk536023130"></a>A pathologist will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is.</p>
<p>ACC is rare but, another type of tumor in the adrenal glands, adrenocortical adenoma, is quite common. Adrenocortical adenoma is not as dangerous as ACC. It can be difficult to tell the difference between them because they are both found in the adrenal glands and the cells can look similar. Getting the correct diagnosis is very important to&nbsp;determine the&nbsp;best treatment.</p>
<h2>How is adrenocortical carcinoma treated?</h2>
<p><strong>Surgery: </strong>Surgery is used to remove as much of the ACC as possible. Small ACCs are often cured with surgery.</p>
<p><strong>Chemotherapy: </strong>When the ACC tumors are large, or the cancer cells have spread to other parts of the body, chemotherapy is used with surgery.</p>
<h2>Does adrenocortical carcinoma run in families?</h2>
<p>ACC runs in families 50% of the time. Genetic testing is recommended for all close relatives of people with ACC.<br /> &nbsp;<br /> When you have ACC, you may have other conditions that increase your chance of getting cancer. Genetic testing helps determine if you or your family members are at risk of developing ACC and other diseases. Genetic counseling is often recommended to help you understand&nbsp;the risks to you and your family members.</p>
<h2>How does adrenocortical carcinoma form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms but it can be hard to prove. Because ACC can run in families, we know that changes in genes linked to <a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/6902/li-fraumeni-syndrome">Li-Fraumeni Syndrome</a>, <a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/3343/beckwith-wiedemann-syndrome">Beckwith-Wiedemann Syndrome</a>, and <a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/1119/carney-complex">Carney complex</a> are important in causing ACC.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with adrenocortical carcinoma?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7358815">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate ACC survival rates by how groups of people with ACC have done in the past. Because there are so few people with ACC, these rates may not be very accurate. They also don't consider newer treatments being developed.</p>
<p>If the ACC is small when it is&nbsp;found, prognosis is good and cure is likely. If the ACC is already large or has spread to other parts of the body, treatment is more difficult and the five-year survival rate is 36% to 46%.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=197&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=5309" sys_contentid="5309" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="990" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="5309" sys_variantid="990" sys_relationshipid="7358816">National Cancer Institute &ndash; Adrenocortical Carcinoma Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/558/adrenocortical-carcinoma">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center &ndash; Adrenocortical carcinoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=12&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2285&amp;sys_contentid=1052944" sys_contentid="1052944" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2285" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1052944" sys_variantid="2285" sys_relationshipid="7358817">NCI &ndash; Supported Clinical Trials</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133235" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is anaplastic thyroid cancer?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7337463">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Anaplastic thyroid cancer, or ATC, is a type of thyroid cancer. The thyroid is a gland located in the front of your neck, just below the Adam&rsquo;s apple. It is responsible for sending out hormones to the rest of your body. ATC is different than other types of thyroid cancers because ATC invades other parts of the body very quickly. This type of cancer usually affects people over the age of 60. ATC can also be called anaplastic thyroid carcinoma.</p>
<h2>How common is anaplastic thyroid cancer?</h2>
<p>ATC is a rare type of thyroid cancer, making up 1% to 2% of thyroid cancer cases. ATC affects one to two people per one million per year in the US.</p>
<h2>How is anaplastic thyroid cancer diagnosed?</h2>
<p>ATC can start as a bump in the throat area. The tumor growing on the thyroid can make your voice hoarse by blocking your vocal chords, or it can make it difficult to breathe by blocking your windpipe. Sometimes people can have ATC for a while and not notice it because the tumor remains small.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>If you have symptoms of ATC, your doctor will use imaging scans such as ultrasound, CT, and MRI to look at the size of the tumor. They will also check for signs that the tumor has spread to other parts of the body.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>To check if the tumor is ATC, your doctor will perform a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. A pathologist will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is.</p>
<h2>How is anaplastic thyroid cancer treated?</h2>
<p><strong>Surgery: </strong>Once ATC is diagnosed, you may have surgery to remove the thyroid. This surgery is a called a thyroidectomy.&nbsp;If a thyroidectomy is not an option, your doctor will discuss other options with you.</p>
<p><strong>Radiation therapy and chemotherapy: </strong>A thyroidectomy is often combined with radiation and chemotherapy treatments. Doctors and scientists are looking for ways to improve radiation therapy. For example, new ways to give radiation therapy have been developed that allow higher radiation doses over less time with more precision. The hope is to target the tumor without injuring the healthy nearby muscle and tissue.</p>
<p>ATC is a difficult disease to treat because of its ability to spread to the rest of the body. Research is being conducted on the different types of treatment options, and support networks are available for people with ATC.</p>
<h2>Does anaplastic thyroid cancer run in families?</h2>
<p>No, ATC does not run in families.</p>
<h2>How does anaplastic thyroid cancer form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms, but it can be hard to prove. ATC often starts in a thyroid that is already unhealthy. It can form within a <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000044545&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000044545&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">goiter</a> or it can arise from another thyroid cancer. Scientists have found many different changes in ATC cells, which tells them that there are likely many ways that ATC can start. This makes it very hard to develop a single treatment that can work for all ATC patients.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with anaplastic thyroid cancer?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="860491" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7337460" sys_variantid="2297">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate ATC survival rates by how groups of people with ATC have done in the past. Because there are so few ATC patients, these rates may not be very accurate. They also don&rsquo;t consider newer treatments being developed. ATC is one of the fastest growing cancers, with only half of people with ATC surviving 6 months after diagnosis. It is very important to work with a team of experts as soon as possible after diagnosis to improve your chances of survival. You can <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133262" sys_contentid="1133262" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133262" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7337461" sys_variantid="2297">contact MyPART</a> for help connecting with experts in ATC.</p>
<p>As scientists&nbsp;learn more about how ATC forms, new treatments will continue to be&nbsp;tested.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=43&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=814&amp;sys_contentid=15562" sys_contentid="15562" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="814" sys_dependentid="15562" rxinlineslot="103" sys_relationshipid="7337462" sys_variantid="814">National Cancer Institute &ndash; Thyroid Cancer Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/664/anaplastic-thyroid-cancer">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center &ndash; Anaplastic Thyroid Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?q=anaplastic+thyroid+cancer&amp;t=&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">NCI-Supported Clinical Trials</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133236" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is medullary thyroid cancer?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7344711">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637&amp;sys_command=edit" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Medullary thyroid cancer, or MTC, is a cancer that forms in the thyroid. The thyroid is a gland located in the front of your neck, just below the Adam&rsquo;s apple. It is responsible for sending out hormones to the rest of your body. The inside of the thyroid is called the medulla. The medulla contains special cells called parafollicular C cells that produce and release hormones. MTC happens when the C cells become cancerous and grow out of control. MTC may also be called medullary thyroid carcinoma.</p>
<h2>How common is medullary thyroid cancer?</h2>
<p>Thyroid cancer is fairly common. There are four different types of thyroid cancers and MTC is the rarest type making up 3% to 4% of all thyroid cancers. About 1,000 people are diagnosed with MTC each year in the U.S.</p>
<h2>How is medullary thyroid cancer diagnosed?</h2>
<p>MTC can start as a lump in the throat. The tumor growing in the thyroid can make your voice hoarse by blocking your vocal chords or it can make it hard to breathe by blocking your windpipe. Sometimes people can have MTC for a long time without symptoms because the tumor&nbsp;remains small. MTC can spread to other organs, such as lung, liver, bones, and brain.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>MTC is diagnosed by your doctor first feeling your throat to check for a lump, followed by imaging scans of the thyroid. Imaging scans might include ultrasound, CT, or MRI.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>The doctor will also want to take out a small amount of tissue, called a biopsy, from the thyroid using a very thin needle. A pathologist will look at the tissue under the microscope to see if there are cancer cells and, if so, what type of thyroid cancer it is.</p>
<h2>How is medullary thyroid cancer treated?</h2>
<p>MTC is usually treated by removing the thyroid. This surgery is called a thyroidectomy. In certain people with a high risk for MTC, such as people carrying certain gene changes, a thyroidectomy may be performed to prevent cancer.</p>
<p>Besides surgery, sometimes other treatments are also required, including radiation therapy or chemotherapy. Also, targeted therapies are available that act on changes in DNA found in some cases of MTC.</p>
<p>After treatment, your doctor will monitor levels of a tumor marker called CEA and the hormones produced by C cells to keep track of how well the treatment is working or if cancer has come back. CEA is a type of tumor marker found in the blood of those with MTC.</p>
<h2>Does medullary thyroid cancer run in families?</h2>
<p>Twenty-five percent of MTC cases run in families. MTC may be passed down when families carry a change in the <em>RET</em> gene that causes a condition called multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2, or MEN2. There are two types of MEN2: MEN2A and MEN2B.</p>
<p><strong>MEN2A:</strong> If you have MEN2A, you have a high chance (90%) of getting MTC. You are also at risk (30% to 50%) for getting pheochromocytoma, a cancer of the adrenal glands. MEN2A is rare, affecting 1 in 40,000 people. MEN2A may also be called Sipple syndrome or PTC syndrome.</p>
<p><strong>MEN2B</strong>: MEN2B can sometimes be passed from parent to child but most of the time, it isn&rsquo;t. If you have MEN2B, you have a 100% chance of getting MTC at a very young age. You also have a 50% chance of getting pheochromocytoma at some point in your life. MEN2B is also called Wagenmann&ndash;Froboese&nbsp;syndrome or MEN3.</p>
<h2>How does medullary thyroid cancer form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms but it can be hard to prove. We know that some MTC cases have changes in the <em>RET </em>gene. MTC is also more common in females than males. This information gives scientists clues about how MTC forms and can lead to new treatments.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with medullary thyroid cancer?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>If the cancer responds to chemotherapy</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7344708">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate MTC survival rates by how groups of people with MTC patients have done in the past. Given that there are so few MTC patients, survival rates may not be very accurate. They also don&rsquo;t consider newer treatments being developed. We know that people can live with MTC for many years, even though there is no cure.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=43&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=814&amp;sys_contentid=15562" sys_contentid="15562" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="814" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="15562" sys_variantid="814" sys_relationshipid="7344709">National Cancer Institute &ndash; Thyroid Cancer Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/7004/thyroid-cancer-medullary">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center &ndash; MTC</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?q=medullary+thyroid+carcinoma&amp;t=&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">NCI-Supported Clinical Trials</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133238" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is angiosarcoma?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7337495">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Angiosarcoma is a rare cancer that develops in the inner lining of blood vessels and lymph vessels. This cancer can occur anywhere in the body but most often is in the skin, breast, liver and spleen.</p>
<h2>How common is angiosarcoma?</h2>
<p>For every&nbsp;million people, one will be diagnosed with angiosarcoma per year in the U.S. Angiosarcomas make up about 1% to 2% of all sarcomas. They are most common in people over the age of 70 but can happen at any age.</p>
<h2>How is angiosarcoma diagnosed?</h2>
<p>Angiosarcomas often look like a bruised, purple-ish area on the skin. These areas may bleed easily when they are scratched or bumped. They grow larger over time and the skin around the bruised area can swell.</p>
<p>You may have pain in the area where the tumor is growing. If the angiosarcoma is growing deeper in your body (such as in the liver), and not towards the skin&rsquo;s surface, you may not notice as many symptoms. It is sometimes possible to feel the lump.</p>
<p><strong>Imaging: </strong>If you have symptoms, your doctor will use imaging scans such as MRI, CT, or PET scan to look at the tumor's size&nbsp;and location.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy: </strong>To check if the tumor is angiosarcoma, your doctor will perform a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. A pathologist will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is.</p>
<h2>How is angiosarcoma treated?</h2>
<p>Angiosarcoma is a fast-growing cancer, so your doctors will treat it aggressively.</p>
<p><strong>Surgery</strong>: Doctors will remove as much of the angiosarcoma as possible with surgery but sometimes it is not possible due to the location.</p>
<p><strong>Radiation Therapy:</strong> Radiation therapy can be used around the time of surgery. The radiation is aimed at the tumor area to prevent it from growing back after it is removed. Radiation therapy may also be used if your angiosarcoma cannot be removed with surgery.</p>
<p><strong>Chemotherapy: </strong>If your tumor has spread to other parts of your body, chemotherapy may be used to kill the cancer cells. Chemotherapy may also be combined with radiation therapy if your angiosarcoma cannot be removed by surgery.</p>
<p>Doctors and scientists are developing new treatments for angiosarcoma.</p>
<h2>Does angiosarcoma run in families?</h2>
<p>Angiosarcoma can sometimes run in families. Scientists have found that people with a change in a gene called <em>POT1 </em>may develop angiosarcoma of the heart, and this change can be passed on to their children.</p>
<h2>How does angiosarcoma form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms, but it can be hard to prove. We know that some risk factors for getting angiosarcoma include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lymphedema, a problem in which extra lymph fluid builds up in tissues,&nbsp;causing swelling, usually in the arms or legs</li>
<li>Past radiation therapy, such as treatment for breast cancer or Hodgkin lymphoma</li>
<li>Exposure to some cancer-causing chemicals</li>
</ul>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with angiosarcoma?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has&nbsp;<a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="860491" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7337493" sys_variantid="2297">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate survival rates by how groups of people with angiosarcomas have done in the past. Given that there are so few angiosarcoma patients, survival rates may not be accurate. They also do not&nbsp;consider newer treatments being developed.</p>
<p>People with low-grade breast angiosarcoma survive longer than people with other types of this cancer. Many people with angiosarcoma aren&rsquo;t diagnosed until their cancer has already spread to other parts of the body, which often results in a worse prognosis.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=52&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1050998" sys_contentid="1050998" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="990" sys_dependentid="1050998" rxinlineslot="103" sys_relationshipid="7337494" sys_variantid="990">National Cancer Institute &ndash; Childhood&nbsp;Vascular Tumors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/5814/angiosarcoma-of-the-scalp">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center &ndash; Angiosarcoma of the Scalp</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?t=C3088%7CC9040&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">National Cancer Institute sponsored clinical trials&nbsp; for Angiosarcoma</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133239" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is an epithelioid hemangioendothelioma?</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7344725">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvArticle">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Link to Participate in Trial page" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133467&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1137637&amp;sys_command=edit" /></div>
<h3>Participate in Our Trial</h3>
<p>You can help speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Epithelioid hemangioendothelioma (EHE or eHAE) is a rare cancer that grows from the cells that make up blood vessels. This cancer can occur anywhere in the body with the most common sites being bones, liver, and lungs. It usually happens in people between 30 and 50 years of age but can occur in young children and the elderly.</p>
<h2>How common is epithelioid hemangioendothelioma?</h2>
<p>EHE is very rare, with only one in every one million people affected worldwide. Around 20 cases are diagnosed in the United States per year.</p>
<h2>How is epithelioid hemangioendothelioma diagnosed?</h2>
<p>People with EHE will have different symptoms depending on where the tumor is located. Common symptoms include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pain and swelling around the tumor area</li>
<li>Weight loss</li>
<li>Problems moving or walking</li>
<li>Skin lumps and bumps that may appear red or blue</li>
<li>Broken bones</li>
<li>Coughing up blood and trouble breathing</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Imaging</strong>: If you have symptoms of EHE, your doctor will take images of the tumor using MRI, CT, X-ray, or PET scan to determine the size and location of the tumor. These factors determine which treatment options are available.</p>
<p><strong>Biopsy:</strong> To check if the tumor is EHE, your doctor will perform a biopsy, taking a small sample from the tumor with a needle. <a name="_Hlk536023130"></a>A pathologist will study cells from the sample under the microscope to see what kind of tumor it is.</p>
<h2>How is epithelioid hemangioendothelioma treated?</h2>
<p>Given that EHE is so rare, there is no standard treatment. Treatment for EHE depends on where it starts and if it has spread, which is different for each patient. You should go to an expert in tumors that form in blood vessels to decide the best approach for your cancer. You can <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133262" sys_contentid="1133262" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133262" sys_relationshipid="7344720" sys_variantid="2297">contact MyPART</a>&nbsp;for help finding experts near you.</p>
<p><strong>Surgery: </strong>Surgery is most often used to treat EHE. Surgery can also be combined with chemotherapy and radiation therapy.</p>
<p><strong>Radiation therapy:</strong> Doctors sometime use radiation therapy to treat EHE, with or without surgery. Because radiation therapy can cause other cancers in the future, it is important to discuss this option with your doctor.</p>
<p><strong>Chemotherapy: </strong>Doctors may combine chemotherapy with other treatments. It is important to discuss the&nbsp;side effects with your doctor.</p>
<p><strong>Targeted therapy:</strong> Because EHE is made up of cells that form blood vessels, some doctors are trying treatments that target tumor blood vessels. These treatments are called anti-angiogenics.</p>
<p><strong>Immunotherapy: </strong>Some doctors use interferon to treat EHE. Interferon may block the growth of tumors directly, block the growth of tumor blood vessels, or turn on the immune system to fight cancer.</p>
<h2>Does epithelioid hemangioendothelioma run in families?</h2>
<p>No, EHE is not passed down in families.</p>
<h2>How does epithelioid hemangioendothelioma form?</h2>
<p>Scientists are always working to understand how cancer forms, but it can be hard to prove. We think that in EHE, chromosomes (the parts of your cells that contain all of your genes) break apart and get put back together in the wrong way. This can cause cells to not function like they should. In most EHEs, the <em>WWTR</em> gene that makes the TAZ protein joins with the <em>CAMTA1</em> gene. In a small number of EHEs, the <em>YAP</em> gene joins with the <em>TFE3</em> gene. <em>TAZ</em> and <em>YAP</em> work together to drive growth and scientists are looking at ways to block them. Doctors may look for these changes in chromosomes to confirm that the cancer is EHE.</p>
<h2>What is the prognosis for someone with epithelioid hemangioendothelioma?</h2>
<p>The estimate of how a disease will affect you long-term is called prognosis. Every person is different and prognosis will depend on many factors, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where the tumor is in your body</li>
<li>If the cancer has spread to other parts of your body</li>
<li>How much of the tumor was taken out during surgery</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want information on your prognosis, it is important to talk to your doctor. NCI also has&nbsp;<a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=41&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=860491" sys_contentid="860491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="860491" sys_relationshipid="7344721" sys_variantid="2297">resources to help you understand cancer prognosis</a>.</p>
<p>Doctors estimate survival rates by how groups of people with EHE have done in the past. Given that&nbsp;there are so few EHE patients, survival rates may not be very accurate and&nbsp;do not consider newer treatments being developed.</p>
<p>The course of the disease for people with EHE can be hard to predict. Some people live a long time, even without treatment. In other cases, the cancer grows quickly and spreads, even with treatment. Some of this depends on where the EHE is located, so it is very important to discuss your case with you doctor to understand your prognosis.</p>
<h2>For More Information</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=52&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=990&amp;sys_contentid=1050998" sys_contentid="1050998" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="990" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1050998" sys_relationshipid="7344722" sys_variantid="990">National Cancer Institute &ndash; Childhood Vascular Tumors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/6557/hemangioendothelioma">Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center &ndash; Hemangioendothelioma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/r?t=C114923%7CC3800&amp;a=&amp;z=&amp;rl=1">National Cancer Institute sponsored clinical trials - Epithelioid Hemangioendothelioma</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133248" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>We know that studying rare tumors is difficult. Finding treatments for rare cancer requires a multi-institutional effort to collect specimens for research and accrue patients to clinical trials. Robust model systems often don&rsquo;t exist. These issues put rare tumor researchers at a disadvantage and discourage innovation in the field.</p>
<h2>How MyPART Is Addressing Challenges in Rare Tumor Research</h2>
<p>MyPART is addressing rare tumor research challenges through data and biospecimen collection and sharing, clinics, and workshops.</p>
<h3>Data</h3>
<p>MyPART is collecting genomic and other molecular data on rare tumors that are&nbsp;matched to clinical data and patient-reported outcomes. Data will be made available to researchers as they are&nbsp;collected. We are conducting longitudinal studies so researchers can follow the effects of treatments on rare tumors over time.</p>
<h3>Biospecimens</h3>
<p>As part of the <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133251" sys_contentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7344758" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133251" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305">Natural History Study of Rare Solid&nbsp;Tumors</a>, we are collecting biospecimens from people with rare tumors to catalog the following data:</p>
<ul>
<li>Genome</li>
<li>Epigenome</li>
<li>Transcriptome</li>
<li>Immunolome</li>
<li>Gut microbiome</li>
</ul>
<p>Samples not needed for these analyses will be banked for future studies.</p>
<h3>Clinics</h3>
<p>For some rare tumors, we hold yearly <a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1133257&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133257" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7344760">multi-day clinics</a> at the NIH Clinical Center in Bethesda, MD, in collaboration with advocacy groups. These clinics bring experts and people with rare tumors from around the country together to focus on how the rare cancer affects the patient and how therapies affect the cancer.</p>
<p>People with rare tumors benefit by having their cases reviewed by many experts at once and by spending time with others with the same disease.</p>
<p>Experts benefit by seeing many patients at the same time and exchanging ideas on the best way to care for them. These clinics often form the basis for future collaborations in rare tumor research.</p>
<h3>Workshops</h3>
<p>In addition to clinics, we promote communication and collaboration through workshops and symposia. These workshops bring together basic and clinical researchers, advocates, and FDA representatives to discuss how to overcome barriers to developing new treatments. Discussions are facilitated through presentations and breakout sessions. These workshops often allow researchers to take stock of where the field is and where it is headed.<a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133249" sys_contentid="1133249" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7344756" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133249" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305"> Learn more about our recent workshops.</a></p>
<h2>How to Get Involved</h2>
<p>If you are interested in collaborating with us on rare tumor research, please contact us at <a href="mailto:NCICCRRareTumors@mail.nih.gov">NCICCRRareTumors@mail.nih.gov</a>. &nbsp;</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133249" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>We hold workshops in the Center for Cancer Research to help scientists learn what to study about rare cancer. During these workshops:</p>
<ul>
<li>Scientists come together to share their research.</li>
<li>Advocates come to share issues that are important to patients.</li>
<li>Clinicians come to share their experience treating the rare cancer.</li>
<li>FDA representatives come to help researchers design experiments and clinical trials with the best chance of drug approval.</li>
</ul>
<p>Workshops we have held in the past include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Malignant Peripheral Nerve Sheath Tumor (MPNST)</li>
<li>Merkel Cell Carcinoma</li>
<li>Chordoma</li>
</ul>
<h2>Malignant Peripheral Nerve Sheath Tumor (MPNST) Workshop</h2>
<p>&nbsp;&ldquo;MPNST State of the Science: Outlining a Research Agenda for the Future,&rdquo; was a workshop held in Bethesda, MD on October 6-7, 2016.</p>
<p>The goals of the workshop were to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Summarize findings on MPNST since the last consensus meeting in 2002</li>
<li>Find barriers and knowledge gaps</li>
<li>Find the best chances for future progress</li>
<li>Make plans for working together</li>
</ul>
<p>The workshop was co-sponsored by the Center of Cancer Research and the Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, NCI, and the Children&rsquo;s Tumor Foundation. Before the workshop, the organizers wrote a summary of MPNST research to date and published it in an <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28592921">article by Kim et al., 2017</a>. Fifty-six experts came from the U.S. and four other countries. Dr. Sasha Jumbe,&nbsp;from the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation gave a keynote talk on solving health problems. Seven pathologists from around the country met the day before the workshop to look at tumor cases. They came to agreement on how to describe tumors changing from benign to malignant and published their findings for the scientific community in an <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28551330">article by Miettinen et al., 2017</a>.</p>
<p>There were five topics that the experts focused on at the workshop:</p>
<ul>
<li>Clinical Trials Methodology</li>
<li>Diagnosis/Imaging/Primary Management</li>
<li>Genomics/Biomarkers</li>
<li>Preclinical Models</li>
<li>Pathology/Histology</li>
</ul>
<p>The experts agreed on the top priorities for research in each of these areas. The group published their findings for the scientific community in an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29117388">article by Reilly et al., 2017</a>.</p>
<h2>Merkel Cell Carcinoma Workshop</h2>
<p>An international workshop on Merkel Cell Carcinoma was held in Rockville, MD on March 5-6, 2018. It was co-sponsored by the NCI Center for Cancer Research, National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases, and the University of Michigan. Fifty-two experts from the U.S. and four other countries gathered to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Find the most important research questions</li>
<li>Build plans for research collaborations</li>
</ul>
<p>Giovanna Tosato (NCI), Connie Trimble (Johns Hopkins University), and Bernie Fox (Oregon Health and Sciences University) gave keynote talks.</p>
<p>The attendees broke into smaller groups to discuss issues in Merkel cell carcinoma research. The three groups were:</p>
<ul>
<li>Basic research</li>
<li>Translational research</li>
<li>Clinical research</li>
</ul>
<p>The results from the meeting were published for the scientific community in an <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=harms+p+brownell">article by Harms et al., 2018</a>.</p>
<h2>Chordoma Workshop</h2>
<p>The NCI Chordoma Workshop was held on June 15, 2018. It was sponsored by the Center for Cancer Research and planned with the help of the Chordoma Foundation. Thirty-eight experts gathered from across the U.S. to discuss plans for a chordoma clinic in the NCI Center for Cancer Research. The group reviewed how chordoma presents in children and families and how it differs from chordoma in adults. Doctors from the Center for Cancer Research described how rare tumor clinics work. The experts discussed four topics:</p>
<ul>
<li>How to design clinical trials for chordoma</li>
<li>New therapy options for chordoma</li>
<li>Measuring quality of life in chordoma patients</li>
<li>Molecular changes in chordoma and ways to test new treatments</li>
</ul>
<p>As a result of these discussions, the group agreed to move forward with a <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133257" sys_contentid="1133257" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133257" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7344727" sys_variantid="2297">Pediatric Chordoma Clinic</a> that is being planned for April 2019. The clinic is being planned based on the suggestions of doctors, scientists, advocates, and FDA representatives at this workshop.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133251" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is a natural history study?</h2>
<p>The purpose of a natural history study is to collect information, tissue and tumor samples, and data from patients to better understand how cancer develops and grows. When researchers don&rsquo;t know how cancer grows, it is much harder to design trials to test new treatments. Natural history studies help researchers understand cancer better. &nbsp;</p>
<p>In a natural history study, you will meet experts who often have more experience with rare cancer than your home medical team. These experts can advise you on treatments for your cancer. Also, detailed analysis of your cancer in the natural history study may point to treatment trials that you may be eligible for.</p>
<p>By taking part in a natural history study, you can speed up the development of new treatments by giving researchers the tools they need to understand how cancer forms and grows, and to find new treatments. Researchers use natural history studies to look for trends and get new ideas on how to treat rare cancers.</p>
<p>Unlike treatment trials, natural history studies don&rsquo;t test whether new treatments work and are safe. Because you are not exposed to any experimental treatment, natural history studies are considered very safe. &nbsp;</p>
<h2>What is the Natural History Study of Rare Solid Tumors?</h2>
<p>The Natural History Study of Rare Solid Tumors is a natural history trial taking place at the NIH Clinical Center in Bethesda, Maryland. The purpose of the trial is to collect information and samples from people with rare tumors and their relatives, and track their health histroy over a long period of time.</p>
<p>During this trial, we hope to learn more about how rare tumors develop and progress and new ways to control them.</p>
<h2>How You Can Take Part in Our Study</h2>
<p>The Natural History Study of Rare Solid Tumors is enrolling people in two ways.</p>
<p>At first, you will provide information and a saliva sample from home. We will also request your medical records from your doctor and any samples of your cancer that may be available from a prior biopsy or surgery. Then, we will review your information and combine it with information from other patients to get a clearer understanding of your cancer. We will keep in touch with you to learn more about how you are doing and to let you know what we are learning about rare cancer.</p>
<p>Based on the review of your medical records, you might be invited to the NIH Clinical Center, where you will meet with a team of expert doctors and other healthcare providers. They will run more detailed tests on your cancer and can answer any questions related to your treatment.</p>
<h2>Can I still get treatment for my rare cancer?</h2>
<p>Yes, you can receive treatment for your cancer while in the natural history study. You can have standard treatment or take part in a treatment trial. We are partnering with researchers who are running treatment trials that accept rare cancer patients. If you are eligible, we will help you join these trials. We will also let you know if a new trial opens that may be right for you.</p>
<h2>How can I get more information or join the study?</h2>
<p>For specific questions about our Natural History Study of Rare Solid Tumors, email&nbsp;<a href="mailto:NCICCRRareTumorClinic@mail.nih.gov">NCICCRRareTumorClinic@mail.nih.gov</a><span>.</span><span> You can also see our </span><span></span><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133262" sys_contentid="1133262" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133262" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7328932" sys_variantid="2297"><span>Contact Us</span><span> page</span></a><span> for other ways to find out information or join to a clinical trial.</span></p>
<p>Eligibility criteria&nbsp;and other details are available in the study&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials/search/v?q=NCT03739827&amp;loc=0&amp;rl=1&amp;id=NCI-2018-03297&amp;pn=1&amp;ni=10">protocol summary</a>.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133253" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>In the MyPART network, our mission is to engage patients as partners in rare tumor research. Advocacy groups are a critical bridge between patients and researchers,&nbsp;helping share experiences and expertise between these important stakeholders. Non-profit organizations dedicated to improving the experiences and outcomes of people with rare solid tumors are important members of the MyPART network.</p>
<h2>How We Can Work Together</h2>
<p>Our goal is to work with you, our advocacy partners, to raise awareness and provide education about the tumors we study.</p>
<p>We will:</p>
<ul>
<li>share information about our research activities and clinical trials for you to disseminate to your constituents.</li>
<li>provide your group with summaries of the latest research findings written for lay audiences about your rare tumors of interest.</li>
<li>include representatives from your group in workshops and focus groups at NCI.</li>
<li>link to your website to help people find your support and educational services.</li>
<li>provide you with the MyPART network badge to display on your website indicating your membership in the network.</li>
</ul>
<p>You will:</p>
<ul>
<li>provide valuable input on issues important to the people you represent, so we can make sure our research is centered on the needs of people with rare tumors.</li>
<li>link to the MyPART website to help people with rare tumors find information on the MyPART network.</li>
<li>share news with your constituents about MyPART clinical trials and other opportunities for involvement.</li>
</ul>
<h2>How to Join Our Network&nbsp;</h2>
<p>To learn more about having your group become a member of the MyPART network, please email <span><a href="mailto:NCICCRRareTumors@mail.nih.gov">NCICCRRareTumors@mail.nih.gov</a></span><span> for more information.</span></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133255" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>What is the role of caregivers?</h2>
<p>When your loved one has a rare cancer, it can affect your entire family. Parents, spouses, adult children, or other loved ones often need to handle details of medical care and provide physical and emotional support.</p>
<p>With medical care, there&nbsp;are many appointments to schedule and go to with the patient. Sometimes you need to go on long-distance trips with the patient to see expert doctors. You may need to help the patient keep track of medicines and their treatment plan. You can also help by <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=20&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=176775" sys_contentid="176775" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="1764" sys_relationshipid="7328950" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="176775" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">asking questions and raising concerns with doctors</a>. And, you can share news and updates with their family and friends.</p>
<p>You may need to help your loved one with daily tasks, especially during treatment. Your loved one may have side effects from treatment that can make them feel tired, dizzy, or nauseous. This can make it hard for them to safely bathe, dress, or prepare food without help.</p>
<p>Having cancer can be overwhelming or scary at times and people with rare tumors need emotional support. You may need to help your loved one <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=29&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=858130" sys_contentid="858130" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7328951" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="858130" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">cope with difficult feelings</a>. This may include listening when they need to vent or comforting them when they feel sad, worried, angry or frustrated. You may also need to figure out when they need help from a counselor or therapist.&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What supports are available for caregivers?</h2>
<p>Caring for someone with cancer is hard. Caring for a loved one with a rare cancer can be even harder. Information about rare cancers may be harder to find. You may feel lost or alone. But, there are <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=50&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=859801" sys_contentid="859801" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7328952" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="859801" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">many sources of support</a> to help families cope and handle the stress of having a rare cancer.</p>
<p>You can often find coping support at local hospitals. Support for you and your family can include counseling services, spiritual care, or child life services for siblings. Social workers and medical psychologists at hospitals are trained to help you when your loved one is sick. You can also seek out support from a provider in your community. Your doctor or your loved one&rsquo;s medical team may be able to refer you to someone in your area.</p>
<p>There also are many online resources to help caregivers cope. In particular, the National Cancer Institute has information for <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=57&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1034143" sys_contentid="1034143" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7328953" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1034143" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">families</a>&nbsp;and <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Psycho-Oncology/resources/support/siblings">siblings</a>.</p>
<p>Social media can connect you to other families facing rare cancers. You can share stories and learn about others&rsquo; experiences. Some social media websites link you to help from your community. This could include meal delivery, help with errands, or financial support.</p>
<p>Patient advocacy groups and support groups&nbsp;can be a great support for families facing rare cancers. These groups can give you reliable information about treatment or research on rare cancer. They may also help you connect with doctors or rare cancer researchers, or with other families experiencing the struggle with a rare cancer.</p>
<p>The National Cancer Institute <a href="https://supportorgs.cancer.gov/home.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">maintains a list of advocacy groups</a>.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133257" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1139367" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299480">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card cgvBlogPost">
<div class="image-hover"><img alt="Becky Owens and Sara Rothschild at the NIH Clinical Center" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=2074&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1134351&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139392&amp;sys_command=edit" /></div>
<h3>NCI&rsquo;s Rare Cancer Clinics Fostering Collaboration</h3>
<p>Clinics bring together clinicians, patients, and advocates.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><span>Each year, staff at the Center for Cancer Research and the MyPART team host&nbsp;</span>clinics on select rare cancers at the NIH Clinical Center in Bethesda, MD. These clinics include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pediatric and Wild-type GIST</li>
<li>Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma</li>
<li>Pediatric Chordoma&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p>During these one- to three-day meetings, people with the specific rare tumor and experts from around the country meet to learn more about the tumor from each other. Advocacy groups play an important role in helping us design these clinics. They can tell us what matters most to people with the tumor and find the right experts, so we study the most important issues.</p>
<h2>NIH Pediatric and Wild-type GIST Clinic</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/gist">NIH Pediatric and Wild-type GIST Clinic</a> started in 2008 to learn about gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST). Many GISTs have mutations in the <em>KIT</em> or <em>PDGFR</em> genes, but GISTs that don&rsquo;t have mutations in these genes were not well understood. These &ldquo;wild-type&rdquo; GISTs had no treatment options. This group includes most GISTs that occur in children.&nbsp;Because of the data collected in the clinic, it is now known that these tumors can form when succinate dehydrogenase (SDH) isn&rsquo;t working properly. This is giving scientists new ideas for how to treat these tumors.</p>
<h2>Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma Clinic</h2>
<p>The first medullary thyroid carcinoma clinic was held in 2018. This clinic brought together people whose tumor had started growing again after they had treatment. During the first clinic, experts talked about what patients should try next. Given that we have the clinic annually, we hope to find new clues about how to treat this tumor&nbsp;will arise to discuss.</p>
<h2>Pediatric Chordoma Clinic</h2>
<p>There are treatment trials for adult chordoma but children with chordoma may not be able to join the trials. Chordoma in children grows faster and can have different mutations than adult chordoma. We are planning a clinic to focus on children and young adults with chordoma in 2019. We will focus on how to detect chordoma. We will also learn how to use patients&rsquo; symptoms to make better treatments.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133260" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>MyPART is the My Pediatric and Adult Rare Tumor network. It is a group of scientists, patients, family members, advocates, and healthcare providers who want to help find treatments for rare cancers. We are working on childhood, teen, and young adult solid rare tumors that have no cures. We think that working as a team will help us find treatments for rare cancers faster. Everyone can play a part.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The MyPART network will:</p>
<ul>
<li>ask patients, their family members, and healthcare providers about how the rare tumor affects patients&rsquo; lives.</li>
<li>collect samples like blood, saliva, and biopsy tissue from people with rare tumors to study how rare tumors grow and how we could treat them.</li>
<li>share data from rare cancer samples with scientists around the world.</li>
<li>hold workshops with patients, advocates, doctors, and scientists to talk about how to improve patients&rsquo; lives and find new treatments.</li>
<li>build new ways of testing new treatments.</li>
<li>use what we learn to design new clinical trials for rare cancers.</li>
<li>teach the public about how we are trying to find new treatments.</li>
<li>share research results with individual patients.</li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133261" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>My Pediatric and Adult Rare Tumor Network (MyPART) is a team of doctors, nurses, scientists, and other staff, working together to improve the lives of children, adolescents, and young adults with rare solid tumors. Our team members come from different locations within the United States and around the world, bringing diverse interests. Here you can meet the members of the team at the Center for Cancer Research in the National Cancer Institute.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1139305" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299454">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139305&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h2>MyPART Leadership Team</h2>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136336" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299455">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Brigitte Widemann" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136336&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong><a href="https://irp.nih.gov/pi/brigitte-widemann">Brigitte C. Widemann, M.D.</a></strong> is co-leader of MyPART and Deputy Director of the Center for Cancer Research and Chief of the Pediatric Oncology Branch at NCI. She brings her expertise in pediatric oncology, natural history studies, and developing clinical trials for rare tumors to MyPART. She has been at NCI for 26 years. She grew up in Cologne, Germany and has&nbsp;six sisters. She is also a twin! She loves running, spending time outside, and watching soccer.</p>
</div>
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1135814" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299456">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Karlyne Reilly" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1135814&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Pediatric-Oncology-Branch/karlyne-m-reilly">Karlyne M. Reilly, Ph.D.</a></strong> is co-leader of MyPART and oversees a basic cancer research group in the Pediatric Oncology Branch in the Center for Cancer Research. She brings her expertise in mouse models of rare cancers and genome-wide data analysis to MyPART. She grew up in Berkeley, California and has been at NCI for 16 years. She loves oil painting and costume design whenever she has the time.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1135788" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299457">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Abby Sandler" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1135788&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Abby B. Sandler, Ph.D. </strong>is the executive director of MyPART. She brings her experience in cancer policy and advocacy, and program oversight to the MyPART team. She grew up in Yonkers, New York and has been at NCI for 22 years. She loves to cook and is an avid figure skating fan.</p>
</div>
</div>
<h2>MyPART Doctors</h2>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136337" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299458">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Jaydira del Rivero" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136337&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Pediatric-Oncology-Branch/jaydira-del-rivero">Jaydira del Rivero, M.D.</a> </strong>is a medical and endocrine oncologist and the principal investigator of the NCI Center for Cancer Research Natural History Study of Rare Tumors. She grew up in Veracruz, Mexico. She has been at NIH for&nbsp;eight years and at NCI for&nbsp;three years. She loves dancing and wishes she had more time for it.</p>
</div>
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136338" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299459">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="John Glod" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136338&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Pediatric-Oncology-Branch/john-w-glod">John Glod, M.D., Ph.D.</a></strong> is a pediatric oncologist/neuro oncologist and the Clinical Director of the Pediatric Oncology Branch in the Center for Cancer Research. He grew up in Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania, and roots for all Philadelphia sports teams. He has been at NCI for&nbsp;five years. He loves to go fishing.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1138955" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299460">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Fernanda Arnaldez" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1138955&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong><a href="https://ctep.cancer.gov/branches/idb/bios/arnaldez.htm">Fernanda Arnaldez, M.D.</a></strong> is a pediatric oncologist, the Scientific Officer of the NCI Experimental Therapeutics Clinical Trials Network, and Clinical Director of the SDH-Deficient NIH GIST Clinic. She brings her expertise in clinical trial design and rare tumor clinics to the MyPART network. She grew up in Buenos Aires, Argentina, but became a Steelers fan after living in Pittsburgh. She plays field hockey and the guitar, and loves throwing crazy dance parties for her children and their friends.</p>
</div>
</div>
<h2>MyPART Genetic Counselor</h2>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1135821" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299461">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Margarita Raygada" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1135821&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Margarita Raygada, Ph.D., M.M.Sc.</strong> is the genetic counselor for MyPART and an expert in hereditary cancer syndromes. She grew up in Venezuela and very recently joined NCI, after working on hereditary cancer syndromes in children at the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. She works to help families understand how their genes affect their health.</p>
</div>
</div>
<h2>MyPART Psychologists</h2>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136329" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299462">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Taryn Allen" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136329&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Taryn Allen, Ph.D. </strong>is a clinical psychologist for MyPART. She grew up in Connecticut and has been involved in pediatric cancer research for over a decade. Her favorite pastime is cooking and baking.</p>
</div>
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136335" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299463">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Pamela Wolters" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136335&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Pediatric-Oncology-Branch/pamela-l-wolters">Pam Wolters, Ph.D.</a></strong> co-directs the Behavioral Health Core and is head of the Neurobehavioral Research Program in the Pediatric Oncology Branch of the Center for Cancer Research. She has been at NCI for 30 years. She loves watching her kids play sports and enjoys the Washington Capitals, as well. She likes to swim and read. She used to compete in triathlons.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136328" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299464">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Staci Peron" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136328&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Pediatric-Oncology-Branch/staci-martin-peron">Staci Martin Peron, Ph.D.</a></strong> is the clinical director and training director of the Pediatric Psychology and Neurobehavioral Research Program of the Pediatric Oncology Branch. She grew up in Florida and has been at NCI for 18 years. She is committed to helping children with cancers or rare tumors and their families cope with the mental and psychological effects of cancer treatment.</p>
</div>
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136339" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299465">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Lori Wiener" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136339&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/Pediatric-Oncology-Branch/lori-wiener"><strong>Lori Wiener, Ph.D., D.C.S.W, L.C.S.W.-C.</strong></a> co-directs the Behavioral Health Core and is head of the Psychosocial Support and Research Program in the Pediatric Oncology Branch. She grew up in New York and has been at NCI for 32 years. She has developed many programs advancing psychosocial research and psychosocial care standards for patients and families who face life-threatening illnesses. Her favorite hobby is nature and portrait photography. Her family are huge Baltimore Ravens fans.</p>
</div>
</div>
<h2>MyPART Nurses</h2>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136340" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299466">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="BJ Thomas" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136340&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>BJ Thomas, R.N.</strong> is the lead research nurse for MyPART. She grew up in the Washington, D.C. area and has been working on NCI clinical studies for 15 years, and even longer at NIH. Her favorite sports are the Winter Olympics. She loves to travel and fondly remembers getting stranded in Italy when she missed her bus back to Rome.</p>
</div>
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1139356" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299467">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Laura Wisch" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139356&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Laura Wisch, R.N., M.S.N, C.C.R.P.</strong> is a research nurse supporting MyPART and has been at NCI for 19 years. She has brought her clinical research coordinator experience to the MyPART team. She grew up in Northern Kentucky and is retired from the US Army. In her spare time, she enjoys reading and skiing, and is an enthusiastic follower of Virginia Tech football.</p>
</div>
</div>
<h2>MyPART Clinical Research Support</h2>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1135829" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299468">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Sherri DePollar" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1135829&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Sherri DePollar</strong> is the Patient Care Coordinator for MyPART. She grew up in Maryland and has been with NCI for 13 years, and with NIH even longer. Her favorite teams are the Washington Redskins and DC United. In her spare time, she enjoys beading and making jewelry. Beyond her role as a patient care coordinator at NCI, she is also a certified Reiki Master and teacher.</p>
</div>
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136327" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299469">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Sarah Fuller" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136327&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Sarah Fuller</strong> is a post-baccalaureate fellow in the Pediatric Oncology Branch supporting MyPART and the weekly rare tumor clinic in the NIH Clinical Center. She grew up in Hartford, Connecticut and joined NCI this year. She loves to go sailing with her younger sisters.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136341" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299470">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Maran Illanchezhian" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136341&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Maran Ilanchezhian </strong>is a post-baccalaureate fellow in the Pediatric Oncology Branch supporting MyPART and annual clinics focused on individual rare tumors. He grew up in Herndon, Virginia and joined NCI this year. He loves all the Washington, DC sports teams and plays flag football on the weekends. He also enjoys hiking.</p>
</div>
</div>
<h2>MyPART Research Staff</h2>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136342" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299471">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Katie Pendo" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136342&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Katie Pendo, M.S.</strong> is a research technician supporting the analysis of biospecimens from the Natural History Study of Rare Tumors. She has been at NCI a little over&nbsp;one year. She grew up in Rapid City, South Dakota and enjoys keeping in touch with her friends and family around the world by videochat. Her favorite sports team is DC United, and her favorite hobby is playing video games.</p>
</div>
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1135820" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299472">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Francesco Tomassoni Ardori" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1135820&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Francesco Tomassoni Ardori, Ph.D. </strong>is a research technician designing new mouse models of rare tumors for MyPART using information gathered from the Natural History Study of Rare Tumors. He grew up in Italy and has been at NCI for&nbsp;eight years. His favorite pastime is windsurfing.</p>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Behind the Screens of MyPART</h2>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136343" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299473">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Jason Levine" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136343&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/jason-e-levine">Jason E. Levine, M.D.</a></strong> is Associate Director of the CCR Office of Information Technology. He specializes in developing systems to manage the flow of clinical data in large-scale clinical studies and brings his expertise to MyPART.</p>
</div>
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136998" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299474">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Christian Mambrin" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136998&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Christian J. Mambrin, M.S.</strong><span class="Apple-converted-space">&nbsp;</span>is the Program Manager for MyPART information technology. He has been at NCI for&nbsp;two years and grew up in Buenos Aires, Argentina. He likes rooting for the Pittsburgh Steelers and restoring antique electronics. Although a towering 6'5" he has never played basketball!</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="row collapse">
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136887" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299475">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Nurlanbek Shonkoev" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136887&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Nurlanbek Shonkoev, M.Eng.</strong> is the web developer and software engineer for the MyPART database and user interfaces. He joined NCI this year and is thankful for having the opportunity to contribute to the fight against cancer.</p>
</div>
<div class="columns large-5">
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1136884" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7299476">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="Yuti Gandhi" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133464&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1136884&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Yuti Gandhi</strong> develops web applications for MyPART. She joined NCI this year and grew up in India. She loves to travel. Her favorite sports are football and cricket.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1133262" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>There are several ways to get in touch with us and learn more about MyPART.</p>
<p>Sign up for news or get involved in rare tumor research by emailing <span><a href="mailto:NCICCRRareTumors@mail.nih.gov">NCICCRRareTumors@mail.nih.gov</a></span>.</p>
<p><span>Learn more&nbsp;about our <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133251" sys_contentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133251" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7265873" sys_variantid="2297" sys_folderid="">natural history trial for rare tumor patients</a></span><span>&nbsp;by emailing <a href="mailto:NCICCRRareTumorClinic@mail.nih.gov.">NCICCRRareTumorClinic@mail.nih.gov</a>.</span></p>
<p>Look for NCI-supported clinical trials using <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=12&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2285&amp;sys_contentid=1052944" sys_contentid="1052944" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2285" sys_dependentid="1052944" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7265874" sys_variantid="2285" sys_folderid="">NCI's Clinical Studies Search</a>.</p>
<p>If you want to join a clinical trial at the NIH Clinical Center, call the <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/clinical-trials/patients">CCR referral coordinator</a>&nbsp;at 1-888-NCI-1937 (1-888-624-1937) or the <a href="https://clinicalcenter.nih.gov/recruit/">Patient Recruitment and Liaison Office</a>&nbsp;at 1-800-411-1222</p>
<p>The <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=103&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=14539" sys_contentid="14539" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" sys_dependentid="14539" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="" sys_relationshipid="7265875" sys_variantid="1764" sys_folderid="">National Cancer Institute</a> is available to answer rare cancer questions via phone, chat, or email.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1134393" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Rare bone tumors include bone cancer and cartilage cancer. They can be called by different names depending on where they are in the body. For example, a chordoma tumor that forms at the skull base might be called a clival tumor, and one that forms near the tailbone might be&nbsp;called a sacral tumor.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Some of the rare bone tumors that affect children, adolescents, and young adults are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133218" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="7316128" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133218" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1133218">Adamantinoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133220" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="7316129" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133220" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1133220">Chordoma</a></li>
</ul>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1145631" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7316131">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133175&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1145631" alt="diagram of a skeleton on a femal figure and diagram of the spine seen from the side with the differnt sections labeled" /><!--Comment--> <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1518&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133175&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1145631" target="_blank" class="article-image-enlarge no-resize" rel="noopener noreferrer" sys_variantid="1518" sys_contentid="1145631">Enlarge</a></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Bone tumors can form in different parts of the skeleton (left). Bone tumors that form in the spine, which is part of the skeleton, are named after the area of the spine where they grow.</p>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1134552" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Rare soft tissue tumors form in the body&rsquo;s soft tissues such as muscle, fat, tendons, ligaments, lymph and blood vessels, nerves, or other tissue that connects and supports the body. These cancers can develop anywhere but are found mostly in the arms, legs, chest, and abdomen. They can be called by different names depending on the tissue where they start and what they look like under the microscope. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>Some of the rare soft tissue tumors that affect children, teens, and young adults are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133222" sys_contentid="1133222" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133222" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7334057" sys_variantid="2297">Alveolar soft part sarcomas</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133223" sys_contentid="1133223" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133223" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7334058" sys_variantid="2297">Desmoid tumor</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133225" sys_contentid="1133225" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133225" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7334059" sys_variantid="2297">Inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133227" sys_contentid="1133227" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133227" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7334060" sys_variantid="2297">Synovial sarcoma</a></li>
</ul>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1139383" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7334062">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133177&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139383&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--> <a class="article-image-enlarge no-resize" href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1518&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133177&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139383&amp;sys_command=edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" sys_variantid="1518" sys_contentid="1139383">Enlarge</a></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Soft tissue makes up many parts of the body and can form different kinds of tumors</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1134553" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Rare digestive system tumors form in organs that are important for digesting food and drinks. These organs include your esophagus, stomach, intestines, liver, and pancreas. The cancer may be named by the organ (liver cancer or stomach cancer) or by the type of cell&nbsp;it looks like (neuroendocrine, squamous cell, or stromal cell).&nbsp;</p>
<p>Some of the rare digestive system tumors that affect children, teens, and young adults are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133231" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133231" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7260147" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1133231">Fibrolamellar hepatocellular carcinoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133232" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133232" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7260148" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1133232">SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST)</a></li>
</ul>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1139385" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7262956">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133179&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139385" alt="" /><!--Comment--> <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1518&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133179&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139385" target="_blank" class="article-image-enlarge no-resize" rel="noopener noreferrer" sys_variantid="1518" sys_contentid="1139385">Enlarge</a></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1134554" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Rare endocrine tumors form in glands or in cells that produce hormones. These include your thyroid, adrenal, and pituitary glands, and cells in your pancreas. Endocrine tumors can be called by different names depending on where they are in the body or what type of cell they look like.</p>
<p>Some of the rare endocrine tumors that affect children, teens, and young adults are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133234" sys_contentid="1133234" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7260191" sys_folderid="" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133234" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Adrenocortical carcinoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133235" sys_contentid="1133235" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7260192" sys_folderid="" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133235" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Anaplastic thyroid cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133236" sys_contentid="1133236" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7260193" sys_folderid="" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133236" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Medullary thyroid cancer</a></li>
</ul>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1139386" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7264237">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1134557&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139386&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--> <a class="article-image-enlarge no-resize" href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1518&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1134557&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1139386&amp;sys_command=edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" sys_variantid="1518" sys_contentid="1139386">Enlarge</a></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1134555" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Rare vascular tumors form in cells that make blood or lymph vessels. They can occur anywhere in the body, such as the skin, in the tissues below the skin, or in an organ. These tumors are named for the type of cells they look like and how they grow. &nbsp;</p>
<p>Some of the rare vascular tumors that affect children, teens, and young adults are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133238" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133238" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7315970" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1133238">Angiosarcoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133239" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133239" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7315971" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1133239">Epithelioid hemangioendothelioma</a></li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2082" sys_dependentid="1145587" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7315973">
<figure class="image-center centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133183&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1145587" alt="diagrams of the ciculatory system on the female body and the lymphatic system on a male body" /><!--Comment--> <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1518&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1133183&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1145587" target="_blank" class="article-image-enlarge no-resize" rel="noopener noreferrer" sys_variantid="1518" sys_contentid="1145587">Enlarge</a></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Vascular cancers can form from the cells of the circulatory system, which is made up of blood vessels (left). They can also form from the cells that make up the lymphatic system, which carries a clear liquid called lymph that is important for the immune system (right).</p>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1134559" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>When you are diagnosed with a rare cancer, you and your family may think about joining a clinical trial or study. Much of what scientists have learned about cancer has come from rare cancer patients sharing their experience and tissue. You can help future rare cancer patients by helping researchers today.</p>
<p>A clinical trial may give you access to a new drug. It may also be a chance to see doctors that are world experts in your rare cancer. Clinical trials that test a new treatment are often called intervention trials. Clinical trials that learn more about the rare cancer without trying to treat it may be called <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133251" sys_contentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7316111" sys_dependentid="1133251" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_siteid="305">natural history studies</a>.&nbsp;</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="1835" sys_dependentid="1145620" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7316115">
<figure class="video left size50">
<div class="flex-video widescreen" id="ytplayer-zn5hcnhO9LU" data-video-id="zn5hcnhO9LU" data-video-title="Pediatric Oncology: A Tour for New Patients"><noscript>			&lt;p&gt;				&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zn5hcnhO9LU" target="_blank" title="Pediatric Oncology: A Tour for New Patients"&gt;					View this video on YouTube.				&lt;/a&gt;			&lt;/p&gt;		</noscript></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><span>Clinical trials for common cancer may fill up quickly, but clinical trials for rare cancers can take much longe</span>r to complete. Sometimes drugs for rare cancers cannot be tested properly because there aren&rsquo;t enough people with the rare tumor to join the trial. When you have a rare tumor, you can make a big difference by joining a study.Keeping Families Together During Studies at the NIH Clinical Center&nbsp;</p>
<p>It can be hard on families when a child or teen is in a clinical trial because they may need to travel far from home to participate. Children with cancer who come to the NIH Clinical Center can stay with their families for free at <a href="https://childrensinn.org/for-inn-families/">The Children&rsquo;s Inn</a>. You can take a virtual tour of The Children&rsquo;s Inn to learn what it is like to stay there. You can also <a href="https://childrensinn.org/category/stories/family-stories/">read about other families&rsquo; experiences at The Children&rsquo;s Inn</a>.&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Where to Learn More About Participating in a Rare Cancer Clinical Trial</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="1839" sys_dependentid="591269" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7316116">
<figure class="video right size50">
<div class="flex-video widescreen" id="ytplayer-HuxA_ccCnUg" data-video-id="HuxA_ccCnUg" data-video-title="What are clinical trials?"><noscript>			&lt;p&gt;				&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HuxA_ccCnUg" target="_blank" title="What are clinical trials?"&gt;					View this video on YouTube.				&lt;/a&gt;			&lt;/p&gt;		</noscript></div>
<figcaption class="caption-container">
<p>Health professionals, people with cancer and their loved ones discuss what clinical trials are, why they are important, and how your safety is protected.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You may have mixed feelings or have a lot of questions about taking part in a clinical trial. It may help to know what to expect. The National Cancer Institute has <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=102&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=63867" sys_contentid="63867" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="7316109" sys_dependentid="63867" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_siteid="305">resources to help you understand what you can expect</a>.</p>
<p>You should know that joining a clinical trial is your choice. You are in control and can drop out of the trial if you feel it is not right for you. You should also understand that there are <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=40&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=63858" sys_contentid="63858" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7316108" sys_dependentid="63858" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_siteid="305">systems to protect your privacy and your safety</a>. The trial doctors and nurses are happy to answer your questions to help you know if the trial is the right choice for you.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1137813" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>MyPART team members are participating in upcoming meetings to talk about our programs. If you are interested in learning more about MyPART you can find us at the following events.</p>
<p>For more information about our upcoming events, email&nbsp;<a href="mailto:NCICCRRareTumors@mail.nih.gov">NCICCRRareTumors@mail.nih.gov</a>.</p>
<h2>Past Events</h2>
<h3>American Society for Clinical Oncology Annual Meeting, May 31, 2019</h3>
<p>Several members of the MyPART team attended the <a href="https://meetings.asco.org/am/register-submit-abstracts">American Society for Clinical Oncology Annual Meeting</a> in Chicago, IL from May 31 through June 4, 2019.</p>
<h3>American Association for Cancer Research Annual Meeting, April 1, 2019</h3>
<p>MyPART co-organized an NCI, NIH sponsored panel at the <a href="https://www.aacr.org/Meetings/Pages/MeetingDetail.aspx?EventItemID=174&amp;DetailItemID=942">American Association for Cancer Research Annual Meeting</a> in Atlanta, GA. The session was titled &ldquo;New NCI Collaborative Initiatives on Rare Tumors and RASopathies.&rdquo; We presented an overview of MyPART and the research we are doing to find treatments for rare cancers.</p>
<h3>Rare Disease Day at NIH, February 28, 2019</h3>
<p>Members of the MyPART team will be &ldquo;showing our stripes&rdquo; on <a href="https://ncats.nih.gov/rdd">Rare Disease Day at NIH in Bethesda, MD</a>. Rare Disease Day is a worldwide event on Feb 28, 2019 for people with rare diseases. MyPART is co-organizing a panel to discuss &ldquo;Success Factors for Rare Cancer Research &ndash; Building Strong Foundations.&rdquo; We will also be in the exhibit area, so please stop by and see us if you plan to attend.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1139288" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1133525" sys_contentid="1133525" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1133525" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262058" sys_variantid="2317">Rare Tumors</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133216" sys_contentid="1133216" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133216" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262059" sys_variantid="2297">About Rare Cancers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1134393" sys_contentid="1134393" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1134393" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262060" sys_variantid="2297">Rare Bone Tumors</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133218" sys_contentid="1133218" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133218" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262061" sys_variantid="2297">Adamantinoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133220" sys_contentid="1133220" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133220" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262062" sys_variantid="2297">Chordoma</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1134553" sys_contentid="1134553" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1134553" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262063" sys_variantid="2297">Rare Digestive System Tumors</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133231" sys_contentid="1133231" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133231" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262064" sys_variantid="2297">Fibrolamellar hepatocellular carcinoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133232" sys_contentid="1133232" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133232" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262065" sys_variantid="2297">SDH-deficient gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST)</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1134554" sys_contentid="1134554" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1134554" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262066" sys_variantid="2297">Rare Endocrine Tumors</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133234" sys_contentid="1133234" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133234" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262067" sys_variantid="2297">Adrenocortical carcinoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133235" sys_contentid="1133235" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133235" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262068" sys_variantid="2297">Anaplastic thyroid cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133236" sys_contentid="1133236" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133236" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262069" sys_variantid="2297">Medullary thyroid cancer</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1134552" sys_contentid="1134552" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1134552" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262070" sys_variantid="2297">Rare Soft Tissue Tumors</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133222" sys_contentid="1133222" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133222" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262071" sys_variantid="2297">Alveolar soft part sarcomas</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133223" sys_contentid="1133223" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133223" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262072" sys_variantid="2297">Desmoid tumor</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133225" sys_contentid="1133225" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133225" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262073" sys_variantid="2297">Inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133227" sys_contentid="1133227" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133227" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262074" sys_variantid="2297">Synovial sarcoma</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1134555" sys_contentid="1134555" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1134555" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262075" sys_variantid="2297">Rare Vascular Tumors</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133238" sys_contentid="1133238" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133238" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262076" sys_variantid="2297">Angiosarcoma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133239" sys_contentid="1133239" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133239" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262077" sys_variantid="2297">Epithelioid hemangioendothelioma</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1133526" sys_contentid="1133526" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1133526" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262078" sys_variantid="2317">Research</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133249" sys_contentid="1133249" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133249" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262079" sys_variantid="2297">Rare Tumor Workshops</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133248" sys_contentid="1133248" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133248" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262080" sys_variantid="2297">Challenges for Rare Tumor Researchers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1133502" sys_contentid="1133502" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1133502" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262081" sys_variantid="2317">Participate</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133251" sys_contentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133251" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262082" sys_variantid="2297">Natural History Study of Rare Solid Tumors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1134559" sys_contentid="1134559" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1134559" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262083" sys_variantid="2297">Participating in a Clinical Trial for Rare Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133253" sys_contentid="1133253" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133253" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262084" sys_variantid="2297">The Role of Advocacy in MyPART</a></li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133255" sys_contentid="1133255" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133255" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262085" sys_variantid="2297">Support</a></h2>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133258" sys_contentid="1133258" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133258" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262086" sys_variantid="2297">News</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133257" sys_contentid="1133257" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133257" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262087" sys_variantid="2297">Rare Tumor Clinics</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1137813" sys_contentid="1137813" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1137813" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262088" sys_variantid="2297">Upcoming Events</a></li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1133447" sys_contentid="1133447" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1133447" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262089" sys_variantid="2317">About</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133260" sys_contentid="1133260" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133260" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262090" sys_variantid="2297">What Is MyPART?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133261" sys_contentid="1133261" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133261" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262091" sys_variantid="2297">MyPART Team</a></li>
<li><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133262" sys_contentid="1133262" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1133262" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7262092" sys_variantid="2297">Contact MyPART</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1145882" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Recent news about the MyPART program and other advances in the study of rare tumors.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1147225" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="&lt;div sys_dependentvariantid=&quot;2088&quot; sys_dependentid=&quot;1147228&quot; inlinetype=&quot;rxvariant&quot; rxinlineslot=&quot;105&quot; sys_siteid=&quot;305&quot; class=&quot;rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable&quot; contenteditable=&quot;false&quot; rxselectedtext=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image-left-small centered-set&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;centered-element&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;amp;sys_context=0&amp;amp;sys_folderid=1145880&amp;amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;amp;sys_contentid=1147225&amp;amp;sys_command=edit&quot; alt=&quot;Chordoma Clinic Participants Talking&quot; /&gt;&lt;!--Comment--&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;" sys_relationshipid="7359888">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1145880&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1147225&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Chordoma Clinic Group" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Chordoma Clinic Group, April 2019</p>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2></h2>
<h2><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1147224" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1147224" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7359885" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1147224">First Chordoma Clinic Brings Together Patients, Families, and Expert Doctors</a></h2>
<p>MyPART, Center for Cancer Research, and the Chordoma Foundation collaborated to host the first childhood, teen, and young adult Chordoma Clinic at NIH from April 16th to 18th, 2019. The clinic aimed to share knowledge and to collect data for research on chordoma affecting young people.</p>
<p><em>April 19, 2019</em></p>
<p></p>
<hr />
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1145883" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7359889">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1145880&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1145883&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="a child sitting on the floor drawing" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h2><a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/news/article/mek-inhibitor-selumetinib-granted-breakthrough-designation-by-fda-to-treat-neurofibromatosis-type-one-in-pediatric-patients">MEK inhibitor selumetinib granted breakthrough designation by FDA to treat neurofibromatosis type 1 in pediatric patients</a></h2>
<p>Selumetinib, a treatment for Neurofibromatosis Type 1, was given a breakthrough designation by the FDA to treat pediatric patients.</p>
<p><em>CCR News Headlines - April 12, 2019</em></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1147224" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Chordoma is a rare type of cancer that grows in the bones at the base of the skull and spine. Only about one per one million people per year are diagnosed with chordoma, which translates to about 300 people in the U.S. and 700 people throughout Europe diagnosed each year. Chordoma is often hard to treat due to where the tumor is. In about 30-40% of cases, the cancer can spread to other parts of the body.</p>
<p>MyPART worked with the <a href="https://ccr.cancer.gov/">Center for Cancer Research</a> staff and the <a href="https://www.chordomafoundation.org/">Chordoma Foundation</a> to host the first childhood, teen, and young adult Chordoma Clinic at NIH on April 16<sup>th</sup> &ndash; 18<sup>th</sup>, 2019. The goals of the first clinic were to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Bring together young chordoma patients with expert doctors and patient advocates.</li>
<li>Collect data for basic and clinical research on chordoma affecting young people.</li>
<li>Share knowledge and start new team projects on childhood, teen, and young adult chordoma.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Chordoma Foundation helped find patients who could gain the most from the clinic. Patients were invited to the clinic by MyPART clinicians and joined the <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133251" sys_contentid="1133251" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133251" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7360351">MyPART Natural History Study</a>.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2088" sys_dependentid="1147228" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7360357">
<figure class="image-left-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1145880&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1147228&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Chordoma Clinic Participants Talking" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Expert chordoma doctors from both inside and outside NIH met with each patient and their family to talk about their case. MyPART staff collected blood samples, patient-reported symptoms, and medical records. Patients also met with a genetic counselor, a psychologist, and other specialists to learn more about how to take care of themselves.</p>
<p>For patients and their families, the Chordoma Clinic was a chance to meet with the &ldquo;dream team&rdquo; of doctors, as parent Mr. Frank Fernandes called them. Mr. Fernandes&rsquo;s son was diagnosed with chordoma in 2010. After a long journey with chordoma, he is now cancer free. Mr. Fernandes explained the importance of sharing their experience and learning from the experts. When his family was invited to the clinic, they &ldquo;felt like, here is another tool we can add to the toolbox,&rdquo; Mr. Fernandes explained. For them, the Natural History Study is a tool that may one day lead to new chordoma treatments.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2090" sys_dependentid="1147226" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7360358">
<figure class="image-right-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1145880&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1147226&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Little Girl Holding Cupcakes" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Mr. Fernandes also talked about being an advocate for his son and finding other partners to collaborate with on his son&rsquo;s treatment: &ldquo;When we find a doctor [who] wants to be part of a collaborative team, that&rsquo;s who we steer towards.&rdquo; They want to work with doctors who will become partners with them in treating the disease. Having partners that make up a collaborative team makes sure the patient is getting the best possible care. Those partners include doctors, but also patient advocacy groups like the Chordoma Foundation. Patient advocacy groups like the Chordoma Foundation can help patients find the advocates they need quickly.</p>
<p>For patients with rare cancer, finding a support network can be very hard. In addition to bringing chordoma patients together with experts, the Chordoma Clinic gave patients and families the chance to meet and bond with each other. For most patients, this was the first time they had met someone else with chordoma. During a dinner on Tuesday night at <a href="https://childrensinn.org/">the Children&rsquo;s Inn</a>, patients and families were able to spend time together and share their experiences. They exchanged contact information to keep in touch after the clinic ended. In this way, the Chordoma Clinic helped provide emotional support as well as medical support for patients and their families.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2090" sys_dependentid="1147227" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7360359">
<figure class="image-right-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1145880&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1147227&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Group talking at the Chordoma Clinic" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The success of the Chordoma Clinic shows the need for patients, doctors, and advocates to work together on rare cancers. MyPART will continue to host rare cancer clinics to bring people together for rare cancer research and treatment.</p>
<p>Learn more about <span><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1133257" sys_contentid="1133257" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1133257" sys_variantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7360352">MyPART rare cancer clinics here</a>.<br /></span></p>
<p><span>We thank the patients, families, and advocates who joined us at the inaugural Chordoma Clinic. We also thank the MyPART staff and each of the following external experts who gave their time to the Chordoma Clinic:</span></p>
<ul>
<li>Dr. Gregory Cote (Medical Oncology, Massachusetts General),</li>
<li>Dr. Paul Gardner (Neurosurgery, University of Pittsburgh)</li>
<li>Dr. Christopher Heery (Medical Oncology, Bavarian Nordic)</li>
<li>Dr. Norbert Liebsch (Radiation Oncology, Massachusetts General)</li>
<li>Dr. Robert Malyapa (Radiation Oncology, University of Maryland)</li>
<li>Dr. Debraj Mukherjee (Neurosurgery, Johns Hopkins University)</li>
<li>Dr. Deric Park (Neurology, University of Chicago)</li>
<li>Dr. Nick Rowan (Otolaryngology, Johns Hopkins University)</li>
<li>Dr. Carl Snyderman (Otolaryngology, University of Pittsburgh)</li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
</rows>