<rows>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6894043"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Torchilin VP: Passive and active drug targeting: drug delivery to tumors as an example. <em>Handb Exp Pharmacol </em>2010(197):3-53.</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6894044"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Chow EK, Ho D: Cancer nanomedicine: from drug delivery to imaging. <em>Science translational medicine </em>2013, 5(216):216rv214.</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6894045"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Fang J, Nakamura H, Maeda H: The EPR effect: Unique features of tumor blood vessels for drug delivery, factors involved, and limitations and augmentation of the effect. <em>Adv Drug Deliv Rev </em>2011, 63(3):136-151.</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6894046"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Kamaly N, Xiao Z, Valencia PM, Radovic-Moreno AF, Farokhzad OC. Targeted polymeric therapeutic nanoparticles: design, development and clinical translation. Chem Soc Rev. 2012;41:2971-3010</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6894047"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Farokhzad OC, Langer R. Impact of nanotechnology on drug delivery. ACS Nano. 2009; 27;3:16-20</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6894048"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Omidi Y, Barar J: Targeting tumor microenvironment: crossing tumor interstitial fluid by multifunctional nanomedicines. <em>Bioimpacts </em>2014, 4(2):55-67.</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6894049"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Zhu L, Staley C, Kooby D, El-Rays B, Mao H, Yang L: Current status of biomarker and targeted nanoparticle development: The precision oncology approach for pancreatic cancer therapy. <em>Cancer Lett </em>2016, 388:139-148.</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6894050"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Anchordoquy TJ, Barenholz Y, Boraschi D, Chorny M, Decuzzi P, Dobrovolskaia MA, Farhangrazi ZS, Farrell D, Gabizon A, Ghandehari H<em> et al</em>: Mechanisms and Barriers in Cancer Nanomedicine: Addressing Challenges, Looking for Solutions. <em>ACS Nano </em>2017, 11(1):12-18.</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117213"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Weissleder et al. Imaging approaches to optimize molecular therapies. Science Trans Med. 2016</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117214"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Phillips et al. Clinical translation of an ultrasmall inorganic optical-PET imaging nanoparticle probe. Science Trans Med. 2016</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117215"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Ye et al. Bioorthogonal cyclization-mediated in situ self-assembly of small-molecule probes for imaging caspase activity in vivo. Nature Chemistry 2014</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117216"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Kircher et al. A brain tumor molecular imaging strategy using a new triple-modality MRI-photoacoustic-Raman nanoparticle. Nature Med 2012</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117217"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Nam JM, Thaxton CS, Mirkin CA. Nanoparticle-based bio-bar codes for the ultrasensitive detection of proteins. Science. 2003; 26;301:1884-6.</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117218"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Fan R, Heath JR et al. Integrated barcode chips for rapid, multiplexed analysis of proteins in microliter quantities of blood. Nat Biotechnol. 2008;26:1373-8</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117219"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Haun JB, Castro CM, Wang R, Peterson VM, Marinelli BS, Lee H, Weissleder R. Micro-NMR for rapid molecular analysis of human tumor samples. Sci Transl Med. 2011;3:71ra16</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117220"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Gaster RS, Hall DA, Wang SX. nanoLAB: an ultraportable, handheld diagnostic laboratory for global health. Lab Chip. 2011; 7;11:950-6</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117221"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Park et al., Molecular profiling of single circulating tumor cells from lung cancer patients. PNAS 2016</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117222"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Lin et al. Nanostructure Embedded Microchips for Detection, Isolation, and Characterization of Circulating Tumor Cells. Accounts of Chemical Research 2014</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117223"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Jiang et al. A comparison of isolated circulating tumor cells and tissue biopsies using whole-genome sequencing in prostate cancer. Oncotarget 2015</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="7117224"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Shuhendler et al. Molecular Magnetic Resonance Imaging of Tumor Response to Therapy. Scientific Reports 2015</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6654363"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Matsumura and Maeda, Cancer Res, 1986</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6654369"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Matsumura and Maeda, Cancer Res, 1986</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6654364"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Maeda et al., Adv Drug Deliv Rev, 2013</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6654365"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Bertrand et al, Adv Drug Deliv Rev, 2014</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6654366"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Duan et al. Photodynamic Therapy Mediated by Nontoxic Core&minus;Shell Nanoparticles Synergizes with Immune Checkpoint Blockade To Elicit Antitumor Immunity and Antimetastatic Effect on Breast Cancer. JACS 2016</p>
</div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6654367"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>He et al. Core-shell nanoscale coordination polymers combine chemotherapy and photodynamic therapy to potentiate checkpoint blockade cancer immunotherapy. Nature Comm. 2016</p></div>]]></row>
  <row langcode="en" citation_id="6654368"><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><p>Giljohann et al., J Am Chem Soc, 2009</p></div>]]></row>
</rows>