<rows>
  <row id="1061499" langcode="en">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div sys_relationshipid="7315949" sys_dependentid="1088990" rxinlineslot="105" contenteditable="false" sys_dependentvariantid="2066" rxselectedtext="" rxanchortext="" unselectable="on" inlinetype="rxvariant" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable">
          <figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">        <div class="centered-element">                      <img src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088990&amp;sys_command=preview" alt=""><!--Comment--></img>
                                                </div>
                  <figcaption>
            <div class="caption-container no-resize">
                              
<p>The image is an electron micrograph of a suspended microchannel resonant (SMR) mass sensor under development by researchers at the MIT-Harvard CCNE/CNPP. This sensor is being developed for label-free detection of cancer biomarkers.</p>
                                            <div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>                          </div>
          </figcaption>
              </figure>
       </div>
<p></p>
<p>Funding opportunities currently available from the NCI&nbsp;Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch&nbsp;for the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer (link for downloadable Factsheet) are accessible from <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1064733" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1064733" sys_relationshipid="7315942" sys_variantid="1764" sys_contentid="1064733">Apply to Alliance</a> and other opportunities are accessible from <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1063327" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1063327" sys_relationshipid="7315943" sys_variantid="1764" sys_contentid="1063327">Research Funding</a> below.</p>
<p>Similarly, funding for specific research or training opportunities within the field of cancer nanotechnology or fields that contain much cross-sectional overlap to cancer nanotechnology may be accessed from either <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1063327" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1063327" sys_relationshipid="7315944" sys_variantid="1764" sys_contentid="1063327">Related NCI Funding and Initiatives</a> or <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1063349" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1063349" sys_relationshipid="7315945" sys_variantid="1764" sys_contentid="1063349">Training Grants</a> below. These opportunities are from across the NIH and are offered here as a resource to the research community. Also, you may visit the <a href="https://grants.nih.gov/funding/index.htm">NIH Guide for Grants and Contracts</a> for the latest publication of all NIH funding opportunities and notices.</p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="1071465" langcode="en">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Currently, scientists are limited in their ability to turn promising molecular discoveries into cancer patient benefits. Nanotechnology &mdash;the science and engineering of controlling matter, at the molecular scale, to create devices with novel chemical, physical and/or biological properties&mdash; can provide technical control and tools to enable the development of new diagnostics, therapeutics, and preventions that keep pace with today&rsquo;s explosion in knowledge.</p>
<p>Nanotechnology has the potential to radically change how we diagnose and treat cancer. Although scientists and engineers have only recently (ca. 1980's) developed the ability to industrialize technologies at this scale, there has been good progress in translating nano-based cancer therapies and diagnostics into the clinic and many more are in development.</p>
<p>Nanotechnology is the application of materials, functionalized structures, devices, or systems at the atomic, molecular, or macromolecular scales. At these length scales, approximately the 1-100 nanometer range as defined by the <a href="http://www.nano.gov/">U.S. National Nanotechnology Initiative (NNI)</a> , unique and specific physical properties of matter exist, which can be readily manipulated for a desired application or effect. Furthermore, nanoscale structure can be used as individual entities or integrated into larger material components, systems, and architectures.</p>
<div sys_relationshipid="6886915" sys_dependentid="1091245" rxinlineslot="105" contenteditable="false" sys_dependentvariantid="2084" rxselectedtext="" rxanchortext="" unselectable="on" inlinetype="rxvariant" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable">
          <figure class="image-center-full centered-set">        <div class="centered-element">                      <img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091245&amp;sys_command=preview" alt=""><!--Comment--></img>
                                                </div>
                  <figcaption>
            <div class="caption-container no-resize">
                              
<p>Nanoscale devices are one hundred to ten thousand times smaller than human cells.&nbsp; The depiction displays this scale in size.</p>
                                            <div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>                          </div>
          </figcaption>
              </figure>
       </div>
<p>This emerging field involves scientists from many different disciplines, including physicists, chemists, engineers, information technologists, and material scientists, as well as biologists. Nanotechnology is being applied to almost every field imaginable, including electronics, magnetics, optics, information technology, materials development and biomedicine. Nanotechnology-based structures and devices are already enabling a large number of novel applications in various fields &ndash; including medicine.</p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="1071471" langcode="en">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The primary purpose of the <em>Cancer Nanotechnology Plan 2015</em> is to serve as a strategic document to the <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051623" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051623" sys_relationshipid="7357461" sys_variantid="2317" sys_contentid="1051623">NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer</a> as well as a guiding document to the cancer nanotechnology and oncology fields, as a whole. Now in its third incarnation, it has increased in its scope since its inception in 2005, mostly due to the fact that the field has significantly matured and expanded over this time. It includes contributions from researchers, clinicians, policy makers, and industrial experts in order to give a broad perspective on where the field is now and where it is heading in the future. The plan is also available in a reduced form as a slide presentation to train others as to the field and future potential for clinical cancer care.</p>
<p>The Cancer Nanotechnology Plan is available for download through the links below:</p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="1071491" langcode="en">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Biological processes, including ones necessary for life and those that lead to cancer, occur at the nanoscale. Thus, in fact, we are composed of a multitude of biological nano-machines. Nanotechnology provides researchers with the opportunity to study and manipulate macromolecules in real time and during the earliest stages of cancer progression. Nanotechnology can provide rapid and sensitive detection of cancer-related molecules, enabling scientists to detect molecular changes even when they occur only in a small percentage of cells. Nanotechnology also has the potential to generate entirely novel and highly effective therapeutic agents.&nbsp;</p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="1071493" langcode="en">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The multi-disciplinary CCNE teams are the main venue for the discovery and tool development toward the application of nanotechnology to clinical oncology. Teams are focused on integrated technology solutions and the aggressive development of these solutions from pre-clinical to clinical application. These are multiple project centers and are designed to enable multi-disciplinary team research by linking physical scientists, engineers and technologists working at the nanoscale with cancer biologists and oncologists specializing in the diagnosis, prevention and treatment of cancer.</p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="1071494" langcode="en">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The IRCNs address major barriers in cancer biology and oncology using nanotechnology approaches, and emphasize fundamental understanding of nanomaterial and nanodevice interactions with biological systems in vivo. The individual, circumscribed research projects are designed to enable multi-disciplinary team research and transformative discoveries in cancer biology and oncology, diagnostics, and therapeutics through the use of nanotechnology.</p>
<p>The outcomes of IRCN-supported projects are expected to better inform, inspire, and aid in the development of innovative, clinically relevant nanotechnology solutions for cancer through a greater understanding of these interaction mechanisms. To advance these nanotechnologies, the IRCN projects take advantage of the collaborative environment of the Alliance network.</p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="1071499" langcode="en">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield"><br />
<h3><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1064733" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1064733" sys_relationshipid="7315946" sys_variantid="1764" sys_contentid="1064733">Apply for the Alliance</a></h3>
<p>NCI Alliance funding is by way of many grant mechanisms of the National Institutes of Health.&nbsp; Appliaction details for current Alliance funding is listed here.</p>
<h3><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1063327" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1063327" sys_relationshipid="7315947" sys_variantid="1764" sys_contentid="1063327">Research Funding</a></h3>
<p>Find specific research opportunities relevant to nanotechnology and cancer.</p>
<h3><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1063349" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1063349" sys_relationshipid="7315948" sys_variantid="1764" sys_contentid="1063349">Training Grants</a></h3>
<p>Funding for specific research and training opportunities within the field of cancer nanotechnology as well as fields that contain much cross-sectional overlap to the field.</p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="1071623" langcode="en">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer is an integrated, milestone driven, and product oriented program aimed at eliminating the burden of cancer.</p>
<p>Committed to building a community of researchers dedicated to using nanotechnology to advance the fight against cancer, the Alliance is engaged in efforts to harness the power of nanotechnology to radically change the way we diagnose, treat, and prevent cancer. The Alliance works in concert with other NCI advanced technology initiatives to provide the scientific foundation and team science that is required to transform cancer research and care.</p>
<p>Launched in 2004, the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer (Alliance) advanced a number of promising nanotechnologies for the diagnosis, treatment and prevention of cancer in its first five years. This progress led NCI to announce in September 2010 its continued support of this program with the award of five-year, multi-institution grants to generate new preventative, diagnostic and therapeutic approaches to cancer in areas where improvements cannot be realized using existing technologies. The next five years of the program aim to:</p>
<ul>
<li>rapidly advance new nanotechnology discoveries and speed their transformation into cancer-relevant applications in clinical practice</li>
<li>aid nanoparticle characterization and standardization of characterization methods to enable technology transfer from university laboratories to companies that bring these technologies to patients</li>
<li>develop the next-generation of cancer researchers in the area of nanotechnology</li>
</ul>
<p>The Alliance focused on development and translation of nanotechnology-based techniques and tools for:</p>
<ul>
<li>early disease diagnosis using in vitro (laboratory) assays and devices, and in vivo (live) imaging techniques</li>
<li>multifunctional therapeutic solutions</li>
<li>techniques for cancer prevention and control</li>
</ul>
<p>Regardless of their specific area of focus, the Alliance investigators are encouraged to concentrate their efforts on the following tumor types where the disease is characterized by low survival rates: brain, lung, ovary, and pancreas.</p>
<p>The Alliance&rsquo;s programs foster innovation and collaboration among researchers within and between institutions, as well as across scientific disciplines.</p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="1097637" langcode="en">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>CNTCs are designed to establish innovative research education programs supporting the development of a multi-disciplinary nanotechnology workforce capable of pursuing cancer research. CNTCs target graduate students and post-doctoral researchers with backgrounds in medicine, biology, and other health sciences as well as in the physical sciences, chemistry, and engineering. The program of multi-disciplinary research education in cancer nanotechnology is primarily focused on mentored laboratory-based training through participation in dedicated training research projects. This program is administered by the <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=197&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=16360" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="16360" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="7371340" sys_variantid="2317" sys_contentid="16360">NCI Center for Cancer Training</a>.</p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="6315718" langcode="en" long_title="Research ">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<ul>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051623" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6315665" sys_folderid="" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051623" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1064730&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=734&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="734" sys_dependentid="1064730" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627702">Alliance Published Research</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1077669&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1077669" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627703">NCI Alliance Companies</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=734&amp;sys_contentid=1051475" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6315668" sys_folderid="" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051475" sys_dependentvariantid="734">Data Sharing</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1077670&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1077670" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627704">Nanotechnology Characterization Lab</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1051489&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=734&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="734" sys_dependentid="1051489" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627705">Partners &amp; Collaborators</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="6399954" langcode="en" long_title="Cancer &amp; Nanotechnology">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<ul>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1074439" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1074439" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627709">Benefits of Nanotechnology</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1074443" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1074443" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627710">Detection &amp; Diagnosis</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1074446" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1074446" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627711">Treatment &amp; Therapy</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1073910" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1073910" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627712">Safety of Nanotechnology</a></li>
</ul>
<p><a class="arrow-link learn-more" href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051465" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_dependentid="1051465" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627713">Learn more about cancer and nanotechnology</a></p>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
  <row id="6400038" langcode="en" long_title="Grants &amp; Training">
    <body><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<ul>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1064733&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=734&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="734" sys_dependentid="1064733" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627699">Apply for the Alliance</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1063327&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=734&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="734" sys_dependentid="1063327" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627700">Related NCI Funding &amp; Initiatives</a></li>
<li><a class="arrow-link" href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1063349&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=734&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="734" sys_dependentid="1063349" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6627701">Training Grants</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></body>
  </row>
</rows>