<rows>
  <row para_id="1051457" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch</strong><br />Cancer Imaging Program<br />National Cancer Institute<br />Divsion of Cancer Treatment and Dianosis<br />9609 Medical Center Drive<br />Bethesda, MD 20892-9725</p>
<p><strong>NCI Press Officers</strong><br />Phone: (240) 760-6600<br />Fax: (301) 451-7440<br />Email: <a href="mailto:ncipressofficers@mail.nih.gov">ncipressofficers@mail.nih.gov</a></p>
<p>For broad information or to seek help, please visit <a href="http://www.cancer.gov/">www.cancer.gov</a> or call NCI's Cancer Information Services at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).</p>
<h2>NSDB&nbsp;Staff</h2>
<p><strong>Piotr Grodzinski, Ph.D. <br /></strong><strong>Branch Chief<br /></strong><strong>NCI Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch</strong></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2090" sys_dependentid="1090836" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7315996">
<figure class="image-right-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090836&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Dr. Piotr Grodzinski is&nbsp;Branch Chief&nbsp;of the Nanotechnology for Cancer programs at NSDB. He coordinates program and research activities of the Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer which has received dedicated NCI funds (2004&ndash;present). These funds have supported the formation of multiple interdisciplinary centers, as well as individual research and training programs, targeting nanotechnology solutions for improved prevention, detection, and treatment of cancer.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Though&nbsp;a materials scientist by training, Dr. Grodzinski found bio- and nanotechnology fascinating. In the mid-nineties, he left the world of semiconductor research and built a large microfluidics program at Motorola Corporate Research &amp; Development in Arizona. The group made important contributions to the development of integrated microfluidics for genetic sample preparation with its work being featured in <em>Chemical &amp; Engineering News</em> and <em>Nature Reviews</em>.</p>
<p>After his tenure at Motorola, Dr. Grodzinski joined the Bioscience Division of Los Alamos National Laboratory where he served as a Group Leader and an interim Chief Scientist for the Department of Energy's <em>Center for Integrated Nanotechnologies (CINT)</em>.</p>
<p>Dr. Grodzinski received his Ph.D. in Materials Science from the <em>University of Southern California</em>, Los Angeles in 1992. He is an inventor on 15 patents and has authored over 100 technical publications and conference presentations. He has been an invited speaker and has served on the committees of numerous bio- and nano-Micro-Electromechanical Systems conferences.</p>
<p><strong>Scott E. McNeil, Ph.D.<br />Director, Nanotechnology Characterization Laboratory<br />National Cancer Institute</strong></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2090" sys_dependentid="1090837" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7315997">
<figure class="image-right-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090837&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Dr. McNeil serves as the Director of the Nanotechnology Characterization Laboratory (NCL) for SAIC-Frederick and Frederick National Laboratory for Cancer Research, where he coordinates preclinical characterization of nanotech cancer therapeutics and diagnostics. At the NCL, Dr. McNeil leads a team of scientists responsible for testing candidate nanotech drugs and diagnostics, evaluating safety and efficacy, and assisting with product development &ndash; from discovery-level, through scale-up and into clinical trials. NCL has assisted in characterization and evaluation of more than 300 nanotechnology products, several of which are now in human clinical trials. Dr. McNeil is a member of several working groups on nanomedicine, environmental health and safety, and other nanotechnology issues. He is an invited speaker to numerous nanotechnology-related conferences and has several patents pending related to nanotechnology and biotechnology. He is also a Vice President of SAIC-Frederick.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Prior to establishing the NCL, he served as a Senior Scientist in the Nanotech Initiatives Division at SAIC where he transitioned basic nanotechnology research to government and commercial markets. He advises industry and State and US Governments on the development of nanotechnology and is a member of several governmental and industrial working groups related to nanotechnology policy, standardization and commercialization. Dr. McNeil&rsquo;s professional career includes tenure as an Army Officer, with tours as Chief of Biochemistry at Tripler Army Medical Center, and as a Combat Arms officer during the Gulf War. He received his bachelor's degree in Chemistry from <em>Portland State University</em> and his Ph.D. in Cell Biology from <em>Oregon Health Sciences University</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Christopher M. Hartshorn, Ph.D.<br />Program Director<br />NCI Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch</strong></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2090" sys_dependentid="1090839" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7315998">
<figure class="image-right-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090839&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Dr. Christopher M. Hartshorn serves as a program director in NCI's Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer program. In this role, he manages the nanotechnology research projects, evaluates the effectiveness of the Alliance programs, and maintains the proper stewardship over federally funded research. He serves as a technical expert to Alliance members, acts as senior editor / author on strategic Alliance documents, and participates in the development and direction of new research initiatives.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Prior to joining the NSDB, Dr. Hartshorn worked for the <em>National Institute of Standards and Technology</em> (NIST) on the research and development of novel high-speed non-invasive nonlinear optical imaging modalities for tumor histopathology as well as for <em>in situ</em> materials and pharmaceutical characterization. In addition to his research, he co-founded and led the NIST Material Measurement Laboratory Post-doctoral Association and served on the Washington Editorial Review Board. Dr. Hartshorn earned his Ph.D. in Physical Chemistry from <em>Washington State University</em> where his research studies focused on modeling the physical effects of nanomaterials at biological interfaces, development of nanoparticle-DNA oligomer conjugates for the single-molecule measurement of HIV-RT binding kinetics, and was part of a interdisciplinary team developing a multi-antigen biosensor. Prior to his graduate work, he co-authored the collaborative discovery of the modulus-density scaling behaviour and framework architecture for nanoporous silicates. He earned his Bachelor of Science degree's in Chemistry and Biology from the <em>University of New Mexico</em>.</p>
<p>Over his academic and research career, Dr. Hartshorn has co-authored many peer reviewed publications including several in <em>Nature</em> journals within the disciplines of nanomaterials, photonics, and biology as well as co-authoring several funded grants and book chapters. He has been the recipient of two national fellowships, an invited speaker for many conferences, and is a member of <em>Sigma Xi</em> and the <em>American Chemical Society</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Christina Liu, Ph.D., P.E.<br />Program Director<br />NCI Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch</strong></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2090" sys_dependentid="1090840" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7315999">
<figure class="image-right-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090840&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Dr. Liu serves as a program director for NCI's Office of Cancer Nanotechnology Research. She manages nanotechnology projects and grants, participates in the development of new initiatives, and evaluates the effectiveness of programs within the Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Dr. Liu graduated with a Ph.D from <em>Rice University</em> in Chemical Engineering and subsequently worked in the Petrophysical Interpretation Group in Baker Hughes Oil Service Company in Houston, TX where magnetic resonance data (MRI) was used for oil exploration. While there, she earned her Professional Engineer License in the State of Texas. She later moved to Boston, MA for her postdoctoral training and independent research at <em>Massachusetts General Hospital/Harvard Medical School</em> with research focusing on drug addiction and stroke using contrast-enhanced functional and molecular MRI.</p>
<p>In 2010, Christina became a Health Scientist Administrator in the Division of Biomedical Technology of National Center for Research Resources (NCRR) where she served as Program Officer for the Shared Instrumentation Programs. Most recently, Dr. Liu was program director within the National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering (NIBIB). Christina had joined the Division of Applied Science and Technology at NIBIB in 2012 where she managed MRI/Optical/Ultrasound-based Molecular Imaging Technology and Structural Biology portfolios. She also served as the Coordinator for NIBIB's Biomedical Technology Resource Centers (P41) Program.</p>
<p><strong>Luisa Russell, Ph.D.</strong><br /><strong>CRTA Postdoctoral Fellow</strong><br /><strong>NCI Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch</strong></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2090" sys_dependentid="1113339" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7316000">
<figure class="image-right-small centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1113339&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p>Dr. Luisa Russell serves as a CRTA Postdoctoral Fellow in research and grants management in the Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch of the Cancer Imaging Program at NCI. In this role, she leads coordination of the caNanoLab online database for cancer nanomedicine research. She also participates in nanomedicine and nanoinformatics-based NIH and interagency working groups.<br />Prior to joining the NSDB, Dr. Russell received her Ph.D. in Materials Science and Engineering from Johns Hopkins University in the lab of Dr. Peter Searson in the Institute for NanoBioTechnology (INBT). Her thesis work focused on the push to standardize the way nanomedicines for passive accumulation in solid tumors are characterized, including development of an in vivo protocol for cross-platform benchmarking, and in the development and characterization of a novel CD47 marker-of-self based liposome. She was funded by a T32 NTCR training grant, as well as several smaller fellowships. Dr. Russell graduated from Stanford University with a B.S. in Materials Science and Engineering, during which she conducted research as an undergraduate on electron microscopy techniques for analysis of nanoparticle interactions with biological systems under the guidance of Dr. Robert Sinclair.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051459" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The National Cancer Institute has recognized that the achievement of 21st century personalized cancer care requires a commitment to a new kind of scientific enterprise. Such an enterprise is characterized by &ldquo;team science&rdquo; across multiple laboratories that share data in standardized formats; collaborations among academic, private, and public sector organizations; and high-throughput technology platforms supported by seamless informatics capability and systems-level planning and management. The technology initiatives launched through the NCI, including the Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer, are positioned to support this transformation in cancer research for better prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of cancer and improved outcomes for patients.</p>
<p>Learn about the offices within the NCI's&nbsp;<a href="https://dctd.cancer.gov/">Division of Cancer Treatment and Diagnosis</a>&nbsp;by visiting each program website:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://brb.nci.nih.gov/">Biometric Research Program (BRP)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://cdp.cancer.gov/">Cancer Diagnosis Program (CDP)</a></li>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=16678&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=945&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="945" sys_dependentid="16678" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6897134">Cancer Imaging Program (CIP)</a></li>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=18589&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=945&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="945" sys_dependentid="18589" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6897135">Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program (CTEP)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://dtp.cancer.gov/">Developmental Therapeutics Program (DTP)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rrp.cancer.gov/">Radiation Research Program (RRP)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://trp.cancer.gov/">Translational Research Program (TRP)</a></li>
<li><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=17436&amp;sys_revision=4&amp;sys_variantid=945&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="945" sys_dependentid="17436" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6897136">Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM)</a></li>
</ul>
<!-- old code
<li><a href="http://proteomics.cancer.gov/">Clinical Proteomic Technologies for Cancer (CPTC)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://biospecimens.cancer.gov/">Office of Biorepositories and Biospecimen Research (OBBR)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ocg.cancer.gov/">Office of Cancer Genomics (OCG)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://physics.cancer.gov/">Physical Sciences in Oncology (PSIO)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://tcga.cancer.gov/">The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA)</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
-->
<p>Learn about other complementary NCI initiatives:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://cbiit.nci.nih.gov/ncip">National Cancer Informatics Program (NCIP)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://innovation.cancer.gov/">Innovative Molecular Analysis Technologies Program (IMAT)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://sbir.cancer.gov/">Small Business Innovation Research &amp; Small Business Technology Transfer Program (SBIR &amp; STTR)</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051460" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The programs funded through the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer have made significant progress in advancing cancer nanotechnology research. The&nbsp;NSDB routinely publishes reports, strategic peer-reviewed manuscripts, and subject matter expertise papers relative to our myriad of interdisciplinary backgrounds. These papers are listed below.</p>
<p><a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10544-019-0360-6 ">NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer - From Academic Research to Clinical Interventions</a><strong><br /></strong>March&nbsp;2019<br />This paper published in the journal Biomedical Microdevices takes a look at last thirteen years of the Alliance program operations and delineates its outcomes, successes, and outlook for the future.</p>
<p><a href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acsnano.7b05108">Nanotechnology Strategies to Advance Outcomes in Clinical Cancer Care</a><strong><br /></strong>January&nbsp;2018<br />A review paper focusing upon emerging areas in cancer nanotechnology in the journal ACS Nano. The paper presents several evolving areas in cancer nanotechnology in order to identify key clinical and biological challenges that need to be addressed to improve patient outcomes. A strategic emphasis on future goals and guidance to the field are highlighted as well.</p>
<p><a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsnano.7b07252 ">Big Potential from Small Agents: Nanoparticles for Imaging-Based Companion Diagnostics</a><br />January 2018 <br />Nanoparticles are uniquely suited for advancing existing imaging tools, not only as imaging contrast agents but also as companion diagnostics. This review published in the journal ACS Nano provides an overview of many ways nanoparticle imaging agents have contributed to cancer imaging, both preclinically and in the clinic, as well as charting future directions in companion diagnostics.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/ni.3828">Biomarkers of chronic inflammation in disease development and prevention: challenges and opportunities</a><strong><br /></strong>November 2017<br />A paper published in Nature Immunology that provides a collective view of recent advances in chronic inflammation and cancer as well as a synopsis of a recent NCI strategic workshop on the subject.</p>
<p><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=955&amp;sys_contentid=1052583" sys_contentid="1052583" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="7312565" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1052583" sys_dependentvariantid="955" sys_variantid="955">NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer: Phase II Program Summary 2010-2015</a><strong><br /></strong>January 2016<br />The NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer published its 2010-2015 Phase II Program Summary summarizing the accomplishments of the program over the past 5-year funding period. The summary outlines the various ways the Alliance reached the wider scientific community, advanced cancer research, and advanced translation efforts for the cancer nanotechnology field.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nature.com/articles/npjbcancer201522">Cell-to-cell communication in cancer: workshop report</a><strong><br /></strong>December 2015<br />A paper published in <em>Nature Breast Cancer</em> that provides a collective view of recent advances in cancer biology and the development of new research tools have enabled interrogations of single cells and cell-cell interactions.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25625382">Cancer nanomedicines: closing the translational gap</a><br />December 2014<br />A paper published in <em>The Lancet</em> that provides a collective view of the translational state of nanomedicines for cancer.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25429991">NCI Investment in Nanotechnology: Achievements and Challenges for the Future</a><br />November 2014<br />A paper published in WIRE's <em>Nanomedicine and Nanobiotechnology</em> that provides an overview of NCIs investment in nanotechnology training and research, including a review of various nanotechnology programs supported by the NIH and NCI. This paper also discusses plans for future work with the nanotechnology community in the pursuit of innovative nanotechnology-based solutions to cancer.</p>
<p><a href="http://cancerres.aacrjournals.org/content/74/5/1307.abstract">Future Opportunities in Cancer Nanotechnology&mdash;NCI Strategic Workshop Report</a><br />March 1, 2014<br />The National Cancer Institute, which currently supports an array of research activities in cancer nanotechnology, convened a strategic workshop to explore the most promising directions and areas for future resource investment. The major discussion points, as well as the opportunities identified, were published in the journal <em>Cancer Research</em>.</p>
<p><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=955&amp;sys_contentid=1052668" sys_contentid="1052668" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="7312566" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1052668" sys_dependentvariantid="955" sys_variantid="955">Summary of Responses to the Request for Information</a><br />March 2014<br />The National Cancer Institute Office of Cancer Nanotechnology Research published a summary of the responses to a request for information on the Directions and Needs for Cancer Nanotechnology Research and Development. The RFI sought to gain feedback, comments and ideas on the status and future of the field and the role NCI funding has played and should continue to play in the future.</p>
<p><a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=955&amp;sys_contentid=1052669" sys_contentid="1052669" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="7312567" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1052669" sys_dependentvariantid="955" sys_variantid="955">NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer Annual Bulletin</a><br />2013<br />The NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer published its 2013 issue of the annual bulletin summarizing the accomplishments of the program over the past year. The bulletin outlines the various ways the Alliance reaches the wider scientific community, as demonstrated by numerous news stories, perspective articles, and solicitations for community input, all focused on advancing the cancer nanotechnology field.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Biotargeted+Nanomedicines+for+Cancer%3A+Six+Tenets+Before+You+Begin+Published+in+Nanomedicine/">Biotargeted Nanomedicines for Cancer: Six Tenets Before You Begin Published in <em>Nanomedicine</em></a><br />January 2013<br />A paper published in the journal <em>Nanomedicine</em>, provides a brief summary of the most important nano-based tumor targeting systems and strategies, and discusses recent advances and future directions in the development of tumour-targeted nanomedicines.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22669131">Best Practices in Cancer Nanotechnology: Perspective from NCI Nanotechnology Alliance Published in <em>Clinical Cancer Research</em></a><br />June 2012<br />The NCI Office of Cancer Nanotechnology Research published a paper in <em>Clinical Cancer Research</em> that discusses the future prospects of using nanotechnology in cancer applications and practices and methodologies used in the development and translation of nanotechnology-based therapeutics.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22385196">Kindling Translational Cancer Nanotechnology Research Published in <em>Nanomedicine</em></a><br />March 2012<br />A paper published in the journal <em>Nanomedicine</em>, provides an overview of the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer and features the Alliance's programs which are dedicated to supporting cancer nanomedicine research.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20814720">Nanotechnology-based Cancer Therapeutics&mdash;Promise and Challenge&mdash;Lessons Learned through the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer Published in <em>Pharmaceutical Research</em></a><br />February 2011<br />The NCI Office of Cancer Nanotechnology Research published a paper in <em>Pharmaceutical Research</em> that summarizes current developments in nanotechnology-based drug delivery and discusses the path forward in the context of research and development occurring within the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer.</p>
<p><a href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/freeabs_all.jsp?arnumber=5871455">Commentary on Nanomedicine in Cancer Therapy Published in <em>IEEE Nanotechnology</em></a><br />June 2011<br />The NCI Office of Cancer Nanotechnology Research published a paper in <em>IEEE Nanotechnology</em>, highlighting interesting research conducted by the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer investigators aimed at improving cancer diagnoses and treatment.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20552623">Alliance Achievements and Path Forward Published in <em>WIREs Nanomedicine and Nanobiotechnology</em></a><br />June 8, 2010<br />A paper published in the journal <em>WIREs Nanomedicine and Nanobiotechnology</em> highlights Alliance achievements in demonstrating that multidisciplinary research catalyzes scientific developments and advances clinical translation in cancer nanotechnology. The paper also discusses goals for the next phase of the program.</p>
<p><a href="http://cancerres.aacrjournals.org/content/early/2010/05/11/0008-5472.CAN-09-3716.abstract?maxtoshow=&amp;hits=100&amp;RESULTFORMAT=&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;fdate=5/1/2010&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT">Highlights from Alliance Workshops on Cancer Nanotechnology Published in <em>Cancer Research</em></a><br />May 11, 2010<br />The Alliance conducted three strategic workshops focused on the use of nanotechnology in the areas of <em>in vitro</em> diagnostics and prevention, therapy and post-treatment, and <em>in vivo</em> diagnosis and imaging. Highlights from these workshops were published in the journal <em>Cancer Research</em>.</p>
<p><a href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/nn100073g">Highlights from 2009 Alliance PI Meeting Published in <em>ACS Nano</em></a><br />February 23, 2010<br />Alliance research in the areas of <em>in vitro</em> diagnostics, targeted delivery of anticancer and contrast enhancement agents, and nanotherapeutics that was presented at the 2009 Principal Investigators&rsquo; Meeting in Manhattan Beach, CA, were published in <em>ACS Nano</em>.</p>
<p><a href="http://cancerres.aacrjournals.org/content/69/13/5294.full">Meeting Report from First Joint China-U.S. Symposium on Nanobiotechnology and Nanomedicine Published in <em>Cancer Research</em></a><br />July 1, 2009<br />The first Joint China-U.S. Symposium on Nanobiotechnology and Nanomedicine was convened in October 2008, in Beijing, China. Participants shared experiences and exchanged information pertaining to the development of nanotechnology for medical use including the prevention, detection, and treatment of disease, and ensuring the safety of the general public and of personnel working in the field. The symposium also provided a platform for exploring the development of new research collaborations among top Chinese and American scientists.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.expert-reviews.com/doi/abs/10.1586/14737159.6.3.307">Alliance Commentary on the Use of Nanotechnology to Improve Cancer Diagnosis Published in <em>Expert Review of Molecular Diagnostics</em></a><br />May 1, 2006<br />A paper published in <em>Expert Review of Molecular Diagnostics</em> discusses why nanotechnology is in a unique position to transform cancer diagnostics and to produce a new generation of biosensors and medical imaging techniques with higher sensitivity and precision of recognition. <em>In vitro</em> and <em>in vivo</em> diagnostic applications of nanoparticles and other nanodevices are also discussed.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051466" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Nanotechnology is the application of materials, functionalized structures, devices, or systems at the atomic, molecular, or macromolecular scales. At these length scales, approximately the <em>1-100 nanometer range </em>as defined by the U.S. National Nanotechnology Initiative (NNI), unique and specific physical properties of matter exist, which can be readily manipulated for a desired application or effect. Furthermore, nanoscale structures can be used as individual entities or integrated into larger material components, systems, and architectures. Nanotechnology-based structures and devices are already enabling a large number of novel applications in various fields &ndash; including medicine.</p>
<h2>Clinical Use</h2>
<p>The earliest nanotechnology-enabled imaging agents and cancer drugs were approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) over a decade ago, and FDA approved nanomedicines include iron oxide nanoparticles for enhanced MRI imaging contrast and Abraxane&reg;, a nanoparticle formed by binding the serum protein albumin to the chemotherapy drug paclitaxel, and Doxil&reg;, a pegylated liposomal formulation of the chemotherapy drug docetaxel.&nbsp; Abraxane improves patient tolerance of the drug paclitaxel by stabilizing the drug for <em>in vivo</em> delivery without requiring the use of non-biocompatible chemical stabilizers. For some patients and cancers, Doxil improves the therapeutic efficacy of docetaxel and reduces cardiomyopathy, a dangerous side effect of the drug.</p>
<p>A number of nanomedicines and nanoparticle drugs have received Investigational New Drug (IND) approval from the FDA are currently undergoing clinical trials. Although some are intended to improve performance of existing chemotherapy drugs, as with Abraxane and Doxil, others enable use of potent compounds that are too toxic or insufficiently biocompatible for use without the pharmacokinetic advantages conferred by the nanoparticle packaging. Nanoparticles are also being investigated for delivery of nucleic acids and proteins that are unstable in blood, such as small interfering RNA (siRNA) for RNA interference (RNAi) therapy, and molecularly targeted therapies such as tyrosine kinase inhibitors.</p>
<h2>Treatment and Therapy&nbsp;</h2>
<p>Research on nanotechnology cancer therapy extends beyond drug delivery into the creation of new therapeutics available only through use of nanomaterial properties. Although small compared to cells, nanoparticles are large enough to encapsulate many small molecule compounds, which can be of multiple types. At the same time, the relatively large surface area of nanoparticle can be functionalized with ligands, including small molecules, DNA or RNA strands, peptides, aptamers or antibodies. These ligands can be used for therapeutic effect or to direct nanoparticle fate <em>in vivo</em>. These properties enable combination drug delivery, multi-modality treatment and combined therapeutic and diagnostic, known as &ldquo;theranostic,&rdquo; action. The physical properties of nanoparticles, such as energy absorption and re-radiation, can also be used to disrupt diseased tissue, as in laser ablation and hyperthermia applications.</p>
<p>Integrated development of innovative nanoparticle packages and active pharmaceutical ingredients will also enable exploration of a wider repertoire of active ingredients, no longer confined to those with acceptable pharmokinetic or biocompatibility behavior. In addition, immunogenic cargo and surface coatings are being investigated as both adjuvants to nanoparticle-mediated and traditional radio- and chemotherapy and as stand-alone therapies. Innovative strategies include the design of nanoparticles as artificial antigen presenting cells and <em>in vivo</em> depots of immunostimulatory factors that exploit nanostructured architecture for sustained anti-tumor activity.&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Early Detection and Diagnosis</h2>
<p>Although not yet deployed clinically for cancer detection or diagnosis, nanoparticles are already on the market in numerous medical screens and tests, with the most widespread use that of gold nanoparticles in home pregnancy tests. Nanoparticles are also at the heart of the Verigene&reg; system from Nanosphere and the T2MR system from T2 Biosystems, currently used in hospitals for a variety of indications.&nbsp;</p>
<p>For cancer, nanodevices are being investigated for the capture of blood borne biomarkers, including cancer-associated proteins circulating tumor cells, circulating tumor DNA, and tumor-shed exosomes. Nano-enabled sensors are capable of high sensitivity, specificity and multiplexed measurements. Next generation devices couple capture with genetic analysis to further elucidate a patient&rsquo;s cancer and potential treatments and disease course.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Already clinically established as contrast agents for anatomical structure, nanoparticles are being developed to act as molecular imaging agents, reporting on the presence of cancer-relevant genetic mutations or the functional characteristics of tumor cells. This information can be used to choose a treatment course or alter a therapeutic plan.&nbsp; Bioactivatable nanoparticles that change properties in response to factors or processes within the body act as dynamic reporters of <em>in vivo</em> states and can provide both spatial and temporal information on disease progression and therapeutic response.</p>
<h2>Research Tools</h2>
<p>Nanotechnology can also be used for development of research tools to advance the study of cancer. Examples include <em>in vitro </em>tumor models, such as vessel perfused microfluidic chips that mimic tumor microenvironment and enable study of transport properties within tumors and devices that use nanoparticle probes to study cellular drug responses and mechanisms.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051475" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Communicating new discoveries and sharing resources, including data and physical material generated as part of the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer, is of critical importance to realize the full potential of nanotechnology for the good of cancer patients. Regular communication and sharing of information needs to occur at three basic levels:</p>
<ul>
<li>Among institutions and investigators participating in the research activities within a given <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051493" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051493" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="6655269">Center of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence (CCNEs)</a>;</li>
<li>Among the CCNEs and other programs that compose the Alliance; and</li>
<li>Among the greater research and development communities outside the Alliance.</li>
</ul>
<p>Research goals can only be reached by achieving advances at each level of collaboration and data sharing. Therefore, it is critical that a well-organized system of data sharing be established both within and outside the Alliance to achieve not only the free exchange of data and materials for research purposes, but also the translation of research into commercially viable therapeutics and diagnostics to treat patients.</p>
<p>To address the challenges of data sharing, NCI has participated in the development of nanomaterial data sharing resources and opportunities for the research community to discuss data sharing and define standards for nanotechnology.</p>
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="tools">
<h2>Data Sharing Tools</h2>
<p><a href="http://cananolab.nci.nih.gov/">Cancer Nanotechnology Laboratory (caNanoLab) Data Portal</a> <br />The caNanoLab is a web portal designed to facilitate sharing of well&ndash;characterized biomedical nanomaterial data in the research community.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nanomaterialregistry.org/">Nanomaterial Registry</a> <br />The Nanomaterial Registry is a free web-based resource launched by Research Triangle Institute International, organizes and evaluates the biological and environmental implications of well-characterized nanomaterials from publically available resources.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.nci.nih.gov/display/ICR/Nanotechnology+Working+Group">National Cancer Informatics Program Nanotechnology Working Group (NCIP Nano WG)</a> <br />The NCIP Nano WG was established to work closely with the nanotechnology research community to develop and encourage adoption of a shared informatics infrastructure that describes the physicochemical properties, biological interactions, and environmental interactions of nanomaterials. The NCIP Nano WG is comprised of over 20 active participants from academia, government and industry.</p>
</section>
<section id="updates">
<h2>caNanoLab and Data Sharing Updates</h2>
<p><a href="https://nciphub.org/groups/cananolab_usability"><span>caNanoLab 2.0 launched with enhancements to improve usability-learn more about planned enhancements and provide feedback on the caNanoLab Usability Discussion Forum</span></a><br /> December 2014</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nature.com/nnano/journal/v9/n12/full/nnano.2014.287.html"><span>The Nanomaterial Registry and caNanoLab were highlighted as comprehensive NIH nanotechnology public repositories in Nature Nanotechnology article on checklist for life sciences</span><span><span>&nbsp;</span></span><em><span>"Joining the reproducibility initiative."</span></em></a><br /> December 2014</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.nci.nih.gov/display/caNanoLab/caNanoLab+FAQ"><span>caNanoLab provides nanomaterial research text for Data Sharing Plans applicable to NIH research grant applications</span></a><br /> September 2014</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nature.com/sdata/data-policies/repositories"><span>caNanoLab is listed as a recommended data repository for Scientific Data, a new online journal launched by Nature's publishers that issues peer&ndash;reviewed descriptions of scientifically valuable datasets</span></a><br /> May 2014</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nanomaterialregistry.org/resources/DataManagement.aspx"><span>The Nanomaterial Registry provides text for Data Management Plans applicable to NIH or NSF research grant applications</span></a><br /> May 2014</p>
</section>
<section id="publications">
<h2>Data Sharing Publications</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26425437">Nanocuration workflows: Establishing best practices for identifying, inputting, and sharing data to inform decisions on nanomaterials</a> <br />Powers et al, <em>Beilstein Journal of Nanotechnology</em>, 2015, Sep 4;6:1860-71</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26425427">The Nanomaterial Data Curation Initiative: A collaborative approach to assessing, evaluating, and advancing the state of the field</a> <br />Hendren et al, <em>Beilstein Journal of Nanotechnology</em>, 2015, Aug 18;6:1752-62</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26425409">Experiences in supporting the structured collection of cancer nanotechnology data using caNanoLab</a> <br />Morris et al, <em>Beilstein Journal of Nanotechnology</em>, 2015, Jul 21;6:1580-93</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25364375"><span>caNanoLab: data sharing to expedite the use of nanotechnology in biomedicine</span></a><br /> Sharon Gaheen et al,<span>&nbsp;</span><em>Computational Science &amp; Discovery</em>, 2013, 6 014010</p>
<p><a href="http://www.dovepress.com/the-nanomaterial-registry-facilitating-the-sharing-and-analysis-of-dat-peer-reviewed-article-IJN"><span>The Nanomaterial Registry: facilitating the sharing and analysis of data in the diverse nanomaterial community</span></a><br /> Ostraat ML et al,<span>&nbsp;</span><em>International Journal of Nanomedicine</em>, 2013:8 (Suppl 1) 7-13.</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051476" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>As successful as researchers have been in using nanotechnology to address and solve many important questions in the laboratory, the ultimate measure of the field&rsquo;s success lies in the translation of research discoveries to the clinic. Currently, multiple nanotechnology-enabled diagnostic and therapeutic agents are in clinical trials, and many more are nearing that goal.&nbsp; The link here will bring you to current <a href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=nanoparticle&amp;cond=Cancer&amp;Search=Apply&amp;recrs=b&amp;recrs=a&amp;recrs=d&amp;recrs=c&amp;age_v=&amp;gndr=&amp;type=&amp;rslt=">U.S. clinical trials listed at ClinicalTrials.gov</a> which involve nanotechnology for cancer.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051489" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Nanotechnology research is an interdisciplinary endeavor by nature. Investigators with basic science, engineering, molecular biology, and clinical backgrounds must collaborate in order to design new drugs and diagnostic tools that can improve patient outcomes.</p>
<p>The&nbsp;Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch&nbsp;is continually working with our private sector, academic, and government partners to advance the translation and research of nanotechnology-center solutions for cancer. Below are a list of a few recent efforts toward this end.</p>
<h3>TONIC</h3>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2388" sys_dependentid="1063402" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6889746">
<div class="topic-feature large-4 columns card right">
<div class="feature-card nciFile">
<h3>TONIC Federal Register Announcement</h3>
<p>The Federal Register Announcement introducing TONIC.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The NCI has initiated a public-private industry partnership called <strong>T</strong>ranslation <strong>o</strong>f <strong>N</strong>anotechnology <strong>i</strong>n <strong>C</strong>ancer (TONIC) to accelerate the translation and development of nanotechnology solutions for the early detection, diagnosis, and treatment of cancer. The TONIC consortium, made up of government entities, and pharmaceutical, biotechnology, and other healthcare-related companies, will work in parallel to the Alliance. The consortium seeks to evaluate promising nanotechnology platforms and facilitate their successful translation from academic research to the clinic, resulting in safe, timely, effective, and novel diagnosis and treatment options for patients.</p>
<p>By encouraging mutual collaborations between Alliance investigators and industry partners on both pre-competitive and late-stage programs, TONIC stands to promote the qualification, development, and regulatory acceptance of nanotechnologies in cancer.</p>
<p><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1051622" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051622" sys_relationshipid="6889743">Contact NSDB</a> to learn about participating in TONIC.</p>
<h3>Start-Up Challenge</h3>
<p><a href="http://www.thecenterforadvancinginnovation.org/">The Center for Advancing Innovation</a> and&nbsp;NCI have partnered to launch the <a href="http://www.nscsquared.org/">Nanotechnology Startup Challenge</a> in Cancer.&nbsp;This Challenge features inventions conceived and developed by scientists at the National Institutes of Health and is also open to teams that bring other promising cancer nano-technology inventions. The goal of the challenge is to accelerate and increase the volume of commercialized cancer nanotechnology by launching new startups.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051490" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The use of nanotechnology for diagnosis and treatment of cancer is largely still in the development phase. However, there are already several nanocarrier-based drugs on the market and many more nano-based therapeutics in clinical trials.&nbsp; The application of nanotechnology to medicine includes the use of precisely engineered materials to develop novel therapies and devices that may reduce toxicity as well as enhance the efficacy and delivery of treatments. As a result, the application of nanotechnology to cancer can lead to many advances in the prevention, detection, and treatment of cancer. The first nanotechnology-based cancer drugs have passed regulatory scrutiny and are already on the market including Doxil<sup>&reg;</sup> and Abraxane<sup>&reg;</sup>.</p>
<p>In recent years, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has approved numerous Investigational New Drug (IND) applications for nano-formulations, enabling clinical trials for breast, gynecological, solid tumor, lung, mesenchymal tissue, lymphoma, central nervous system and genito-urinary cancer treatments. The majority of these trials repurpose the previously approved technologies described above.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051623" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051623" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="6654272">NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology </a>funds development of new technologies to bring the next generation of cancer treatments and diagnostics to the clinic.</p>
<h2>Approved Cancer Drug Therapies Based on Nanotechnology</h2>
<table class="table-default" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
<tbody>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<th style="height: 13px;">Product</th>
<th style="height: 13px;">Company</th>
<th style="height: 13px;">Nanoparticle material</th>
<th style="height: 13px;">Drug</th>
<th style="height: 13px;">Indication</th>
<th style="height: 13px;">FDA</th>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35.97px;">
<td style="height: 35.97px;">
<p>Abraxane</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35.97px;">
<p>Abraxis/Celgene</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35.97px;">
<p>Nanoparticle-bound albumin</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35.97px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045258&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045258&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Paclitaxel</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35.97px;">
<p>Breast cancer, Pancreatic cancer, Non-small-cell lung cancer</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35.97px;">
<p>2005</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>DaunoXome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Galen</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Liposome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045261&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045261&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Daunorubicin</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Kaposi&rsquo;s sarcoma</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>1996</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>DepoCyt</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Pacira</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Liposome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045155&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045155&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Cytarabine</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Neoplastic meningitis</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>1999</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 108px;">
<td style="height: 108px;">
<p>Doxil</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 108px;">
<p>Johnson and Johnson</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 108px;">
<p>Liposome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 108px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045140&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045140&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Doxorubicin</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 108px;">
<p>Kaposi&rsquo;s sarcoma,</p>
<p>Ovarian cancer,</p>
<p>Breast cancer,</p>
<p>Multiple myeloma</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 108px;">
<p>1995</p>
<p>1999</p>
<p>2003</p>
<p>2007 (Europe, Canada)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Genexol-PM</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Samyang/Biopharm</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>PEG-PLA polymeric micelle</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045258&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045258&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Paclitaxel</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Breast cancer, Lung cancer, Ovarian cancer</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>2007 (South Korea)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Lipo-Dox</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Taiwan Liposome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Liposome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045140&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045140&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Doxorubicin</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Kaposi&rsquo;s sarcoma, Breast cancer, Ovarian cancer</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>1998 (Taiwan)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Marqibo</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Talon</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Liposome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045435&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045435&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Vincristine</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Acute lymphoid leukemia</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>2012</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Mepact</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Takeda</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Liposome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000644755&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000644755&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Mifamurtide</a> MTP-PE</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Osteosarcoma</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>2009 (EU)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Myocet</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Cephalon</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Liposome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045140&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045140&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Doxorubicin</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Breast Cancer</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>2000 (EU)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>NanoTherm</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Magforce Nanotechnologies</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Iron oxide nanoparticle</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Thermal ablation glioblastoma</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>2010 (EU)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Oncaspar</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Enzon-Sigma-tau</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Polymer protein conjugate</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000601030&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000601030&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">L-asparaginase</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Leukemia</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>2006</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Onivyde</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Merrimack Pharma</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Liposome</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p><a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045391&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="/Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045391&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Irinotecan</a></p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>Pancreatic cancer</p>
</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>2015</p>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Adapted from Wicki A, Witzigmann D, Balasubramanian V, Huwyler J. Nanomedicine in cancer therapy: challenges, opportunities, and clinical applications. J Control Release (2015) 200: pp. 138-57.</p>
<h2>Nanotechnology in Clinical Trials</h2>
<p>Promising new Alliance-developed diagnostics and therapies are in clinical trials. <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1051476" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051476" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" sys_relationshipid="6654271">Learn more about these nanotechnology-based advances.</a></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051518" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="1">
<h2>Center Overview</h2>
<p>The Nanosystems Biology Cancer Center (NSBCC) is a partnership between the California Institute of Technology, the Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center (JCCC) at the University of California Los Angeles (UCLA), and the David Geffen School of Medicine. The NSBCC is led by the renowned scientists, James Heath of CalTech and Mike Phelps of UCLA.&nbsp; Both are supported by a team of co-investigators whom cross the projects from these institutions. The NSBCC was supported by the prior two rounds of CCNE funding, but it enters into this new funding period with a new set of faculty and a mission centered around trying to understand how best to administer combination therapies for cancer patients. The Center's cancer focus is on advanced brain cancers, as a model for a heterogeneous cancer that is effectively untreatable, and melanoma, as a model for understanding and expanding the power of immunotherapy. The NSBCC has four projects and two cores listed below.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1097028" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6749521">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=687270&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1097028&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Overall goals of the NanoSystems and Biology Cancer Center (NSBCC) include bringing novel tools and biological insight for treating glioblastoma multiforme and metastatic melanomas. The novel tools include a set of single cell analytics, nanotechnology based devices and delivery systems as well as novel animal models from patient derived tumor samples.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: CalTech CCNE</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Projects</h2>
<h3>Project 1: Targeted Nanoparticle Therapeutics for Treating Intracranial Disease</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Mark Davis, Ph.D., Timothy Cloughesy, M.D., and David Nathanson, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Project 1 is led by Mark Davis, a pioneer in the development of nanoparticle therapeutics for cancer, with co-investigators Timothy Cloughesy, M.D., a clinical researcher, and David Nathanson, who has built a library of patient derived mouse models of brain cancer for testing response to therapies. The project is focused on developing nanotherapeutics that can cross the blood-brain barrier by combining state-of-the-art nanotherapeutics, deep clinical experience, and patient derived murine models.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1097034" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6749522">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=687270&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1097034&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="Project 1 focus is on nanoparticle therapies for delivery across the blood-brain barrier (BBB). " /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Project 1's focus is on nanoparticle therapies for delivery across the blood-brain barrier (BBB). Delivery across this barrier is traditionally one of the toughest biological barriers to deliver therapy the other side of. Project 1 is developing a novel nanoparticle (NP) system to target BBB, cross BBB, and ultimately deliver chemotherapeutics to the tumor. The figure above depicts the general strategy to develop the platform and novel animal models as well as testing of in vivo efficacy.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: CalTech CCNE</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h3>Project 2: Specifically Targeting Oncoproteins with PCC Agent-Loaded Nanoparticles</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: James Heath, Ph.D., Mark Davis, Ph.D., Raymond Deshaies, Ph.D., and Johannes Czernin, M.D.</p>
<p>In Project 2, NSBCC PI James Heath will collaborate with Mark Davis, Raymond Deshaies, Ph.D. and Johannes Czernin, M.D. to design molecular and nanotechnologies for targeting specific oncoproteins, with a particular focus on KRASG12D. In previous funding cycles, NSBCC resources were leveraged to help develop protein catalyzed capture agents (PCCs). PCCs can be targeted to bind to specific mutated sites on at least certain oncoproteins, with high selectivity relative to wildtype. This provides the opportunity for drug-targeting only diseased tissues. Here, PCCs will be combined with nanotherapeutics and novel proteolysis targeting chimeric antigen (PROTAC) methods developed by Raymond Deshaies to develop a new class of targeted cancer therapies.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1097035" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6749523">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=687270&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1097035&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="The Project 2 focus is on development of Protein Catalyzed Capture (PCC) Agents as cancer drugs." /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>The Project 2 focus is on development of Protein Catalyzed Capture (PCC) Agents as cancer drugs. The primary goal is to enable more specific definition of tumor tissue/cell binding sites that will enable novel therapeutics. The figure above displays one of several aspects of this project utilizing experimentally defined parameters to guide novel molecular dynamics simulation of these sites.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: CalTech CCNE</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h3>Project 3: Tools for Capturing Immune Cell / Cancer Cell Interactions in Cancer Immunotherapies and Combination Immunotherapies</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Antoni Ribas, Ph.D., and Mikhail Shapiro, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Project 3 is led by Antoni Ribas, a pioneer in cancer immunotherapy, and Mikhail Shapiro, an expert in nano-enabled imaging techniques. This project represents a continuation of a cancer immunotherapy theme that has existed within the NSBCC for that past 10 years, but with goals that are informed by the recent dramatic advances in the field. Aim 1 is focused on applying a new class of nanotechologies towards identifying the matched antigen specificity and T cell receptor a/b gene sequence for each T cell that infiltrates into a tumor. Aim 2 is focused on applying new molecular nanotechnologies towards understanding the emergence of resistance that is seen in some patients treated with anti-PD1 checkpoint inhibitor therapy. Aim 3 is a new nanobubble ultrasound imaging technology for monitoring T cell trafficking in vivo. Project collaborators will include James Heath and David Baltimore, Ph.D.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1097036" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6749524">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=687270&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1097036&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="The NSBCC Project 3 he Project 3 focus is on utilizing a new class of nanotechologies towards identifying the matched antigen specificity and T cell receptor a/b gene sequence for each T cell that infiltrates into a tumor." /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>The Project 3 focus is on utilizing a new class of nanotechologies towards identifying the matched antigen specificity and T cell receptor a/b gene sequence for each T cell that infiltrates into a tumor. An area overall that will help to identify cancer patient response to immunotherapies, which still represents a major barrier to this therapeutic modality. The figure above represents the general scheme by which this project will develop and correlate these libraries of antigens to T cells for the eventual application of tools that can measure patient response in vivo.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: CalTech CCNE</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h3>Project 4: A Discovery-Level Functional Proteomics / Metabolomics Platform for Resolving the Heterogeneity of GBM Tumors and Identifying Effective Therapy Combinations</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: David Nathanson, Ph.D., James Heath, Ph.D., Wei Wei, Ph.D., Michael Phelps, Ph.D., and Timothy Cloughesy, M.D.</p>
<p>Led by David Nathanson, Project 4 is centered around nanotechnology for resolving the heterogeneity of GBM tumors and identifying effective combination therapies for treating patients. Nathanson will collaborate with Wei Wei, Ph.D., James Heath, Timothy Cloughesy and Michael Phelps to apply nanotechnologies to study and understand GBM patient responses, and to use the results of measurements to guide effective combination therapies. At the heart of the technology platform are very highly multiplexed, integrated metabolic and functional proteomic single cell assay platforms, expanding up to near 100 analytes assayed, and with applications to both studies of intracranial patient-derived murine models, as well as the analysis of resected patient tissue.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1097037" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6749525">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=687270&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1097037&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="NSBCC's Project 4 focuses upon using novel patient-derived animal models to understand glioblastoma multiforme." /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Project 4 focuses upon using novel patient-derived animal models to understand glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) and its subsequent heterogeneity. The downstream goal is develop and apply this understanding for novel drug combinations and immunotherapeutic response in patients with GBM. The figure above displays the various nanoscale tools being used to understand GBM physiology in these novel animal models and via single-cell analytics.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: CalTech CCNE</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="3">
<h2>Cores</h2>
<h3>Nano / micro Fabrication and Materials (NM2) Core</h3>
<p>Core Investigators: James Heath, Ph.D., and Young Shik Shin, Ph.D.</p>
<p>The NM2 core is a common set of facilities for fabricating the technological platforms of the NSBCC, and providing access to commonly studied cell lines and data bases.</p>
<h3>Crump Preclinical Imaging Technology Center</h3>
<p>Core Investigator: Michael Phelps, Ph.D.</p>
<p>The imaging core provides services to all four projects. The NSBCC also takes advantage of a number of core facilities within the JCCC and CIT.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051519" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="1">
<h2>Center Overview</h2>
<p>Current cancer treatment methodologies fall short of providing efficacious, targeted, precision therapies geared towards the individual patient. Due to their novel chemical, biological, and physical properties, nucleic-acid based nanoconstructs can be used to gain access to privileged intracellular environments, discover new aspects of cancer biology, and exploit nanostructure-biomolecular interactions to create effective treatment options. The Northwestern CCNE will explore these vast possibilities by applying a novel class of nanostructure genetic constructs - the spherical nucleic acid (SNA) and variants of it - for the study and treatment of brain and prostate cancer.&nbsp;</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091042" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6653030">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091042" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>SNAs enter cells in large quantities as single-entity agents and have been shown to cross the blood-brain-barrier (BBB) and the blood-tumor-barrier (BTB) in a systemic delivery scheme, and the epidermis in a topical approach. Once inside the cellular environment, SNAs resist enzymatic degradation, do not elicit toxicity or immunogenicity, and can be used to regulate gene expression via antisense and RNAi pathways. SNAs form the foundation of the technological focus of the Northwestern CCNE which, once successful, will generate a large body of fundamental knowledge that will stand to unravel a portion of the complex landscape of cancer genetics and biology, and deliver two first-in-class SNA nanostructure-based agents - a therapeutic for precision neuro-oncology that can be used to treat glioblastoma multiforme and a therapeutic cancer vaccine that can be used to treat prostate cancer.</p>
<p>The Northwestern CCNE is led by International Institute for Nanotechnology Director, Chad A. Mirkin, PhD, and Robert H. Lurie Comprehensive Cancer Center Director, Leonidas Platanias, MD. Dr. Mirkin and Dr. Platanias bring extensive knowledge, skill, and experience to the enterprise, and together, share the authority and responsibility for leading and directing the project.</p>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Projects</h2>
<h3>Project 1: Design Rules for SNAs that Target Cancer</h3>
<p>Project Investigator: Milan Mrksich, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Led by Professor of Chemistry Milan Mrksich, this project will develop the design rules for the synthesis of SNAs with maximum / optimal gene regulatory or immunostimulatory capacity. Major goals include the analysis of the bulk responses from thousands of cells and the use of NanoFlare technology and microfluidic systems to probe and analyze the individual responses of single cells. The data from these measurements will be used to develop structure-activity rules that guide the optimization of nanoparticle therapeutics for Projects 2 and 3. The work will identify those structural features that promote (as well as detract from) the wanted pharmacological effects.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091316" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6653031">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091316&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<h3>Project 2: SNAs for Metabolic Reprogramming of Malignant Glioma</h3>
<p>Project Investigator: Alexander Stegh, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Project 2 is led by Alexander Stegh, an Assistant Professor and Zell Scholar in the Department of Neurology. The project will preferentially inhibit, in GBM cells, one of the most fundamentally important energy generating pathways, the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle, and, in so doing, trigger tumor cell killing induced by inhibitors of receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKi). Major goals of this project include functionally evaluating a library of IDH1-targeting SNAs to identify high-activity constructs, evaluating siIDH1-SNAs as adjuvant for RTKi in GBM subtype-defined PDX models, and determining anti-glioma effects of siIDH1-SNAs and RTKIs in a genetically engineered mouse (GEM) model for GBM. This project will comprehensively characterize IDH1 as a novel therapeutic target in GBM, and provide preclinical proof-of-concept that the systemic transfer of siRNAs targeted to IDH1 as adjuvant for RTKi is an effective new strategy to combat malignant brain cancers.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091317" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6653032">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091317&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<h3>Project 3: SNAs as Immunotherapeutic Agents for Prostate Cancer</h3>
<p>Project Investigator: Chad A. Mirkin, Ph.D.</p>
<p>This is a translational project led by Center PI Chad Mirkin. This project will develop a new class of therapeutic vaccines based on SNAs for the treatment of prostate cancer. SNAs represent a therapeutic platform for the rational design of nanostructures that induce potent immunostimulatory responses directed towards prostate tumor antigens. Major goals of this project include the design and synthesis of immunostimulatory SNAs (IS-SNA) for lymphocyte activation, analysis of the immunostimulatory activity of IS-SNAs with a panel of standardized <em>in vitro</em> assays, assessment and characterization of IS-SNA activity in immunocompetent mouse models, and development of combination therapies for an optimized cancer immunotherapy: immunostimulation by IS-SNAs combined with modulation of the immunosuppression of solid tumors. The IS-SNA platform is expected to show excellent immunostimulatory properties in the treatment of prostate cancer. Furthermore, the combinations of IS-SNAs and tumor microenvironment modulators are expected to show synergy, and lead to improved therapeutic outcomes over those of either agent alone. These results will inform the design of early stage clinical studies that involve the combination of these agents to be conducted by the commercialization partner.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091318" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6653033">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091318&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<p></p>
</section>
<section id="3">
<h2>Cores</h2>
<h3>Oligonucleotide Synthesis and Nanoconstructs Core</h3>
<p>Core Investigator: Teri W. Odom, Ph.D.</p>
<p>This core will provide large quantities of optimized, high-quality SNAs to the projects for preclinical translational research. The core will also seek to better understand how the architecture of the SNA affects its behavior in biological environments.</p>
<h3>Developmental Program</h3>
<p>Center Program Director: Chad Mirkin, Ph.D.</p>
<p>The Northwestern CCNE will include a developmental program designed to broaden capabilities by providing support for junior faculty to engage in pilot projects in emerging high risk/high reward areas and for trans-Alliance research and training projects as well as projects to cross-test novel frameworks.</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051520" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="1">
<h2>Center Overview</h2>
<p>The scientific theme of the MC2TCN is based on advancing and translating a suite of ultrasmall (&lt;10 nm) fluorescent silica organic hybrid nanoparticles, referred to as Cornell dots (or C dots), with tunable size, brightness, and geometry that may dramatically impact the way we diagnose and treat tumors on the basis of their favorable physicochemical, imaging, and biological properties. Earlier generation cancer-targeted C dots for both PET and optical imaging received FDA investigational new drug (IND) approvals for first-in-human clinical trials. Informed by these successes, MC2TCN will develop real-time intraoperative near infra-red (NIR) fluorescence detection tools to improve localization, staging, and treatment of melanoma, in addition to therapeutic delivery vehicles for enhancing targeted particle uptake, penetration, and efficacy in malignant brain tumors. The Center addresses common problems in oncology related to a lack of exquisitely bright, cancer-specific intraoperative visualization tools for targeted treatment of poorly prognostic nodal metastases, as well as the need for better targeted therapeutic delivery vehicles that may overcome the unfavorable biological properties, dose-limiting toxicity, and modest efficacy associated with native small molecule inhibitors (SMIs). The Center will (1) create new &lt;10 nm probes with finely-tuned properties for reliably and accurately detecting cancer and/or normal tissue targets in surgical settings; (2) engineer &lt;10 nm delivery vehicles incorporating SMIs or radiotherapies that can individually, or in combination with immunotherapies, selectively and efficaciously treat cancer, and (3) identify and qualify potential staging, prognostic and/or predictive biomarkers of response that can be validated by future clinical trial designs.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1096438" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6703702">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=687270&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1096438" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
The two PIs leading the Center will be Drs. Michelle Bradbury (MSKCC) and Ulrich Wiesner (Cornell), who have been inter-institutional collaborators on the development and translation of C dots for over nine years. Dr. Michelle Bradbury, the Director of Intraoperative Imaging, Department of Radiology (MSKCC), holds a Joint appointment at Sloan Kettering Institute, and is an Associate Professor of Radiology at Weill Cornell Medical College. Her expertise is largely translational, and based in the areas of nanomedicine and molecular imaging. Prof. Wiesner is the Spencer T. Olin Professor of Engineering in the Materials Science and Engineering Department of Cornell University, with expertise in polymer and silica sol-gel derived nanomaterials.
<p></p>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Projects</h2>
<h3>Project 1: Highly-Integrated Ultrasmall and Bright Fluorescent Silica Particle Architectures</h3>
<p>Project Investigator: Ulrich Wiesner, Ph.D.</p>
<p>The primary objective of Project 1, a basic research effort led by Ulrich Wiesner, is the synthesis and exploration of novel classes of &lt; 10 nm C dots synthesized in water for use as cancer-targeted diagnostic and therapeutic probes. Major goals include using high-resolution analytical tools to characterize variations in particle size, composition, geometry, surface chemistry, and material heterogeneity, and correlate these variations with pharmacokinetics, renal clearance, and tumor-to-background ratios in melanoma models. Expected outcomes are particle structure-biological property correlations enabling economic particle synthesis in water and clinical translation.</p>
<h3>Project 2: Real-time Intraoperative Imaging of Cancer Biomarkers and Peripheral Nerves</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Michelle Bradbury, M.D., Ph.D., and Snehal Patel, M.D.</p>
<p>The primary objective of Project 2, a translational research effort led by Michelle Bradbury and co-lead Snehal Patel, Associate Professor of Surgery at MSKCC, is optimization of new generation C dots for earlier and more reliable detection of multiple targets on melanoma-bearing lymph nodes and / or adjacent nerves, using an FDA-approved handheld intraoperative fluorescence camera. Major goals include development and screening of NIR dye-containing melanoma-targeting particles; selection of lead candidates to assess tumor-specific accumulation and pharmacokinetic profiles in conventional / GEMM animal models; and development of spectrally-distinct NIR dye-containing products for simultaneous differentiation of distinct pathological markers on diseased nodal tissue and normal tissue types. Expected outcomes include novel image-guided multiplexing tools to visualize both disease and normal critical structures for better surgical management and reduced surgical risks.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1096437" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6703703">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=687270&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1096437" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<h3>Project 3: Targeted Ultrasmall Silica Nanoparticles for Alpha- and Beta-Emitting Radiotherapy and Delivery of Small Molecule Inhibitors</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Thomas Quinn, Ph.D., Michael McDevitt, Ph.D., Cameron Brennan, M.D., and Charles Rudin, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<p>The primary objectives of translational research Project 3 are to (1) target radiolabeled C dots to melanoma to deliver highly localized radiation doses and (2) deliver and release SMIs from nanoparticle-drug conjugates (NDCs) to malignant brain tumors. Melanoma studies will be led by Thomas Quinn, Professor of Biochemistry, University of Missouri, with co-lead Michael McDevitt, Radiologist, MSKCC. Major goals for melanoma models include the generation of optimized targeted C dots exhibiting favorable biological properties in melanoma models, as well as the development of safe and efficacious alpha- and beta-emitting C dots for clinical translation. Expected outcomes include the advancement of targeted C dot radiotherapeutics as part of combinatorial treatment paradigms with immunotherapies to improve melanoma management. Major goals of the malignant brain tumor studies, led by Cameron Brennan, M.D., Associate Member, Human Oncology and Pathogenesis Program, Sloan Kettering Institute, and Associate Professor of Neurosurgery, Weill Cornell Medical Center with co-lead Charles Rudin, M.D., Ph.D., Chief, Thoracic Oncology, MSKCC, will include the creation of optimized NDCs that exhibit favorable biological properties and overcome dose-limiting toxicity for use in combinatorial brain tumor treatment strategies. Expected outcomes include the development of potent NDCs with improved PK profiles, tumor accumulation, and enhanced therapeutic index.</p>
</section>
<section id="3">
<h2>Cores</h2>
<h3>Nanoparticle Synthesis and Characterization Core</h3>
<p>Core Investigator: Teresa Porri, Ph.D.</p>
<p>This core, at Cornell and led by Teresa Porri, will support center activities for particle synthesis and characterization, as well as gel permeation chromatography and high performance liquid chromatography equipment for detailed particle characterization.</p>
<h3>Imaging and Radiochemistry Core</h3>
<p>Core Investigator: Pat Zanzonico, Ph.D.</p>
<p>This core, at MSKCC and led by Pat Zanzonico, will support center activities for imaging and radiochemistry and will provide expertise and state-of-the-art instrumentation in positron emission tomography, fluorescence imaging, and cyclotron production of radionuclides.</p>
<h3>Developmental Program</h3>
<p>Center Program Director: Michelle Bradbury, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<p>The goals of MC2TCN will be further enhanced by a developmental program supporting pilot projects, with primary focus on probes below 10 nm.</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051521" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="1">
<h2>Center Overview</h2>
<p>The CCNE-TD, which forms the third cycle CCNE Program at Stanford University, is a consortium that has three highly synchronized Projects and three Cores. Since its initial funding in May 2006, the Stanford CCNE program has matured substantially into a strong multidisciplinary program with expertise and infrastructure to support the growing field of cancer nanomedicine. PI Sanjiv Sam Gambhir, M.D., Ph.D. is the Chairman of the Department of Radiology at Stanford and an expert in Molecular Imaging, Radiology and Bioengineering. MPI Shan X. Wang, Ph.D., is a Professor of Materials Science and Engineering as well as Electrical engineering at Stanford. He has spent the major portion of his career focused on magneto nanobio-sensing. Deputy Director Demir Akin, D.V.M., Ph.D., is an interdisciplinary scientist and a well-known nanomedicine expert. Together, Drs. Gambhir, Wang and Akin provide an enormous breadth of experience ranging from fundamental nanoscience and engineering, to pre-clinical imaging, and on to translation of molecular imaging and cancer nanodiagnostics for clinical applications. The Center is composed of a highly interdisciplinary team of scientists whose expertise areas are highly synergistic and have a long collaboration history that extends to the first cycle of the NCI's CCNE Program.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1090883" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6657146">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090883&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Stanford CCNE Overview and Project Focus Diagram</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: Stanford University</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The CCNE-TD will develop and clinically translate cancer diagnostics and imaging technologies in two scientific thematic focus areas: i) predicting and monitoring cancer therapy response in lung cancer and ii) merging nano-based <em>in vitro</em> and <em>in vivo</em> diagnostics strategies and nano-based imaging for earlier cancer detection and prognostication of prostate cancer. CCNE-TD investigators will utilize nanotechnology to measure changes in cancer patterns via 1) imaging though cancer-triggered-self-assembling as well as dis-assembling nanoparticles (Projects 1 and 3) and 2) in serum using magneto-nano sensors (Project 2). Center nanotechnologies will be used to interrogate single cells for DNA, RNA, proteins, cellular micro/nano vesicles, to evaluate biomarker potentials of those (Projects 2 and 3), and will again utilize nanotechnology (e.g., self-assembling nanoparticles and nanobubbles) to image cell associated proteins in small animal models, as well as humans, and clinically translate them for human prostate cancer imaging with ultrasound / photoacoustics (Project 3). In all of these cases, changes at the molecular level are being measured within the cell, on the cell membrane, and in the extracellular matrix. We believe that measuring these changes is critical to the problem of earlier cancer detection and monitoring response to therapies with both the <em>ex vivo</em> diagnostic nanosensor technologies and the <em>in vivo</em> imaging technologies.</p>
<p>The Center has two major technological arms: i) <em>in vitro</em> genomic/proteomic/cellomic nanosensors, and ii) <em>in vivo</em> molecular imaging with primarily gold as well as nanobubble-based nanoparticles, and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with novel self-assembling and disassembling nanoparticles. The latter arm is directly focused on molecular imaging with specific cellular protein targets. These targets are the basis whereby specific molecular imaging signal is provided. It is the goal of the CCNE-TD to help identify these targets for specific cancers (lung and prostate) and their biochemical pathways and to utilize these targets as ways to home in on cancer cells. In addition, our new class of nanoparticles that can self-assemble intracellularly, from the cell permeable precursors, in a cancer specific manner, in conjunction with our advanced magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) expertise, is expected to directly impact the development of medical imaging modalities for eventual clinical translation. With our highly interactive and cohesive program focused on developing and validating nanotechnology for anti-cancer therapy response, earlier cancer detection and prognostication, we will imagine, invent, and innovate for the benefit of cancer patients.</p>
<p><a href="http://med.stanford.edu/ccne/ccne-td.html">Visit the Stanford CCNE Website</a></p>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Projects</h2>
<h3>Project 1: Multimodality Self-Assembling and Disassembling Nanoparticles</h3>
<p>Project Investigator: Jianghong Rao , Ph.D.</p>
<p>Led by Jianghong Rao, an Associate Professor of Radiology and Chemistry, this project focuses on the development of novel, cancer-triggered self-assembling and disassembling nanoparticles for photoacoustic and PET-MRI visualization of tumors.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1090884" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6657147">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090884&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Stanford CCNE Project 1 Overview</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: Stanford University</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h3>Project 2: Multiscale Nanotechnologies for Comprehensive Assessment of Lung Cancer in Blood</h3>
<p>Project Investigator: Shan Wang, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Project 2, led by Center PI Shan Wang, focuses on the use of magneto-nanotechnology for blood proteomics, single cell sorting and comprehensive analyses.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1090885" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6657148">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090885&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Stanford CCNE Project 2 Overview</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: Standford University</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h3>Project 3: Multimodality Molecular Nanoimaging of Cancer</h3>
<p>Project Investigator: Sam Gambhir, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<p>Project 3, led by Center PI Sam Gambhir, will pursue molecular imaging of prostate cancer through photoacoustic imaging with smart nanoparticles made by Project 1. The project will also develop strategies for monitoring response to anti-lung cancer therapy using imaging and magneto-nanosensors.&nbsp;</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1090886" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6657149">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090886&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Stanford CCNE Project 3 Overview</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: Stanford University</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="3">
<h2>Cores</h2>
<h3>NanoCharacterization and NanoFabrication Core</h3>
<p>Core Investigator: Robert Sinclair, Ph.D.</p>
<p>The NanoCharacterization and NanoFabrication Core is led by Robert Sinclair. The Nano Characterization and Nano Fabrication research core will provided advanced characterization and synthesis support for the projects within the CCNE-TD. The core consists of the Stanford Nano Shared Facilities (SNSF) which is comprised of the Stanford Nanocharacterization Laboratory (SNL) and the Stanford Nano Center (SNC) offering resources for the analysis and fabrication of nanostructures and their interactions with biological materials.</p>
<h3>Clinical Translation Core</h3>
<p>Core Investigator: Alice Fan, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<p>The Clinical Translation Core is led by Alice Fan. This core facilitates clinical translation by linking Center nanotechnologies to existing patient samples and ongoing as well as new clinical trials.</p>
<h3>Developmental Program</h3>
<p>Center Program Director: Sam Gambhir, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<p>The Center has set aside funds for developing Pilot Projects to extend Center capabilities over the five year performance period. Center leadership have also raised substantial funds internally at Stanford to run additional seed / developmental projects. These internally sponsored projects with focus on clinical translation will be at no-cost to NIH-NCI.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051522" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="1">
<h2>Center Overview</h2>
<p>Host response targeting of both immune and stromal components represents an enormous opportunity to overcome cancer through the body's built in defense mechanisms. The focus of the UNC-Chapel Hill CCNE is to exploit the host response through nano approaches for cancer disease management and treatment. The research team is led by Principal Investigators Leaf Huang, Ph.D. and Joel Tepper, M.D. Leaf Huang is a pioneer in liposome research and non-viral gene therapy. He was the first</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha;">
<li>to publish grafting polyethylene glycol to liposomes to enhance the circulation time; and</li>
<li>to develop a low toxicity cationic lipid for gene transfection.</li>
</ol>
<p>Joel Tepper, M.D. is an accomplished leader and clinical and translational investigator who has contributed at both the local and national level to translational research and was co-PI of the previous UNC CCNE. The Center proposes developing targeted methods for the delivery of biologics and immunologic modifiers and chemotherapies against melanoma and non-small cell lung cancers (NSCLC), utilizing innovative nanotechnologies developed at UNC. There are four projects in the CCNE. The projects revolve around the central theme of exploiting the host response against tumors with an emphasis on the immune response. Center projects emphasize the treatment of malignant melanoma, an aggressive tumor with a strong immunological component, and NSCLC, a tumor that when advanced is not well treated by most therapeutic modalities.&nbsp;</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091248" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6654487">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091248&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>University of North Carolina CCNE Overview and Project Focus Diagram</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: University of North Carolina</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://unclineberger.org/ccne">Visit the UNC CCNE Website</a></p>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Projects</h2>
<h3>Project 1: Nanotherapies for Vemurafenib Resistant Melanoma</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Leaf Huang, Ph.D., Jenny Ting, Ph.D., and William Kim, M.D.</p>
<p>Project 1, led by Leaf Huang, Jenny Ting, a world renowned immunologist, and William Kim, a physician scientist with expertise in tumor biology and cancer genomics, is the designated basic science project. Novel polymetformin nanoparticles are being proposed for more efficient and effective delivery of siRNA, which is a critical challenge for drug delivery. The project targets vemurafenib resistant melanoma, and emphasizes direct suppression of drug resistance that is coupled with a new vaccine approach to enhance the effectiveness of treatment of this aggressive tumor.</p>
<h3>Project 2: Nanoparticle-based Immune Modulators in Cancer Therapy and Vaccines</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Jenny Ting, Ph.D., Jon Serody, M.D., and Joseph DeSimone, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Project 2, led by Jenny Ting and Joe DeSimone, an internationally known chemist with major awards for his contributions to chemistry and nanotechnology, along with Jon Serody, a physician scientist who is co-Director of the Immunology Program at the UNC-LCCC. This project evaluates ways to enhance the anti-tumor immune response through novel delivery of antigens via <em>Particle Replication in Non-wetting Templates</em> (PRINT<sup>&reg;</sup>) nanoparticles. Unique adjuvants, such as Pathogen-associated Molecular Patterns, are being explored in this project as well as the active suppression of blockers of host immunity in melanoma.</p>
<h3>Project 3: Combining Radiotherapy and Nanotechnology for Immunotherapy</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Andrew Wang, M.D., Jon Serody, M.D., and Joel Tepper, M.D.</p>
<p>Project 3, led by Dr. Andrew Wang, a physician-scientist with experience in the development of nanotherapeutics, along with Jon Serody and Joel Tepper, and takes advantage of the biology of antigen release and the abscopal effect post irradiation through specifically designed nanoparticles to enhance antigen capture and the immune response to both primary tumors and metastases in melanoma.</p>
<h3>Project 4: High Capacity Polymeric Micelle Therapeutics for Lung Cancer</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Alexander Kabanov, Ph.D., D.Sc., Chad Pecot, M.D., and Andrew Wang, M.D.</p>
<p>Project 4, led by Alexander Kabanov, who has conducted pioneering research on polymeric micelles, NDA/polycation complexes, block ionomer complexes and nanogels, along with Chad Pecot, a physician-scientist interested in RNA interference, and Andrew Wang. This project uses polymeric micelles with high capacity loading to deliver therapeutics targeted to the tumor microenvironment as well as tumor cells in NSCLC.</p>
</section>
<section id="3">
<h2>Cores</h2>
<h3>Small Animal Imaging Core</h3>
<p class="no-t-space">Core Investigator: Zibo Li, Ph.D., Wieli Lin, Ph.D., and Hong Yuan, Ph.D.</p>
<p class="no-t-space">The small animal imaging core leverages extensive UNC small animal imaging capabilities to enhance biodistribution studies and to develop multimodality imaging approaches to evaluate treatment efficacy. The core is led by Zibo Li, Wieli Lin and Hong Yuan, all expert imagers involved in animal imaging and technology development.</p>
<h3 class="no-t-space">Developmental Program</h3>
<p class="no-t-space">Center Program Director: Leaf Huang, Ph.D.</p>
<p class="no-t-space">The Development Program encompasses both pilot projects and auxiliary projects, designed to facilitate the development of new ideas to produce preliminary data for grant applications. The program is intended to support 4 pilot projects annually. There will also be funding available to foster collaborations between Alliance members as well as with other institutions. The Administrative Core is designed to facilitate all of the operations of the UNC CCNE to assure that the scientific work can proceed with maximal efficiency.</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051523" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="1">
<h2>Center Overview</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.mir.wustl.edu/research/research-laboratories/optical-radiology-laboratory-orl/center-for-multiple-myeloma-nanotherapy-cmmn">The Washington University Center for Multiple Myeloma Nanotherapy (WU CMMN)</a> will address overarching questions in bone malignancies, with a focus on multiple myeloma (MM). MM is a hematopoietic disease caused by terminally differentiated malignant plasma B-cells. Despite tremendous improvements in MM patient management, nearly all patients will eventually relapse and die from it. Leveraging the enormous institutional resources and support, diverse expertise in MM, the integral participation of patient advocates and industry partners, and synergistic integration of basic and clinical investigators, the WU CMMN will serve as a comprehensive center for the development of nanotechnology-based solutions for treating MM and bone metastasis. Anchored by three projects and two cores, we aim to improve MM treatment outcomes with minimal off-target toxicity by developing novel nanotherapeutics that combine unique drug delivery mechanisms with spatiotemporal treatment paradigms.</p>
<p>Samuel Achilefu and Gregory Lanza are the PIs/PDs of the Center. Dr. Achilefu is a pioneer in the development of molecular imaging probes and nanomaterials for imaging and treatment of cancer. He currently leads the translation of innovative imaging technologies and molecular probes from bench to bedside. Dr. Lanza is a distinguished leader in the development and translation of nanomaterials to the clinic. He has extensive experience in the practice of medicine, nanomedicine research and development, and pharmaceutical development in large industry as well as small biotechnology start-ups. Three synergistic and highly interactive interdisciplinary research projects will anchor the center. Each project is led by senior investigators with expertise in basic and translational research.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091023" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6671303">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091023&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--> <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1518&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091023&amp;sys_command=edit" target="_blank" class="article-image-enlarge no-resize">Enlarge</a></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Washington University CCNE Overview and Project Focus Diagram</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: Washington University</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Projects</h2>
<h3>Project 1: Preclinical and Clinical Imaging and Treatment of Multiple Myeloma with CMYC-MAX Nanoparticles</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Gregory Lanza, M.D., Ph.D., and Michael Tomasson, M.D.</p>
<p>Project 1 is led by Dr. Lanza and Michael Tomasson, a board-certified hematologist and highly acclaimed expert in both basic and clinical MM research. The team will use smartly designed VLA-4 targeted nanocolloids to selectively deliver novel cMyc-inhibitor prodrugs directly into MM cells to maximize therapy. Through its multiple levels of innovation, Project 1 will revitalize the therapeutic quest to target cMyc for translational development with targeted nanotherapy by synthetically modifying next generation Myc-Max small molecule antagonists.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091024" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6671304">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091024&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Project 1: Small molecule cMYC-inhibitors are incorporated as lipase labile prodrugs in VLA-4-directed Micelles (&lt;20nm).&nbsp; 1) Micelles home beyond the vasculature, penetrate into the extravascular space and bind the alpha 4 beta 1 (VLA-4) cell surface receptor over expressed by multiple myeloma (MM). 2) The micelle forms a hemifusion complex with the MM outer cell membrane and lipid-complexed cMYC prodrug passes into the target cell. 3) The cMYC-prodrug (cMYC-PD) flips from the outer to inner cell membrane, which is contiguous with all of the intracellular membranes of the cell except the mitochondria. 4. Intracellular lipases liberate the cMYC active drug from the inactive lipid prodrug complex, which becomes available to interact with cMYC transcription factor (TF) in the cytosol (4b).&nbsp; 4a Uncomplexed cMYC TF can penetrate into the nucleus, complex with MAX transcription factor to form a heterodimer that interacts with the E-box of DNA to stimulate cell proliferation (5a). cMYC inhibited by the free Myc-inhibitor in the cytosol can enter the nucleus but cannot complex with MAX. This disrupts MM cell proliferation and promotes MM apoptosis.</p>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h3>Project 2: Spatiotemporally Controlled Light Therapy of Multiple Myeloma</h3>
<p>Project Investigators: Samuel Achilefu, Ph.D., Katherine Weilbaecher, M.D., and Pratim Biswas, Ph.D.</p>
<p>Project 2 will utilize a novel spatiotemporal phototherapy to eradicate MM. The team will develop new photosensitizers that will generate diverse cytotoxic free radicals upon absorption of light from radionuclides inside MM cells. Through the ensuing multidimensional assault, the approach will selectively destroy MM cells with minimal systemic toxicity. Dr. Achilefu will lead this Project, accompanied by Katherine Weilbaecher, M.D., a world-class investigator and oncologist whose research interests are focused on understanding the molecular mechanisms of bone cancer and metastasis, and Pratim Biswas, Ph.D., an internationally recognized expert in high precision, metal-based nanomaterials synthesis.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091025" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6671305">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091025&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Washington University CCNE Project 2 Overview</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: Washington University</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h3>Project 3: Combination Therapy to Improve the Efficacy of Multiple Myeloma-Targeted Nanotherapeutics</h3>
<p>Project Investigator: John DiPersio, M.D., Ph.D., and William Frazier, Ph.D</p>
<p>Project 3 is discovery-focused and led by John DiPersio, a preeminent authority in the treatment of refractory and relapsed hematological malignancies and hematopoietic stem cell transplantation, and William Frazier, Ph.D, a pioneer in the field of thrombospondins and the discoverer of CD47, which is used in modulating bone marrow niche. The team will use innovative approaches for combination therapy with the bone marrow niche disrupting agents to enhance the efficacy of MM killing by the nanotherapeutics developed in Projects 1 and 2. The project will also elucidate the molecular mechanisms of nano-induced MM cell death.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091026" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6671306">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091026&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Washington University CCNE Project 3 Overview</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: Washington University</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="3">
<h2>Cores</h2>
<h3>Imaging Biomarker Quanification and Standardization (IBQS)</h3>
<p>Core Investigator: Kooresh Shoghi, Ph.D.</p>
<p>The IBQS Core will develop quantitative benchmarks for assessing response to therapy in preclinical models of MM, thereby facilitating the clinical translation of the nanotherapeutics developed in Projects 1-3. This Core is led by Kooresh Shoghi, an expert in quantitative imaging technology with an established track record in correlating image biomarkers of disease with tissue biomarkers.</p>
<h3>Data Management</h3>
<p>Core Investigator: Fred Prior, Ph.D.</p>
<p>The Data Management Core will develop data acquisition and integration processes and procedures for each project, and interface local data with the NCI's caNanoLab. This Core is led by Fred Prior, an expert and leader in creating petabyte scale information repositories and in developing advanced techniques to mine new knowledge from these resources. He is also the PI of the Cancer Imaging Archive (TCIA) program.</p>
<h3>Developmental Program</h3>
<p>Center Program Director: Samuel Achilefu, Ph.D.</p>
<p>CMMN Developmental Program will support pilot and auxiliary projects that will augment the use of nanotechnology to improve the quality of life for MM and other cancer patients. This Program will encourage new and innovative approaches to increase the clinical impact of nanotechnology in oncology by linking physicians, biologists, physical scientists, engineers, bioinformatics, and technologists for the purpose of improving diagnosis, prevention, and treatment of cancer.</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051570" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Efstathios Karathanasis, Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> James Basilion, Ph.D., Mark Griswold, Ph.D., Ketankumar Ghaghada, Ph.D. (Texas Childrens Hospital), and Jeremy Rich, M.D. (Cleveland Clinic).</p>
<section id="1">
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>The invasive forms of brain tumors, such as glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) are characteristically diffused with infiltrating edges, resistant to drugs and nearly inaccessible to systemic therapies due to the brain-tumor barrier. To address the challenges of drug delivery and resistance, our objective is to integrate the unique features of a chain-like nanoparticle with the appropriate combination of complementary drugs to enable effective treatment of invasive brain tumors. These nanochains are comprised of iron oxide nanospheres and a drug-loaded liposome chemically linked into a chain-like assembly with high precision. The nanochain possesses a unique ability to scavenge the tumor endothelium. By utilizing effective vascular targeting of the &alpha;<sub>&nu;</sub>&beta;<sub>3</sub> integrin receptor, the nanochains achieve rapid deposition on the vascular bed of glioma sites establishing well-distributed drug reservoirs on the endothelium of brain tumors. After reaching the target sites, an on-command, external low-power radiofrequency field can remotely trigger rapid drug release, due to mechanical disruption of the liposome, facilitating widespread and effective drug delivery across the brain-tumor barrier into regions harboring brain tumor cells.</p>
<p>To address the drug resistance issue, we have identified glioma stem cell (GSC)-specific regulators amenable to pharmacologic targeting. We recently showed that the inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) is a unique signal regulator in GSCs. Due to the flexibility of loading various types of drugs within the nanochain, the nanochain will be loaded with standard chemotherapy and an iNOS inhibitor that eliminates the small fraction of GBM cells that are resistant, and can migrate to cause tumor recurrence. Due to enhanced site-specific targeting and rapid drug release, we hypothesize that guaranteeing the simultaneous delivery of drugs with synergistic activity into hard-to-reach glioma sites will facilitate effective treatment and ultimately eradication of the disease using a safe dose of the drugs.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091204" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6654521">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091204&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>This project brings together a team of collaborators from Case Comprehensive Cancer Center, Cleveland Clinic, and Texas Childrens Hospital, with a long prior history of collaboration. The investigators exhibit complementary expertise including cancer nanomedicine (Karathanasis), stem cell biology and neuro-oncology (Rich), cancer pharmacology (Basilion), MR physics (Griswold) and translational nanotechnology (Ghaghada).</p>
</section>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051571" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Wenbin Lin, Ph.D., and Ralph Weichselbaum, M.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> Stephen Kron, M.D., Ph.D., and Charles Pelizzari, Ph.D.</p>
<section id="1">
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>Head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) is the sixth most common cancer worldwide. The clinically used combination, radiation and chemotherapy, is the most common curative treatment for HNSCC, but causes many undesirable side effects and will incur a progressive resistance. Photodynamic therapy (PDT) is an effective anticancer procedure although its clinical application is limited due to extreme light sensitivity of patients before/after treatment, a suboptimal reactive oxygen species generation efficiency, and shallow tissue penetration (&lt; 1 cm) due to the frequency of light required. On the other hand, nanoparticle-based photosensitizers (PSs) can selectively accumulate in tumors alleviating the light sensitivity issue and more. Near-IR triggered PDT and X-ray induced PDT (X-PDT) have the ability to combine the strength of improved tissue penetration depth of the near-IR and X-ray modalities with the clinical advantages of PDT for deep tumor treatment. We are developing an entirely new class of nanoparticle PSs based on nanoscale metal-organic frameworks (NMOFs) that have the ideal characteristics of tunable chemical compositions, crystalline structures, extremely high porosity, short-term stability, and long-term biodegradability to enable NIR triggered PDT for superficial tumors and X-PDT for deep tumors. This project addresses the unmet needs in developing highly efficient and safe nanoparticle PSs that can have much broader clinical applications for cancer by NIR-triggered PDT or X-PDT.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091800" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6664465">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091800" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Specifically, in aim 1 we will optimize NMOF structures, particle sizes, and surface characteristics to achieve NIR-triggered PDT and X-PDT with improved efficiency. Efforts will also be made for scaled-up NMOF synthesis and surface functionalization to achieve long blood circulation times. In aim 2, the NIR-PDT efficacy of NMOFs will be evaluated against multiple HNSCC cell lines <em>in vitro</em>. We will investigate the <em>in vivo</em> toxicity and efficacy of one most potent NMOF identified at cellular level against HNSCC subcutaneous xenograft and orthotopic mouse models. Finally, in aim 3 the X-PDT efficacy of NMOFs will be investigated against HNSCC cells <em>in vitro</em>. For the <em>in vivo</em> studies, we will first evaluate the toxicity of the NMOFs and the X-PDT treatment alone. The <em>in vivo</em> anticancer efficacy will be carried out on both subcutaneous and orthotopic HNSCC mouse models with the two most potent NMOFs identified at the cellular level. We will also apply state-of-the-art small-animal image-guided X-Ray delivery technology to enable image-guided X-PDT, toward translation in clinical radiotherapy.</p>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>The project team includes expertise in nanomaterials, chemistry, radiation oncology, multimodality imaging, and molecular/cell/cancer biology.</p>
</section>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051572" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Lily Yang, M.D., Ph.D., and Hui Mao, Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> Charles Staley, M.D., David Kooby, M.D., Bassel El-Rayes, M.D., Malgorzata Lipowska, Ph.D., Liya Wang, M.D., and Andrew Wang, Ph.D. (Ocean Nanotech, LLD)</p>
<section id="1">
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>The goal of this project is to develop a dual targeted and stroma breaking theranostic nanoparticle platform to address an unmet, clinical challenge of poor drug delivery efficiency in the application of nanomedicine to cancer therapy. Many types of human cancers, particularly pancreatic cancer, present a dense fibrotic tumor stroma that creates physical barriers against conventional drug delivery approaches. Building upon our understanding of pancreatic cancer biology and expertise in developing theranostic nanoparticles, we are developing a stroma breaking drug delivery system using a new generation of 3-nm ultra-fine magnetic iron oxide nanoparticle (uIONP) coated with an anti-fouling 'stealth' polymer for enhanced tumor penetration and retention, high capacity drug loading, and T<sub>1</sub>/T<sub>2</sub>-switchable MRI contrasts for imaging drug delivery. A dual targeting strategy coupling ligands targeting urokinase plasminogen activator receptor (uPAR) and insulin-like growth factor 1 receptor (IGF1R) onto a single nanoparticle is used to maximize both tumor stromal and pancreatic cancer cell targeting, and drug delivery. Additionally, the use of a recombinant MMP14 protease active uPAR targeting ligand should break the extracellular matrix barrier. uIONPs will carry cisplatin and / or SN38, a potent camptothecin analogue, for effective treatment of drug resistant pancreatic cancer cells.</p>
<p>The combination of these unique properties should enable the theranostic uIONPs to break tumor stromal barriers and disrupt the tumor microenvironment leading to improved cancer molecular targeting and drug delivery in treating pancreatic cancer. The efficiency of targeted delivery and intratumoral distribution of the uIONP and therapeutic efficacy will be investigated in orthotopic human pancreatic cancer patient tissue-derived xenograft (PDX) and transgenic mouse pancreatic tumor models using MR and optical imaging, multiphoton microscopy, and histological and chemical analyses. This new generation of theranostic IONPs and our strategy to overcome drug delivery barriers will change the paradigm of future development and translation of image-guided and targeted therapies for the treatment of advanced pancreatic cancer as well as cancer nanotechnology in general.&nbsp;</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091251" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6654531">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091251&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>The team has expertise in targeted cancer therapy, theranostic nanoparticles, image-guided cancer treatment, and animal tumor models as well as extensive experience in the development of magnetic nanoparticles as MRI contrasts / drug carriers and MRI methodology.</p>
</section>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051573" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Kit Lam, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> Edward Pugh, Ph.D., Edward Zawadzki, Ph.D., Yuanpei Li, Ph.D., Li Xing, Ph.D., and Wenwu Xiao, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<section id="1">
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>The overarching premise of our project is to use the mouse eye as a non-surgical window for highly efficient, optical investigation of all aspects of syngeneic or xenograft models, using a state-of-the-art ocular imaging facility, the "EyePod." The EyePod employs single-cell resolution intravital confocal microscopy and optical coherence tomography, performed completely non-invasively through the natural optics of the eye. This technology enables repeatable <em>in vivo</em> imaging over weeks and even months, quantitative tracking of tumor development and delivery of theranostic nanoparticles, and the measurement of tumor and tissue responses. Moreover, the retina is a highly "approachable part of the brain", so that non-invasive study of ocular tumors provides a platform for examining such critical issues as drug delivery across the blood brain barrier (BBB) and neurotoxicity. We will employ our recently reported nanoporphyrin in this research.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091323" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6654564">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091323&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This novel multifunctional porphyrin-based micellar nanoplatform allows:</p>
<ul>
<li>efficient encapsulation of hydrophobic chemotherapeutic drugs or fluorescent dyes,</li>
<li>near-infra red fluorescent (NIRF) detection of the tumor via the intrinsic fluorescence of porphyrins,</li>
<li>photodynamic therapy (PDT) and photothermal therapy (PTT) via efficient free radical and heat generation at the tumor site, respectively,</li>
<li>(Gd(III) loading for MRI imaging,</li>
<li><sup>64</sup>Cu loading for PET imaging, and</li>
<li>convenient ligation of cancer-targeting ligands to the surface of the micelle for cancer-specific targeted delivery.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thorough understanding of how this nanocarrier distributes within the tumor microenvironment, and how it responds to controlled optical stimulation will enable us to maximize its therapeutic potential as a nano-theranostic agent. We will also study the effect of active targeting of nanocarriers with tumor and brain endothelial cell targeting peptides.</p>
<p>In more detail, our specific aims include;</p>
<ul>
<li>To develop intraocular glioblastoma and breast cancer xenograft models in eyes of nude mice, and to use non-invasive optical techniques (e.g., EyePod) to study the development of these tumor models at cellular resolution longitudinally over days and weeks, and their response to treatment with nanodoxorubicin;</li>
<li>To use the tumor models and EyePod to study the biodistribution and photo-response of tumor targeting and non-targeting nanoporphyrins within the tumor micro-environment <em>in vivo</em>, and to use cryo-electron microscopy to "dissect" the nanodelivery at the ultrastructural level; and</li>
<li>To optimize brain vascular endothelial cell-penetrating ligands, and to use <em>in vivo</em> EyePod imaging and cryoelectron microscopy to study their nanodelivery into retinal vasculature, and across the blood retinal barrier, which is very similar to blood brain barrier.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>For this effort, we have assembled a team of interdisciplinary scientists covering expertise across the areas of oncology, optics, imaging / microscopy, ophthalmology, nanomedicine, and cancer biology.</p>
</section>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051574" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Hsian-Rong Tseng, Ph.D., and Edwin Posadas, M.D. (Cedars-Sinai Medical Center)</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> Kingshuk Das, M.D., and Xinmin Li, Ph.D.</p>
<section id="1">
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>The long-term objective of this IRCN award is to develop Thermoresponsive (TR)-NanoVelcro circulating tumor cell (CTC) purification system that can be digitally programmed to achieve optimal performance for recovering viable CTCs in prostate cancer (PC) patients' blood, allowing seamless coupling with various downstream molecular assays. The unique mechanism of our devices is that by switching device temperature in a physiologically endurable range (i.e., 4-37 &deg;C), thermoresponsive conformational changes of nanosubstrate-grafted polymer brushes alter the accessibility of capture agent to specifically capture (37 &deg;C) and release (4 &deg;C) CTCs to give viable CTCs in desired purity. Our central hypothesis is that through rational optimization and systematic validation, viable CTCs can be purified for <em>ex vivo</em> expansion, and molecular characterization of freshly isolated and <em>ex vivo</em> expanded CTCs can help better investigate and monitor PC evolution from androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) sensitive states to castration resistant PC (CRPC).</p>
<p>Our major goals are to:</p>
<ul>
<li>develop, optimize and validate TR-NanoVelcro CTC purification system,</li>
<li>demonstrate improved <em>ex vivo</em> expansion of purified CTCs with minimum "expansion bias", and</li>
<li>establish key genomic and transcriptomic events in PC using both <em>ex vivo</em> expanded and freshly purified CTCs and quantify the potential perturbations introduced by TR-NanoVelcro purification system.</li>
</ul>
<p>This nanomaterial-embedded cancer diagnostic platform is expected to introduce a unique rare-cell sorting method that enables detection, isolation, and characterization of CTCs in peripheral blood, providing an opportunity to noninvasively monitor the disease progression in individual PC patients. Ultimately, we will broaden the future clinical applications to other types of cancer, and channel TR-NanoVelcro CTC purification system into translational and regulatory pipelines.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091249" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6655245">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091249&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>Collectively, the PIs have brought together an interdisciplinary research team with extensive expertise covering nanomaterials, polymer, microfluidics, <em>in vitro</em> diagnostics, urologic oncology, genomic medicine, cancer biology, next-generation sequencing, bioinformatics, and biostatistics to implement the proposed research activities.</p>
</section>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051580" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Andre Nel, M.D., Ph.D., Timothy Donahue, M.D., Huan Meng, Ph.D., and Jeffrey Zink, Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> Caius Radu, M.D., Erkki Ruoslahti, M.D., Ph.D. (Sanford-Burnham Medical Research Institute), and Zev Wainberg, M.D.</p>
<section id="1">
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>Nanocarriers that circumvent the stromal barrier in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) to allow:</p>
<ul>
<li>ratiometric control of a synergistic gemcitabine (GEM)/paclitaxel (PTX) combination,</li>
<li>overcome rate limiting steps in GEM metabolism, and</li>
<li>reduce FOLFIRINOX toxicity (a potent 4-drug regimen that includes irinotecan) could significantly impact PDAC survival.</li>
</ul>
<p>The goal of our multidisciplinary approach is to use rationally designed mesoporous silica nanoparticles (MSNP) to provide efficacious, safe and life-prolonging chemotherapy to PDAC patients. Our objectives are to develop and implement MSNP nanocarriers of which:</p>
<ul>
<li>achieve stable and high dose GEM and irinotecan loading, using a supported lipid bilayer (LB);</li>
<li>provide synergistic PTX/GEM co-delivery, with efficacy testing in human-derived PDAC tumors and a KPC-derived model;</li>
<li>provide high dose encapsulated irinotecan delivery to reduce toxicity;</li>
<li>achieve carrier targeting or transcytosis by iRGD peptide, which may also prevent metastasis;</li>
<li>deliver a small molecule TGF-&beta; inhibitor (TGF-&beta;i) that provides vascular access by interference in pericyte coverage.</li>
</ul>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091324" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6654570">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091324&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Specifically, aim 1 will use LB-coated MSNP to optimize GEM delivery and efficacy in human derived PDAC tumors and a KPC-derived model. Aim 2 will demonstrate how the biocompatibility of LB-MSNP can be used to improve the toxicity profile and efficacy of irinotecan delivery in PDAC. Aim 3 will demonstrate that targeted delivery of iRGD-MSNP, promotion of nanocarrier transcytosis by iRGD co-delivery, or improvement of vascular access by TGF-&beta;i can enhance the chemotherapeutic efficacy of MSNP nanocarriers. We expect the co-delivery of GEM / PTX and irinotecan by multifunctional MSNPs will improve survival and reduce toxicity in robust animal models. Positive impact will include the efficacious and safe nanocarriers that can be placed into the pipeline of novel diagnostics and therapeutics being tested in human PDAC. This research will also increase fundamental understanding of the PDAC microenvironment and PDAC-specific stromal barrier.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>The team include expertise in nanomedicine/nanosafety (Nel), pharmaceutical science/chemistry (Meng), nanomaterial chemistry (Zink), and surgery (Donahue). The team also includes expertise in cancer pharmacology/PET imaging (Radu), oncology (Wainberg) and cancer/vascular biology (Ruoslahti).</p>
</section>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051581" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Alexander V. Kabanov, Ph.D., D.Sc., Tatiana Bronich, Ph.D. (University of Nebraska Medical Center), and Rihe Liu, Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> Sergei Sheiko, Ph.D., Andrew Wang, M.D., and William Zamboni, Ph.D.</p>
<section id="1">
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>The goal of this project is to improve systemic therapies of cancer using soft nanomaterials that can penetrate deep into tumors and deliver potent anticancer agents to targeted cancer cells. We have developed a novel platform for drug delivery that uses aqueous polymeric gel nanoparticles termed core-shell nanogels (CSNGs). CSNGs are manufactured through a proprietary self-assembly process and can be readily filled with various drug payloads. They are water-swollen and are practically non-adhesive, which may diminish their off-target side effects. We hypothesize that</p>
<ul>
<li>the systemic and tumor flow dynamics of CSNGs will be a function of their molecular architecture and mechanical properties and</li>
<li>that these properties can be rationally controlled to modify the PK, distribution and tumor penetration of the CSNGs and the drugs they deliver.</li>
</ul>
<p>We will focus our research efforts on using CSNGs for triple negative breast cancer (TNBC), a disease that, despite treatment advances, still has a very poor outcome. As disease-targeting strategies, we will use the novel single-domain polypeptide antagonists of the EGFR and HER3 that are frequently overexpressed in TNBC and are associated with a higher risk of mortality in TNBC.</p>
<p>The specific aims of our work involve:</p>
<ul>
<li>Determine how the molecular architecture and mechanical properties of polypeptide-based CSNGs affects their ability to load, deliver and release therapeutic cargos;</li>
<li>Determine how the structure and mechanical properties of the drug-loaded CSNGs affect the <em>in vivo</em> PK and tumor distribution of the drugs and nanogels in murine models of TNBC;</li>
<li>Develop EGFR and HER3 targeted drug-loaded CSNGs with maximal tumor penetration, maximal delivery of drug payload to tumors and potent anti-tumor activity in TNBC.</li>
</ul>
<p>These integrative efforts will address major barriers in developing nanotechnology platforms for the treatment of TNBC, and facilitate understanding of the cancer biology and the mechanisms of <em>in vivo</em> delivery.</p>
</section>
<section id="2">
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>We assembled a cross-disciplinary team of physician-scientists and experts in nanotechnology and pharmacology. Specifically, we encompass expertise in polymer-based drug delivery (Kabanov and Bronich), cancer targeting peptides (Liu), soft materials mechanics (Sheiko), oncology (Wang), and pharmacology (Zamboni).</p>
</section>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1051622" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The&nbsp;Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch (NSDB) of the <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=945&amp;sys_contentid=16678" sys_dependentvariantid="945" sys_dependentid="16678" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="6897132">Cancer Imaging Program (CIP)</a> is within the&nbsp;<a href="https://dctd.cancer.gov/">Division of Cancer Treatment and Diagnosis (DCTD)</a>&nbsp;at the <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=72&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=15309" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6897129" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="15309" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">National Cancer Institute (NCI)</a>. NSDB develops and implements programs with and for the extramural research community related to the use of nanotechnology in medicine and cancer.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The NSDB leadership is <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1051457" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6897130" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051457" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">staffed</a> by a team of individuals whose collective backgrounds and expertise cover the broad multidisciplinary nature of cancer nanotechnology.&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Mission</h2>
<p>The mission of the Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch is to strategically develop, fund, and administer initiatives aimed at solving modern oncology problems with nanotechnology solutions.</p>
<p>The overarching goal of these initiatives is to discover and develop innovative nanotechnologies for application(s), ranging from discovery through to clinical translation phases, for the delivery of innovative clinically relevant technologies aimed at cancer prevention, diagnosis, control, and treatment.</p>
<p>These initiatives include a programmatic effort known, collectively, as the <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051623" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6897128" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051623" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer</a>, which aligns to several key areas of the National Cancer Institute&rsquo;s existing priority areas.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1063327" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Find specific research opportunities relevant to nanotechnology and cancer here. Training and fellowship funding opportunities are listed in the <span><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1063349" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6921888" sys_dependentvariantid="1764" sys_dependentid="1063349" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305">Training Grants</a></span>. Also visit the <a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/index.html"><span>NIH Guide for Grants and Contracts</span></a><span>&nbsp;</span>for the latest publication of all NIH funding opportunities and notices.</p>
<p>Please visit <a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/how-to-apply-application-guide/due-dates-and-submission-policies/due-dates.htm">NIH Grants and Funding Due Dates</a> if the Application Receipt Date is not listed below.</p>
<table class="table-default" style="width: 1154.93px;">
<tbody>
<tr style="height: 63px;">
<th style="height: 63px; width: 521px;">Project Name</th>
<th style="height: 63px; width: 155px;"><strong>Program Announcement Number</strong></th>
<th style="height: 63px; width: 453.933px;"><strong>Application Receipt Date(s)</strong></th>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 43px;">
<td style="height: 43px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-CA-18-002.html">Innovative Molecular and Cellular Analysis Technologies for Basic and Clinical Cancer Research (R21)</a></td>
<td style="height: 43px; width: 155px;">RFA-CA-18-002</td>
<td style="height: 43px; width: 453.933px;">September 28, 2018, by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 43px;">
<td style="height: 43px; width: 521px;"><br /><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-CA-18-003.html">Advanced Development and Validation of Emerging Molecular and Cellular Analysis Technologies for Basic and Clinical Cancer Research (R33)</a></td>
<td style="height: 43px; width: 155px;">RFA-CA-18-003</td>
<td style="height: 43px; width: 453.933px;">September 28, 2018, by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 15px;">
<td style="height: 15px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-CA-18-004.html">Innovative Technologies for Cancer-Relevant Biospecimen Science (R21)</a></td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 155px;">RFA-CA-18-004</td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 453.933px;">September 28, 2018, by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 30px;">
<td style="height: 30px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-CA-18-005.html">Advanced Development and Validation of Emerging Biospecimen Science Technologies for Basic and Clinical Cancer Research (R33)</a></td>
<td style="height: 30px; width: 155px;">RFA-CA-18-005</td>
<td style="height: 30px; width: 453.933px;">September 28, 2018, by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 15px;">
<td style="height: 15px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-17-240.html">Innovative Research in Cancer Nanotechnology (IRCN) (R01)</a></td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 155px;">PAR-17-240</td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 453.933px;">May 23, 2018; <br />November 20, 2018; <br />May 23, 2019, <br />November 21, 2019, <br />May 21, 2020, <br />by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 30px;">
<td style="height: 30px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-17-167.html">Early Phase Clinical Trials in Imaging and Image-Guided Interventions (R01)</a></td>
<td style="height: 30px; width: 155px;">PAR-17-167</td>
<td style="height: 30px; width: 453.933px;">June 28, 2018;<br /> October 11, 2018;<br /> February 14, 2019; <br />June 28, 2019;<br /> October 11, 2019;<br /> February 14, 2020,<br />by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 20px;">
<td style="height: 20px; width: 521px;"><br /><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-16-105.html">Cancer Tissue Engineering Collaborative: Enabling Biomimetic Tissue-Engineered Technologies for Cancer Research (U01)</a></td>
<td style="height: 20px; width: 155px;">PAR-16-105</td>
<td style="height: 20px; width: 453.933px;">May 30, 2018; <br />November 30, 2018, <br />by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 15px;">
<td style="height: 15px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-16-089.html">Imaging and Biomarkers for Early Detection of Aggressive Cancer (U01)</a></td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 155px;">PAR-16-089</td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 453.933px;">July 10, 2018; <br />December 11, 2018, <br />by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 15px;">
<td style="height: 15px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-16-044.html">Image-guided Drug Delivery in Cancer (R01)</a></td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 155px;">PAR-16-044</td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 453.933px;">June 21, 2018; <br />November 22, 2018, <br />by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 15px;">
<td style="height: 15px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-15-289.html">The Pancreatic Cancer Detection Consortium (U01)</a></td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 155px;">PAR-15-289</td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 453.933px;">April 6, 2018, <br />by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 14px;">
<td style="height: 14px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-15-287.html">Opportunities for Collaborative Research at the NIH Clinical Center (U01)</a></td>
<td style="height: 14px; width: 155px;">PAR-15-287</td>
<td style="height: 14px; width: 453.933px;">April 11, 2018, by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 15px;">
<td style="height: 15px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-16-416.html">NCI Small Grants Program for Cancer Research (NCI Omnibus R03)</a></td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 155px;">PAR-16-416</td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 453.933px;">June 29, 2018; <br />October 26, 2018; <br />February 26, 2019; <br />June 28, 2019; <br />October 25, 2019&nbsp; <br />May 7, 2018; <br />September 7, 2018; <br />January 7, 2019; <br />May 7, 2019; <br />September 7, 2019; <br />January 7, 2020</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 15px;">
<td style="height: 15px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=501024&amp;org=CBET&amp;from=home">Biotechnology, Biochemical, and Biomass Engineering</a></td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 155px;">PD 11-1491</td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 453.933px;">October 1-20, Annually</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 15px;">
<td style="height: 15px; width: 521px;"><a href="http://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=501023&amp;org=CBET&amp;from=home">Biomedical Engineering</a></td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 155px;">PD 11-5345</td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 453.933px;">October 1-20, Annually</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 15px;">
<td style="height: 15px; width: 521px;"><a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-18-591.html">Administrative Supplements to Existing NIH Grants and Cooperative Agreements (Parent Admin Supp Clinical Trial Optional)</a></td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 155px;">PA 18-591</td>
<td style="height: 15px; width: 453.933px;"></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1063349" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>Training and Educational (F30, F32, K01, K23, K24, K99/R00, R25, T32)</h2>
<table class="table-default">
<tbody>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<th style="height: 13px;">Project Name</th>
<th style="height: 13px;">Program Announcement/RFA Number</th>
<th style="height: 13px;">Application Receipt Date(s)</th>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;"><a href="https://ncifrederick.cancer.gov/SummerProgram/">NCI-sponsored Systems Biology and Physical Oncology Undergraduate Summer Research Opportunity</a></td>
<td style="height: 35px;">N/A</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>February 16, 2018</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 35px;">
<td style="height: 35px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-HG-14-004.html">Predoctoral Training in Biomedical Big Data Science (T32)</a></td>
<td style="height: 35px;">RFA-HG-14-004</td>
<td style="height: 35px;">
<p>July 27, 2015</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 26px;">
<td style="height: 26px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-HG-14-005.html">Revisions to Add Biomedical Big Data Training to Active Institutional Training Grants (T32)</a></td>
<td style="height: 26px;">RFA-CA-15-005</td>
<td style="height: 26px;">June 17, 2015; September 22, 2015, by 5:00 PM local time of applicant organization.</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-HG-14-007.html">Mentored Career Development Award in Biomedical Big Data Science for Clinicians and Doctorally Prepared Scientists (K01)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">RFA-HG-14-007</td>
<td style="height: 13px;">April 1, 2015</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 43px;">
<td style="height: 43px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-HG-14-008.html">Courses for Skills Development in Biomedical Big Data Science (R25)</a></td>
<td style="height: 43px;">RFA-HG-14-008</td>
<td style="height: 43px;">April 1, 2015; and April 1, 2016</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-HG-14-009.html">Open Educational Resources for Biomedical Big Data (R25)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">RFA-HG-14-009</td>
<td style="height: 13px;">April 1, 2015; and April 1, 2016</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-14-121.html">Initiative for Maximizing Student Development (IMSD) (R25)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PAR-14-121</td>
<td style="height: 13px;">January 25, 2016</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 26px;">
<td style="height: 26px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-046.html">Mentored Clinical Scientist Research Career Development Award (Parent K08)</a></td>
<td style="height: 26px;">PA-14-046</td>
<td style="height: 26px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View Mentored Clinical Scientist Research Career Development Award (Parent K08)schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-047.html">Midcareer Investigator Award in Patient-Oriented Research (Parent K24)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-14-047</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View Midcareer Investigator Award in Patient-Oriented Research (Parent K24)&nbsp;schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-049.html">Mentored Patient-Oriented Research Career Development Award (Parent K23)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-14-049</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View Mentored Patient-Oriented Research Career Development Award (Parent K23)&nbsp;schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-11-197.html">NIH Pathway to Independence Award (K99/R00)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-11-197</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-10-063.html">View NIH Pathway to Independence Award (K99/R00)&nbsp;schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants2.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-10-062.html">Mentored Quantitative Research Development Award (K25)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-10-062</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-10-063.html">View Mentored Quantitative Research Development Award (K25) schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-042.html">NIH Pathway to Independence Award (Parent K99/R00)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-14-042</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View NIH Pathway to Independence Award (Parent K99/R00) schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-048.html">Mentored Quantitative Research Development Award (Parent K25)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-14-048</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View Mentored Quantitative Research Development Award (Parent K25) schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13.54px;">
<td style="height: 13.54px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-14-076.html">Postbaccalaureate Research Education Program (PREP) (R25)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13.54px;">PAR-14-076</td>
<td style="height: 13.54px;">January 25, 2016</td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-147.html">Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Award (NRSA) Individual Predoctoral Fellowship (Parent F31)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-14-147</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Award (NRSA) Individual Predoctoral Fellowship (Parent F31) schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-148.html">Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Award (NRSA) Individual Predoctoral Fellowship to Promote Diversity in Health&ndash;Related Research (Parent F31 &ndash; Diversity)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-14-148</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Award (NRSA) Individual Predoctoral Fellowship to Promote Diversity in Health&ndash;Related Research (Parent F31 &ndash; Diversity) schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-149.html">Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Award (NRSA) Individual Postdoctoral Fellowship (Parent F32)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-14-149</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Award (NRSA) Individual Postdoctoral Fellowship (Parent F32) schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-150.html">Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Award (NRSA) Individual Predoctoral MD/PhD or Other Dual&ndash;Doctoral Degree Fellowship (Parent F30)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-14-150</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Award (NRSA) Individual Predoctoral MD/PhD or Other Dual&ndash;Doctoral Degree Fellowship (Parent F30) schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-14-151.html">Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Awards (NRSA) for Individual Senior Fellowship (Parent F33)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PA-14-151</td>
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/funding/submissionschedule.htm">View Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Awards (NRSA) for Individual Senior Fellowship (Parent F33) schedule</a></td>
</tr>
<tr style="height: 13px;">
<td style="height: 13px;"><a href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-14-170.html">Innovative Programs to Enhance Research Training (IPERT) (R25)</a></td>
<td style="height: 13px;">PAR-14-170</td>
<td style="height: 13px;">January 25, 2016</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1064640" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong><span>Carolina Cancer Nanotechnology Training program assembles large video library for learning about Cancer Nanotechnology<br /></span></strong>January 15, 2019<br /><strong><span></span></strong></p>
<p>The<span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://pharmacy.unc.edu/academics/fellowships/carolina-cancer-nanotechnology-t32-training-program/" class="external-link" rel="nofollow" title="Follow link">Carolina Cancer Nanotechnology Training Program</a><span>&nbsp;</span>(CCNTP) T32 program at UNC &ndash; Chapel Hill has prepared a video library of 90+ recorded lectures and seminars from the<span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://pharmacy.unc.edu/research/centers/cndd/nanoformulation-workshop/" class="external-link" rel="nofollow" title="Follow link">Carolina Nanoformulation Workshop</a><span>&nbsp;</span>and seminar speakers who have visited UNC &ndash; Chapel Hill. The library includes videos addressing the topics of: Cancer Biology, Types of Nanoformulations, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics, Computer &amp; Animal Models for Evaluating Efficacy of Nanoformulations, Regulatory Considerations for Nanoformulations, Clinical &amp; Translational Aspects, Informatics &amp; Statistics, and Recorded Lab Demonstrations. The videos are relevant to researchers working in nanomedicine, pharmacoengineering, basic cancer research, and clinical translational sciences.</p>
<p>We would like to share this video library with T32 and cancer nanotechnology-focused colleagues. Visit the site at <a href="http://cancernano.web.unc.edu/">cancernano.web.unc.edu</a>. Email<span>&nbsp;</span><span class="nobr"><a href="mailto:cancernano@unc.edu" class="external-link" rel="nofollow" title="Follow link">cancernano@unc.edu<sup><img class="rendericon" src="https://tracker.nci.nih.gov/images/icons/mail_small.gif" height="12" width="13" align="absmiddle" alt="" border="0" /></sup></a></span><span>&nbsp;</span>to request the site password.</p>
<p><strong>Alliance researchers build army of metal-organic nanoflowers to treat cancer</strong><br />March 29, 2018<br />Wenbin Lin, PI for the <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1051571" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051571" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7311761" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1051571">University of Chicago IRCN</a>, has recently entered his nanotechnology platform based off metal-organic frameworks, into Phase I clinical trials. His recent publication in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41551-018-0203-4">Nature Biomedical Engineering</a> led to the primary candidate now undergoing human testing.</p>
<p><strong>NCI</strong><strong>-sponsored Systems Biology and Physical Oncology Undergraduate Summer Research Opportunity</strong><br />December&nbsp;12, 2017<br />The National Cancer Institute&rsquo;s (NCI) Cancer Systems Biology Consortium and Physical Sciences in Oncology Network are offering rising Junior and Senior undergraduates with outstanding research potential the opportunity to work closely with faculty mentors from NCI-supported institutions for an 8-week summer fellowship. The 2017 summer research program is designed specifically for students to gain experience in the interdisciplinary fields of systems biology and physical oncology. Students who are especially interested in cancer research careers are encouraged to apply. Opportunities are available at 14 research institutions across the United States. Stipend, housing, and travel to and from the host institution are covered by NCI. Additionally, students will convene at the NIH in Bethesda, MD, mid-way through the summer to present their research and network with their peers.</p>
<p>Detailed information about the program and application instructions can be found at: <a href="https://ncifrederick.cancer.gov/SummerProgram/">https://ncifrederick.cancer.gov/SummerProgram/</a>. The application deadline is February 16, 2018.</p>
<p><strong>Wayne's TED Talk Has More Than 300K Views in First Week<br /></strong> October 17, 2017<br /> Congratulations to the UNC CNTC post-doctoral fellow, Dr. Elizabeth Wayne, who delivered a TED talk in April 2017 titled "<i><a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/elizabeth_wayne_we_can_hack_our_immune_cells_to_fight_cancer">We can hack our immune cells to fight cancer</a>.</i>" After posting on the TED main website October 17, 2017 it has already been viewed more than 340,000 times.</p>
<p><strong>2017 International Institute for Nantechnology Symposium</strong><br /> August 1, 2017<br /> Join world experts for nanotechnology in medicine at this year&rsquo;s 2017 IIN Symposium.&nbsp; Held in Evanston, IL September 28, 2017 --- 8:30 am to 5:30 pm.&nbsp; Registration is free although registration is required beforehand and will fill up fast.&nbsp; See the <a href="http://www.iinano.org/2017-iin-symposium-1">IIN website for details and registration</a>.</p>
<p><strong>First Spherical Nucleic Acid Drug Injected into Humans Targets Brain Cancer<br /></strong>May 12, 2017<strong><br /></strong>Chad Mirkin, PI, of the <a href="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1051519" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051519" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_relationshipid="7311762" sys_variantid="2297" sys_contentid="1051519">Northwestern University CCNE</a> has entered his spherical nucleic acid nano platform into <a href="http://news.feinberg.northwestern.edu/2017/05/first-spherical-nucleic-acid-drug-injected-into-humans-targets-brain-cancer/">Phase 0 clinical trials</a>. The patient population targeted for this trial is patients with the highly aggressive form of brain cancer, glioblastoma multiforme. The platform has shown much success in crossing the highly selective blood-brain barrier and represents a novel solution to a very important problem in treating CNS disease and disorders.</p>
<p><strong>NCI Launches Next Phase of Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer Program</strong><br /> September 4, 2015<br /> The National Cancer Institute (NCI) has again awarded several five-year, multi-institution grants in continued support of its Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer program. Given the progress to date of the Alliance, the NCI approved a third phase of the program with a sizable investment in funding. The Alliance program is dedicated to using nanotechnology solutions towards solving cancer biology and oncology problems as well as developing new cancer interventions based on nanotechnology. The program was established in 2004 and funds efforts at academic centers which are engaged in research and translation of new technologies to the clinical environment.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1064730" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer has published numerous articles on the development and characterization of nanotechnology-based imaging agents, detection devices, diagnostics, and therapeutics applicable to cancer. Members of the program have published over 4,000 articles to date in high impact journals such as Science Translational Medicine, Nature Nanotechnology, and Nature Medicine. To learn more about Alliance publications, please see the complete list below.&nbsp; The links below will bring you to these publications on PubMed relative to the search parameter displayed.</p>
<ul>
<li>Complete listing of all publications from <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?term=%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28%28CA199091%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA199090%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA199092%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA198989%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA199075%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA199081%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA198913%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA198900%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA198892%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153952%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA196589%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA196585%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA196561%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA186897%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA207946%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA198999%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA198880%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA198846%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA206997%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA201777%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA213759%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151819%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151662%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151838%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151884%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151881%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151880%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151459%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151652%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151668%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151806%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151815%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151650%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151837%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151455%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151810%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151648%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151452%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151802%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151461%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151792%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA151886%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA154015%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153955%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153825%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153915%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153952%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153954%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153935%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153929%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153772%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153916%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153914%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA153948%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA154006%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119343%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119335%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119338%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119367%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119342%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119341%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119347%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119349%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119617%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119414%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119412%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119409%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119408%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119402%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119397%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119399%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119388%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119387%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA213862%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA218292%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA198910%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA232015%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA232017%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA236702%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA218422%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA218545%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA232056%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119378%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119371%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20OR%20CA119358%5BGrant%20Number%5D%29%20AND%20%28%222003%2F01%2F01%22%5BPDat%5D%20%3A%20%223000%2F12%2F31%22%5BPDat%5D%29">NCI Alliance Funded Research from the Beginning of the Program</a> (2004)</li>
<li>Complete listing of all publications in <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=((%22nanotechnology%22%5BMeSH+Terms%5D)+OR+(%22nanotechnology%22%5BAll+Fields%5D)+OR+(%22nanoparticle%22%5BAll+Fields%5D))+AND+((%22neoplasms%22%5BMeSH+Terms%5D+OR+%22neoplasms%22%5BAll+Fields%5D+OR+%22cancer%22%5BAll+Fields%5D)) ">Cancer Nanotechnology Research Published across Entire Field</a></li>
<li>Complete listing of all publications in <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Db=pubmed&amp;Cmd=DetailsSearch&amp;Term=((%22nanotechnology%22%5BMeSH+Terms%5D)+OR+(%22nanotechnology%22%5BAll+Fields%5D)+OR+(%22nanoparticle%22%5BAll+Fields%5D))+AND+((%22diagnosis%22[Subheading]+OR+%22diagnosis%22[All+Fields]+OR+%22diagnosis%22[MeSH+Terms]))+AND+((%22neoplasms%22[MeSH+Terms]+OR+%22neoplasms%22[All+Fields]+OR+%22cancer%22[All+Fields])) ">Cancer Nanotechnology Research Published across Entire Field -- for Diagnosis</a></li>
<li>Complete listing of all publications in <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Db=pubmed&amp;Cmd=DetailsSearch&amp;Term=((%22nanotechnology%22%5BMeSH+Terms%5D)+OR+(%22nanotechnology%22%5BAll+Fields%5D)+OR+(%22nanoparticle%22%5BAll+Fields%5D))+AND+((%22therapy%22[Subheading]+OR+%22therapy%22[All+Fields]+OR+%22therapeutics%22[MeSH+Terms]+OR+%22therapeutics%22[All+Fields]))+AND+((%22neoplasms%22[MeSH+Terms]+OR+%22neoplasms%22[All+Fields]+OR+%22cancer%22[All+Fields])) ">Cancer Nanotechnology Research Published across Entire Field -- for Therapy</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1064733" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>Apply for Innovative Research in Cancer Nanotechnology R01</h2>
<p>The NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer is accepting applications for the Innovative Research in Cancer Nanotechnology (IRCN) (R01) initiative. The first receipt date for the current Funding Opportunity Announcement (FOA) for this initiative, PAR-17-240 (<a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-17-240.html">https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PAR-17-240.html</a>), is November 21, 2017. The FOA will include five more receipt dates through May 21, 2020.&nbsp; Please see key dates in the FOA listed.</p>
<p>This FOA will solicit applications for the development of innovative research projects addressing major barriers in cancer biology and/or oncology using nanotechnology and emphasizing fundamental understanding of nanomaterial interactions with biological systems, mechanisms of nanoparticle delivery in vivo, and characterization of diagnostic devices in vitro.</p>
<p>Among the areas of research encouraged in this initiative are: studies towards fundamental understanding of nanomaterial and / or nanodevice interactions with biological systems, mechanisms of delivery of nanoparticles and / or nanodevices to desired and intended cancer targets in vivo, and characterization of detection and diagnostic devices in vitro.</p>
<p>Cancer nanotechnology expertise and/or collaborative investigations combining expertise in cancer biology, oncology, chemistry, physics, and materials science will be encouraged and these investigators should consider applying for this new FOA. Awardees will be part of the Alliance network, which also include the <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051493" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6888892" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051493" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Centers of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence</a>, <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1077637" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6888893" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1077637" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Cancer Nanotechnology Research Training Programs</a>, and the <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1077670" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6888894" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1077670" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Nanotechnology Characterization Laboratory</a>. For more information about IRCNs, and the IRCN application and review, please see the <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051494" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6888895" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051494" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">PDF guidance for the IRCN initiative</a>.</p>
<h2>Apply for Cancer Nanotechnology Training Center T32 Grant</h2>
<p>The Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch no longer supports cancer nanotechnology training center through the R25T mechanism.&nbsp; Instead, prospective Cancer Nanotechnology Training Center applicants should seek their funding support under the T32 mechanism.&nbsp; The <strong>Ruth L. Kirschstein National Research Service Award (NRSA) (T32)</strong> supports grants to institutions to develop or enhance research training opportunities for pre and postdoctoral fellow to be trained in cancer research, including nanotechnology-focused activities.&nbsp; Applicants should submit their proposals in response to the <a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-16-152.html">Parent T32 program announcement</a>. All NCI T32 applications are evaluated by Subcommittee F convened by the Division of Extramural Activities of the NCI.&nbsp; See information about <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=124&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=65958" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6888896" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="65958" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">NCI&rsquo;s T32 program</a>. &nbsp; For general information regarding policies and guidance in preparing an application for the T32 award, contact <a href="mailto:lims@mail.nih.gov">Dr. Susan Lim</a>.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1073910" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Nanotechnology is a powerful tool for combating cancer and is being put to use in other applications that may reduce pollution, energy consumption, greenhouse gas emissions, and help prevent diseases. NCI&rsquo;s <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051623" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051623" sys_dependentvariantid="2317" sys_relationshipid="6654334">Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer</a> is working to ensure that nanotechnologies for cancer applications are developed responsibly.</p>
<p>There is nothing inherently dangerous about being nanosized. Our ability to manipulate objects at the nanoscale has developed relatively recently, but nanoparticles are as old as the earth. Many nanoparticles occur naturally (for example, in volcanic ash and sea spray) and as by-products of human activities since the Stone Age (nanoparticles are in smoke and soot from fire). There are so many ambient incidental nanoparticles, in fact, that one of the challenges of nanoparticle exposure studies is that background incidental nanoparticles are often at order-of-magnitude higher levels than the engineered particles being evaluated.</p>
<p>As with any new technology, the safety of nanotechnology is continuously being tested. The small size, high reactivity, and unique tensile and magnetic properties of nanomaterials&mdash;the same properties that drive interest in their biomedical and industrial applications&mdash;have raised concerns about implications for the environment, health, and safety (EHS). There has been some as yet unresolved debate recently about the potential toxicity of a specific type of nanomaterial&mdash;carbon nanotubes (CNTs)&mdash;which has been associated with tissue damage in animal studies. However, the majority of available data indicate that there is nothing uniquely toxic about nanoparticles as a class of materials.</p>
<p>In fact, most engineered nanoparticles are far less toxic than household cleaning products, insecticides used on family pets, and over-the-counter dandruff remedies. Certainly, the nanoparticles used as drug carriers for chemotherapeutics are much less toxic than the drugs they carry and are designed to carry drugs safely to tumors without harming organs and healthy tissue.</p>
<p>To insure that potential risks of nanotechnology are thoroughly evaluated, the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer makes the services of its <a href="https://ncl.cancer.gov/">Nanotechnology Characterization Laboratory (NCL)</a> available to the nanotech and cancer research communities. The NCL, an intramural program of the Alliance, performs nanomaterial safety and toxicity testing <em>in vitro</em> (in the laboratory) and using animal models. The NCL tests are designed to characterize nanomaterials that enter the bloodstream, regardless of route. This testing is just one part of the NCL's cascade of tests to evaluate the physicochemical properties, biocompatibility, and efficacy of nanomaterials intended for cancer therapy and diagnosis. To date, the NCL has evaluated more than 125 different nanoparticles intended for medical applications.</p>
<p>The NCL works closely with the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and National Institutes of Standards and Technology (NIST) to devise experiments that are relevant to nanomaterials, to validate these tests on a variety of nanomaterial types, and to disseminate its methods to the nanotech and cancer research communities. The NCL also facilitates the development of voluntary-consensus standards for reliably and pro-actively measuring and monitoring environment, health and safety ramifications of nanotech applications.</p>
<p>Whether actual or perceived, the potential health risks associated with the manufacture and use of nanomaterials must be carefully studied in order to advance our understanding of this field of science and to realize the significant benefits that nanotechnology has to offer society, such as for cancer research, diagnostics, and therapy.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1074439" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Nanoscale devices are one hundred to ten thousand times smaller than human cells. They are similar in size to large biological molecules ("biomolecules") such as enzymes and receptors. As an example, hemoglobin, the molecule that carries oxygen in red blood cells, is approximately 5 nanometers in diameter. Nanoscale devices smaller than 50 nanometers can easily enter most cells, while those smaller than 20 nanometers can move out of blood vessels as they circulate through the body. Because of their small size, nanoscale devices can readily interact with biomolecules on both the surface and inside cells. By gaining access to so many areas of the body, they have the potential to detect disease and deliver treatment in ways unimagined before now.</p>
<p>Biological processes, including ones necessary for life and those that lead to cancer, occur at the nanoscale. Thus, in fact, we are composed of a multitude of biological nano-machines. Nanotechnology provides researchers with the opportunity to study and manipulate macromolecules in real time and during the earliest stages of cancer progression. Nanotechnology can provide rapid and sensitive detection of cancer-related molecules, enabling scientists to detect molecular changes even when they occur only in a small percentage of cells. Nanotechnology also has the potential to generate entirely novel and highly effective therapeutic agents.</p>
<p>Ultimately and uniquely, the use of nanoscale materials for cancer, comes down to its ability to be readily functionalized and easily tuned; its ability to deliver and / or act as the therapeutic, diagnostic, or both; and its ability to passively accumulate at the tumor site, to be actively targeted to cancer cells, and to be delivered across traditional biological barriers in the body such as dense stromal tissue of the pancreas or the blood-brain barrier that highly regulates delivery of biomolecules to / from, our central nervous system.</p>
<h2>Passive Tumor Accumulation</h2>
<p>An effective cancer drug delivery should achieve high accumulation in tumor and spare the surrounding healthy tissues. The passive localization of many drugs and drug carriers due to their extravasation through leaky vasculature (named the Enhanced Permeability and Retention [EPR] effect) works very well for tumors. As tumor mass grows rapidly, a network of blood vessels needs to expand quickly to accommodate tumor cells&rsquo; need for oxygen and nutrient. This abnormal and poorly regulated vessel generation (i.e. angiogenesis) results in vessel walls with large pores (40 nm to 1 um); these leaky vessels allow relatively large nanoparticles to extravasate into tumor masses. As fast growing tumor mass lacks a functioning lymphatic system, clearance of these nanoparticles is limited and further enhances the accumulation. Through the EPR effect, nanoparticles larger than 8 nm (between 8-100 nm) can passively target tumors by freely pass through large pores and achieve higher intratumoral accumulation. The majority of current nanomedicines for solid tumor treatment rely on EPR effect to ensure high drug accumulation thereby improve treatment efficacy. Without targeting cell types expressing targeting ligand of interest, this drug delivery system is called passive targeting.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2066" sys_dependentid="1088966" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6894095">
<figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088966&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>This image shows micelle-based nanoparticles (red) that have moved beyond the blood vessels (green) of a tumor in a mouse model of ovarian cancer. The nanoparticles diffused throughout the entire tumor within 48 hours of injection, suggesting excellent tumor-penetration capability.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Before reaching to the proximity of tumor site for EPR effect to take place, passive targeting requires drug delivery system to be long-circulating to allow sufficient level of drug to the target area. To design nano-drugs that can stay in blood longer, one can &ldquo;mask&rdquo; these nano-drugs by modifying the surface with water-soluble polymers such as polyethylene glycol (PEG); PEG is often used to make water-insoluble nanoparticles to be water-soluble in many pre-clinical research laboratories. PEG-coated liposomal doxorubicin (Doxil) is used clinically for breast cancer leveraging passive tumor accumulation. As in vivo surveillance system for macromolecules (i.e., scavenger receptors of the reticuloendothelial system, RES) reportedly showed faster uptake of negatively charged nanoparticles, nano-drugs with a neutral or positive charge are expected to have a longer plasma half-life.</p>
<p>Utilizing EPR effect for passive tumor targeting drug delivery is not without problems. Although EPR effect is a unique phenomenon in solid tumors, the central region of metastatic or larger tumor mass does not exhibit EPR effect, a result of an extreme hypoxic condition. For this reason, there are methods used in the clinics to artificially enhance EPR effect: slow infusion of angiotensin II to increase systolic blood pressure, topical application of NO-releasing agents to expand blood and photodynamic therapy or hyperthermia-mediated vascular permeabilization in solid tumors.</p>
<p>Passive accumulation through EPR effect is the most acceptable drug delivery system for solid tumor treatment. However, size or molecular weight of the nanoparticles is not the sole determinant of the EPR effect, other factors such as surface charge, biocompatibility and in vivo surveillance system for macromolecules should not be ignored in designing the nanomedicine for efficient passive tumor accumulation.</p>
<h2>Active Tumor Targeting</h2>
<p>EPR effect, which serves as nanoparticle &lsquo;passive tumor targeting&rsquo; scheme is responsible for accumulation of particles in the tumor region. However, EPR does not promote uptake of nanoparticles into cells; yet nanoparticle/drug cell internalization is required for some of the treatment modalities relying on drug activation within the cell nucleus or cytosol (1). Similarly, delivery of nucleic acids (DNA, siRNA, miRNA) in genetic therapies requires escape of these molecules from endosome so they can reach desired subcellular compartments. In addition, EPR is heterogenous and its strength vary among different tumors and/or patients. For these reasons, active targeting is considered an essential feature for next generation nanoparticle therapeutics. It will enable certain modalities of therapies not achievable with EPR and improve effectiveness of treatments which can be accomplished using EPR, but with less than satisfactory effect. Active targeting of nanoparticles to tumor cells, microenvironment or vasculature, as well as directed delivery to intracellular compartments, can be attained through nanoparticle surface modification with small molecules, antibodies, affibodies, peptides or aptamers.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2066" sys_dependentid="1088969" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6894096">
<figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088969&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>This image shows blood vessels (light blue) infiltrating brain cancer (purple) in a live mouse. The high resolution achieved here enables single cancer cells to be visualized and allows direct observation and quantification of nanoparticle delivery and their targeting cancer cells.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Passive targeting (EPR effect) is is the process of nanoparticles extravasating from the circulation through the leaky vasculature to the tumor region. The drug molecules carried by nanoparticle are released in the extracellular matrix and diffuse throughout the tumor tissue. The particles carry surface ligands to facilitate active targeting of particles to receptors present on target cell or tissue. Active targeting is expected to enhance nanoparticle/drug accumulation in tumor and also promote their prospective cell uptake through receptor mediated endocytosis.&nbsp; The particles, which are engineered for vascular targeting, incorporate ligands that bind to endothelial cell-surface receptors. The vascular targeting is expected to provide synergistic strategy utilizing both targeting of vascular tissue and cells within the diseased tissue.</p>
<p>Most of the nanotechnology-based strategies which are approved for clinical use or are in advanced clinical trials rely on EPR effect. It is expected that next generation nanotherapies will use targeting to enable and enhance intracellular uptake, intracellular trafficking, and penetration of physiological barriers which block drug access to some tumors.</p>
<h2>Transport across Tissue Barriers</h2>
<p>Nanoparticle or nano-drug delivery is hampered by tissue barriers before the drug can reach the tumor site. Tissue barriers for efficient transporting of nano-drugs to tumor sites include tumor stroma (e.g. biological barriers) and tumor endothelium barriers (e.g. functional barriers). Biological barriers are physical constructs or cell formation that restrict the movement of nanoparticles. Functional barriers can affect the transport of intact nanoparticles or nanomedicine into the tumor mass: elevated interstitial fluid pressure and acidic environment for examples. It is important to design nanoparticles and strategies to overcome these barriers to improve cancer treatment efficacy.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2066" sys_dependentid="1088970" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6894097">
<figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088970&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>This image shows magnetic iron nanoparticles that target cells with IGF-1R receptors, and are conjugated to a chemotherapy drug (dark blue). In the tumor stroma of a mouse model of pancreatic cancer, the nanoparticles delivered the chemotherapy to tumor-associated macrophages expressing IGF-1R (red) and CD68 (green). These magnetic iron nanoparticles are theranostic &ndash; capable of both diagnostic and therapeutic functions.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Tumor microenvironment (TME) is a dynamic system composed of abnormal vasculature, fibroblasts and immune cells, all embedded in an extracellular matrix (ECM). TME poses both biological and functional barriers to nano-drug delivery in cancer treatment. Increase cell density and abnormal vasculature elevate the interstitial fluid pressure within a tumor mass. Such pressure gradient is unfavorable for free diffusion of the nanoparticles and is often a limiting factor for the enhanced permeability and retention (EPR) effect. When tumor mass reaches 106 cells in number, metabolic strains ensue. Often, cells in the core of this proliferating cluster are distanced by 100-200 um from the source of nutrient: 200um is a limiting distance for oxygen diffusion. As a result, cancer cells in the core live at pO2 levels below 2.5-10mmHg and become hypoxic; anoxic metabolic pathway can kick in and generate lactic acid. Nanoparticles become unstable in an acidic environment and delivery of the drugs to target tumor cells will be unpredictable. ECM of the tumor provides nutrient for cancer cells and stromal cell. It is a collection of fibrous proteins and polysaccharides and expands rapidly in aggressive cancer as the result of stromal cell proliferation. The most notorious biological barrier to cancer treatment is pancreatic stroma in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PADC). Pancreatic cancer stroma has the characteristics of an abnormal and poorly functioning vasculature, altered extracellular matrix, infiltrating macrophages and proliferation of fibroblasts. Not only tumor-stroma interactions have been shown to promote pancreatic cancer cell invasion and metastasis, but TME and tumor stroma also create an unfavorable environment for drug delivery and other forms of cancer treatments.</p>
<p>Because EPR effect is a clinically relevant phenomenon for nano-carriers&rsquo; tumor penetration, strategies have been developed to address the tumor endothelium barrier. Strategies to reduce interstitial fluid pressure to improve tumor penetration include ECM-targeting pharmacological interventions to normalize vasculature within TME; hypertonic solutions to shrink ECM cells; hyperthermia, radiofrequency (RF) or high-intensity focused ultrasound (HIFU) to enhance nano-drug transport and accumulation. These strategies can also alleviate hypoxic conditions in larger tumor mass. Although TME and tumor mass pose a harsh and acidic environment for nano-carrier stability, pH-responsive nano-carrier designs leveraging this unique feature are gaining interest in recent years. Many of the strategies described above are used to address tumor stroma barrier.</p>
<p>Another formidable tissue barrier for drugs and nanoparticle delivery is the blood-brain barrier (BBB). BBB is a physical barrier in the central nervous system to prevent harmful substances from entering the brain. It consists of endothelial cells which are sealed in continuous tight junction around the capillaries. Outside the layer of epithelial cell is covered by astrocytes that further contribute to the selectivity of substance passage. As BBB keeps harmful substances from the brain, it also restricts the delivery of therapeutics for brain diseases, such as brain tumors and other neurological diseases. There have been tremendous efforts in overcoming the BBB for drug delivery in general. The multi-valent feature of nanoparticles makes nano-carriers appealing in designing BBB-crossing delivering strategies. One promising nanoparticle design has transferrin receptor-targeting moiety to facilitate transportation of these nanoparticles across the BBB.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1074443" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>In the fight against cancer, half of the battle is won based on its early detection. Nanotechnology provides new molecular contrast agents and materials to enable earlier and more accurate initial diagnosis as well as in continual monitoring of cancer patient treatment.</p>
<p>Although not yet deployed clinically for cancer detection or diagnosis, nanoparticles are already on the market in numerous medical screens and tests, with the most widespread use that of gold nanoparticles in home pregnancy tests. Nanoparticles are also at the heart of the Verigene&reg; system from Nanosphere and the T2MR system from T2 Biosystems, currently used in hospitals for a variety of indications.</p>
<p>For cancer, nanodevices are being investigated for the capture of blood borne biomarkers, including cancer-associated proteins circulating tumor cells, circulating tumor DNA, and tumor-shed exosomes. Nano-enabled sensors are capable of high sensitivity, specificity and multiplexed measurements. Next generation devices couple capture with genetic analysis to further elucidate a patient&rsquo;s cancer and potential treatments and disease course.</p>
<p>Already clinically established as contrast agents for anatomical structure, nanoparticles are being developed to act as molecular imaging agents, reporting on the presence of cancer-relevant genetic mutations or the functional characteristics of tumor cells. This information can be used to choose a treatment course or alter a therapeutic plan. Bioactivatable nanoparticles that change properties in response to factors or processes within the body act as dynamic reporters of in vivo states and can provide both spatial and temporal information on disease progression and therapeutic response.</p>
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="in-vivo">
<h2>Imaging <i>In Vivo</i></h2>
<p>Current imaging methods can only detect cancers once they have made a visible change to a tissue, by which time, thousands of cells will have proliferated and perhaps metastasized. And even when visible, the nature of the tumor&mdash;malignant or benign&mdash;and the characteristics that might make it responsive to a particular treatment must be assessed through tissue biopsies. Furthermore, while some primary malignancies can be determined to be metastatic, tumor pre-seeding of metastatic sites and micro-metastases are extremely difficult to detect with modern imaging modalities, even if the tissue in which they commonly occur are known, <i>a priori</i>. Finally, surgical resection of tumor tissue remains the standard of care for many tumor types and surgeons must weigh the consequences of removing often vital healthy tissue versus the cancerous mass which has grown non-uniformly within. Ultimately, removal of cancer cells at the single cell level is not possible with current surgical techniques.</p>
<p>Nanotechnology based imaging contrast agents being developed and translated today, offer the ability to specifically target and greatly enhance detection of tumor in vivo by way of conventional scanning devices, such as magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), (PET), and computed tomography (CT). Moreover, current nanoscale imaging platforms are enabling novel imaging modalities not traditional utilized for clinical cancer treatment and diagnosis, for example photoacoustic tomography (PAT), Raman spectroscopic imaging and multimodal imaging (i.e., contrast agents specific to several imaging modalities simultaneously). Nanotechnology enables all of these platforms by way of its ability to carry multiple components simultaneously (e.g., cancer cell-specific targeting agents or traditional imaging contrast agents) and nanoscale materials that are themselves the contrast agents of which enable greatly enhanced signal.</p>
<p>NCI-funded research has produced many notable examples over the last several years. For example, researchers at Stanford University and Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center developed multimodal nanoparticles capable of delineating the margins of brain tumors both preoperatively and intraoperatively. These MRI-PAT-Raman nanoparticles are able to be used both to track tumor growth and surgical staging, by way of MRI, but also in the same particle be used during surgical resection of brain tumor to give the surgeon &lsquo;eyes&rsquo; down to the single cancer cell level, increasing the potential tumor specific tissue removal.</p>
<p>For metastatic melanoma, researchers at MSKCC and Cornell University have developed silica-hybrid nanoparticles (&lsquo;C-dots&rsquo;) that deliver both PET and optical imaging contrast in the same platform. These nanoparticles are actively targeted to the cancer with cRGDY peptides that target this specific tumor type and have already made it successfully through initial clinical trials.</p>
<p>Another clinical cancer imaging problem being addressed by nanoscale solutions is prostate cancer. Researchers at Stanford University recently have been developing nanotechnologies that give both anatomical size and location of prostate cancer cells (nanobubbles for ultrasound imaging) and functional information to avoid overdiagnosis/treatment as well as to monitor progression (self-assemblying nanoparticles for photoacoustic imaging). The nanoplatforms developed by this group are coupled directly to their recently approved handheld transrectal ultrasound and photoacoustic (TRUSPA) device. Ultimately offering a more effective, integrated and less invasive technique to image and biopsy prostate cancers for diagnosis and prognostication prior to performing common interventions (surgical resection, radiotherapy, etc.).</p>
<p>Similarly, gold nanoparticles are being used to enhance light scattering for endoscopic techniques that can be used during colonoscopies. One really powerful potential that has always been envisioned for nanotechnology in cancer has been the potential to simultaneously image and deliver therapy in vivo and several groups have been pushing forward these &lsquo;theranostic&rsquo; nanoscale platforms. One group at Emory University has been developing one of these for ovarian and pancreatic cancers, which are traditionally harder to deliver therapeutics to. Their platform for pancreatic cancer can break through the fibrotic stromal tissue of which these tumors are protected by in the pancreas. After traversing through this barrier, they are composed of magnetic iron cores which allow MRI contrast for diagnosis and deliver small-molecule drugs directly to cancer cells to treat.</p>
<p>Finally, nanotechnology is enabling the visualization of molecular markers that identify specific stages and cancer cell death induced by therapy, allowing doctors to see cells and molecules undetectable through conventional imaging. A group at Stanford has developed the Target-Enabled in Situ Ligand Assembly (TESLA) nanoparticle system. This is based off nanoparticles which form directly in the body after IV-injection of molecular precursors. The precursors contain specific sequences of atoms which can only form larger nanoparticles after being cleaved by enzymes produced by cancer cells during apoptosis (i.e., cell death) and carry various image contrast agents to monitor (PET, MRI, etc.) local tumor response to therapies. Being able to track cancer cell death in vivo and at the molecular level is extremely important for delivering effective dosing regimens and/or precisely administering novel therapies or combinations.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1088973" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7117232">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088973&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Principle of a triple-modality MRI-photoacoustic-Raman nanoparticle for clinical use. The nanoparticle is injected intravenously. In contrast to small molecule contrast agents that wash out of the tumor quickly, the nanoparticles are stably internalized within the brain tumor cells, allowing the whole spectrum from preoperative MRI for surgical planning to intraoperative imaging to be performed with a single injection. T1-weighted MRI depicts the outline of the tumor due to the T1-shortening effect of the gadolinium. During the surgery, photoacoustic imaging with its greater depth penetration and 3D imaging capabilities can be used to guide the gross resection steps, while Raman imaging can guide the resection of the microscopic tumor at the resection margins. Raman would be used for rapid conformation of clean margins in the operating room instead of the time-consuming analysis of frozen sections.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1088974" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7117233">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088974&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Present and future of NanoOncology Image-guided Surgical Suite. Preoperative conventional imaging tools are used to screen for disease and inform optically- driven minimally-invasive and open surgical procedures. Clinically available particle platforms can be monitored in real-time using portable multichannel camera systems. Representative translational probes and devices for future clinical use are also shown. In the future, the operating surgeon will select suitable probe-device combinations for specific indications, and be provided with structural, functional, and/or molecular-level data regarding ssue status for further treatment management.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="in-vitro">
<h2>Sensing In Vitro</h2>
<p>Nanotechnology-enabled <strong>in vitro diagnostic devices</strong> offer high sensitivity and selectivity, and capability to perform simultaneous measurements of multiple targets. Well-established fabrication techniques (e.g., lithography) can be used to manufacture integrated, portable devices or point-of-care systems. A diagnostic device or biosensor contains a biological recognition element, which through biochemical reaction can detect the presence, activity or concentration of a specific biological molecule in the solution. This reaction could be associated, for example with: binding of antigen and antibody, hybridization of two single stranded DNA fragments, or binding of capture ligand to the cell surface epitope. A transducer part of the detection device is used to convert the biochemical event into a quantifiable signal which can be measured. The transduction mechanisms can rely on light, magnetic, or electronic effects.</p>
<p>Several devices have been designed for detection of various biological signatures from serum or tissue. Few examples of diagnostic devices relying on nanotechnology or nanoparticles are given in Figure #. The bio-barcode assay was designed as a sandwich immunoassay in the laboratory of Chad Mirkin at Northwestern University. It utilizes magnetic nanoparticles (MMPs) which are functionalized with monoclonal antibodies specific to the target protein of interest and then mixed with the sample to promote capture of target proteins. The MMP-protein hybrid structures are then combined with gold nanoparticle (Au-NP) probes which carry DNA-barcodes. Target protein-specific DNA barcodes are released into solution and detected using the scanometric assay with sensitivities in femto-picomolar range.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2066" sys_dependentid="1088975" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7117234">
<figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088975&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>The image shows the DEAL (DNA-encoded antibody library) barcode assay, a high density information test for human blood proteins designed to show the individual identities of every human disease, allowing for personalized medicine.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<p>James Heath&rsquo;s laboratory at Caltech designed sandwich immunoassay devices which rely on DNA-encoded antibody libraries (DEAL). DEAL technique uses DNA-directed immobilization of antibodies in microfluidic channels allowing to convert a pre-patterned single stranded (ss) DNA barcode microarray into an antibody microarray. ssDNA oligomers attached onto the sensor surface are robust and can withstand elevated temperatures of channel fabrication. Subsequent flow-through of the DNA-antibody conjugates in channels transforms the DNA microarray into an antibody microarray and allow to perform multiplex surface-bound sandwich immunoassays. These devices allow for on-chip blood separation and measurement of large protein panels directly from blood.</p>
<p>Diagnostic Magnetic Resonance (DMR) sensor platform was designed in the laboratory of Ralph Weissleder at Massachusetts General Hospital. The DMR mechanism exploits changes in the transverse relaxation signal of water molecules in a magnetic field as a sensing mechanism for magnetic nanoparticle labeled analytes. Highly integrated systems including microfluidic processing circuits and nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) detection head with high signal to noise ratio were built and are capable of to detect presence of cells, vesicles, and proteins in clinical samples.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2066" sys_dependentid="1088965" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7117235">
<figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088965&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Here, when cancer cells (cell nuclei in blue) were treated with antibody-conjugated nanoparticles, the antibodies (red) and the nanoparticle cores (green) separated into different cellular compartments. Such knowledge may lead to improved methods of cancer detection in vivo as well as better nanoparticle-based treatments.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Shan Wang&rsquo;s laboratory at Stanford University designed Giant Magnetoresistive (GMR) biosensors for protein detection. These nanosensors operate by changing their electrical resistance in response to changes in the local magnetic field. They were adapted to detection of biological signatures in solution by implementing a traditional sandwich assay directly on GMR nanosensors. Antibodies are immobilized on the GMR sensor surface and are used as capture probes for the sample containing target proteins. A magnetic particle is used to label the biomolecule of interest in the sample and GMR sensor is used for signal transduction. These sensors were used to measure protein levels in complex sample mixtures and also were employed to assess kinetics of protein interactions.</p>
<p>The devices described above are capable of analyzing large panels of biological signatures at the same time providing for high level of multiplexing. The data analysis can establish correlations among different biomarker levels and map correlations of network signaling and thus provide tools for patient stratification based on their response to different treatments and ultimately improve therapeutic efficacy of the one selected. New advancements in microfluidic technologies opened opportunities to integrate sample preparation and sample processing with biosensors and to realize fully integrated devices that directly deliver full data for a medical diagnosis from a single sample.</p>
</section>
<section id="measuring-response">
<h2>Measuring Response to Therapy and the Liquid Biopsy</h2>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2066" sys_dependentid="1088977" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7117236">
<figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088977&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Imaged here is a microfluidic magneto-nano chip with 8 by 8 sensors arrays and 8 microfluidic channels. These chips are being developed to monitor protein profiles in blood samples from cancer patients to improve therapeutic effectiveness.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Measurement of an individual patient&rsquo;s response to therapeutics during the course of their disease is the basis for precise and prognostic medical care. Accurate and disease relevant monitoring can allow for optimized treatment regimens (e.g., therapeutic course correction, drug combinations, and dose attenuation), preemptive clinical decision making (e.g., therapeutic responders vs. non-responders, and more), and patient stratification for clinical trials. Beyond the more traditional gold standards of in vivo imaging, tissue biopsy and in vitro diagnostics available for this purpose, the &ldquo;liquid biopsy&rdquo; offers the ability to measure response to therapy by way of simple and serial blood draws. Traditional biopsies involve resection of small volumes of the tumor tissue directly, and thus, remain invasive procedures that cannot offer the sampling necessitated to track disease progression relative to the course of therapy or the dynamics of its evolving biology. Liquid biopsies rely on the fact that tumors shed material (e.g., cells, DNA, other cancer-specific biomolecules) into circulation, over time and in response to therapy. Although, the amount of materials shed by any given tumor and / or stage is typically at incredibly low concentrations relative to the rest of the blood&rsquo;s constituents (e.g., erythrocytes, leukocytes, thrombocytes, plasma, etc.). This requires specific and sensitive tools to detect, capture, and purify the circulating tumor material relative to the rest. Nanotechnology is enabling these tools to become reality.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2066" sys_dependentid="1088978" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="7117237">
<figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img alt="" src="https://percussion.cancer.gov:443/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088978&amp;sys_command=edit" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Here a fluorescent nanosensor (cyan) and a chemical with anti-cancer activity (dichloroacetic acid) were injected into the blood vessels (red) of a mouse implanted with human breast cancer (green). This image shows that the nanosensor detects the presence of dichloroacetic acid near the tumor.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Recent technological advances in the coupling of complex microfluidics and nanoscale materials have allowed the high-purity capture and downstream functional characterization of circulating tumor cells (CTCs), cell-free tumor DNA, microemboli, exosomes, proteins, neoantigens, and more. Recent examples include, capture and subsequent release of CTCs within microfluidic systems to maintain viable cells for downstream whole genome sequencing, ex vivo expansion, RNA sequencing, and more. Of these examples, one type of device uses magnetic nanoparticles to enrich whole blood prior to magnetic separation within the microfluidic and the other device uses thermoresponsive nanopolymers that specifically capture CTCs as they flow through the microfluidic then release upon a change in temperature once blood processing is complete. In both cases, the detection sensitivities are very high (e.g., for enumeration &gt;95%) and capture purity is much higher than other non-nanomaterial based devices. Furthermore, the processing times are increasing every year as the technology evolves, currently averaging 10 mL blood per 30 minutes.</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1074446" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Cancer therapies are currently limited to surgery, radiation, and chemotherapy. All three methods risk damage to normal tissues or incomplete eradication of the cancer. Nanotechnology offers the means to target chemotherapies directly and selectively to cancerous cells and neoplasms, guide in surgical resection of tumors, and enhance the therapeutic efficacy of radiation-based and other <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1051490" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1051490" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="6654371">current treatment modalities</a>. All of this can add up to a decreased risk to the patient and an increased probability of survival.</p>
<p>Research on nanotechnology cancer therapy extends beyond drug delivery into the creation of new therapeutics available only through use of nanomaterial properties. Although small compared to cells, nanoparticles are large enough to encapsulate many small molecule compounds, which can be of multiple types. At the same time, the relatively large surface area of nanoparticle can be functionalized with ligands, including small molecules, DNA or RNA strands, peptides, aptamers or antibodies. These ligands can be used for therapeutic effect or to direct nanoparticle fate in vivo. These properties enable combination drug delivery, multi-modality treatment and combined therapeutic and diagnostic, known as &ldquo;theranostic,&rdquo; action. The physical properties of nanoparticles, such as energy absorption and re-radiation, can also be used to disrupt diseased tissue, as in laser ablation and hyperthermia applications.</p>
<p>Integrated development of innovative nanoparticle packages and active pharmaceutical ingredients will also enable exploration of a wider repertoire of active ingredients, no longer confined to those with acceptable pharmokinetic or biocompatibility behavior. In addition, immunogenic cargo and surface coatings are being investigated as both adjuvants to nanoparticle-mediated and traditional radio- and chemotherapy as well as stand-alone therapies. Innovative strategies include the design of nanoparticles as artificial antigen presenting cells and in vivo depots of immunostimulatory factors that exploit nanostructured architecture for sustained anti-tumor activity.</p>
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="chemotherapy">
<h2>Delivering Chemotherapy</h2>
<p>The traditional use of nanotechnology in cancer therapeutics has been to improve the pharmacokinetics and reduce the systemic toxicities of chemotherapies through the selective targeting and delivery of these anticancer drugs to tumor tissues. The advantage of nanosized carriers is that they can increase the delivered drug&rsquo;s overall therapeutic index through nanoformulations in with chemotherapeutics are either encapsulated or conjugated to the surfaces of nanoparticles. This capability is largely due to their tunable size and surface properties. Size is a major factor in the delivery of nanotechnology-based therapeutics to tumor tissues. Selective delivery of nanotherapeutic platforms depends primarily on the passive targeting of tumors through the enhanced permeability and retention (EPR) effect. This phenomenon relies on defects specific to tumor microenvironment such as defects in lymphatic drainage, along with increased tumor vasculature permeability, to allow nanoparticles (&lt;200 nm) to accumulate in the tumor microenvironment. Furthermore, the timing or site of drug release can be controlled by triggered events, such as ultrasound, pH, heat, or by material composition.</p>
<p>Several members of the Alliance are working towards developing nanomaterial-based delivery platforms that will reduce the toxicity of chemotherapeutics and increase their overall effectiveness. In the Centers for Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence, the <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1051523" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1051523" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="6654360">Center for Multiple Myeloma Nanotherapy at Washington University</a> is developing a strategy for photodynamic therapy, which would bypass the toxicity that currently limits the effectiveness of chemotherapy for multiple myeloma patients. This strategy is designed for use in bone marrow, which is normally inaccessible to external radiation sources.</p>
<p>The Innovative Research in Cancer Nanotechnology awardees are focused on understanding the fundamental aspects of nanomaterial interactions with the biological system to improve on the development of cancer therapeutics and diagnostics. Several of these awardees are studying nanoparticle-based delivery and have proposed nanosystems that deliver chemotherapeutics by penetrating through physiological barriers for access to more restricted tumors via targeting and/or mechanical deformation of particles (Yang, Karathanasis, Kabanov). One of them is dedicated to using a synergistic approach for the delivery of paclitaxel and gemcitabine chemotherapeutics in mesoporous silica nanoconstructs (Nel).</p>
</section>
<section id="immunotherapy">
<h2>Nano-enabled Immunotherapy</h2>
<p>Immunotherapy is a promising new front in cancer treatment encompassing a number of approaches, including checkpoint inhibition and cellular therapies. Although results for some patients have been spectacular, only a minority of patients being treated for just a subset of cancers experience durable responses to these therapies. Expanding the benefits of immunotherapy requires a greater understanding of tumor-host immune system interactions. New technologies for molecular and functional analysis of single cells are being used to interrogate tumor and immune cells and elucidate molecular indicators and functional immune responses to therapy. To this end, nano-enabled devices and materials are being leveraged to sort, image, and characterize T cells in the Alliance&rsquo;s NanoSystems Biology Cancer Center.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2066" sys_dependentid="1088984" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6654374">
<figure class="image-right-medium centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088984&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>This scanning electron microscope image shows dendritic cells, pseudo-colored in green, interacting with T cells, pseudo-colored in pink. The dendritic cells internalize the particles, process the antigens, and present peptides to T cells to direct immune responses.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Nanotechnologies are also being investigated to deliver immunotherapy. This includes use of nanoparticles for delivery of immunostimulatory or immunomodulatory molecules in combination with chemo- or radiotherapy or as adjuvants to other immunotherapies. Standalone nanoparticle vaccines are also being designed to raise sufficient T cell response to eradicate tumors, through co-delivery of antigen and adjuvant, the inclusion of multiple antigens to stimulate multiple dendritic cell targets, and continuous release of antigens for prolonged immune stimulation. Molecular blockers of immune-suppressive factors produced can also be co-encapsulated in nanoparticle vaccines to alter the immune context of tumors and improve response, an approach being pursued in the <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1051522" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1051522" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="6654361">Nano Approaches to Modulate Host Cell Response for Cancer Therapy Center at UNC</a>. Researchers in this Center are also investigating the use of nanoparticles to capture antigens from tumors following radiotherapy to create patient specific treatments, similar in principle to a &ldquo;dendritic cell activating scaffold&rdquo; currently in a Phase I clinical trial.</p>
<p>Additional uses of nanotechnology for immunotherapy include immune depots placed in or near tumors for in situ vaccination and artificial antigen presenting cells. These and other approaches will advance and be refined as our understanding of cancer immunotherapy deepens.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1088985" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6654375">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1088985&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Depiction of the complex pathway involved in cancer immunotherapy. Nanoparticle delivery vehicles can play a role at multiple points along this pathway.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="radiotherapy">
<h2>Delivering or Augmenting Radiotherapy</h2>
<p>Roughly half of all cancer patients receive some form of radiation therapy over the course of their treatment. Radiation therapy uses high-energy radiation to shrink tumors and kill cancer cells. Radiation therapy kills cancer cells by damaging their DNA inducing cellular apoptosis. Radiation therapy can either damage DNA directly or create charged particles (atoms with an odd or unpaired number of electrons) within the cells that can in turn damage the DNA. Most types of radiation used for cancer treatment utilize X-rays, gamma rays, and charged particles. As such, they are inherently toxic to all cells, not just cancer cells, and are given in doses that are as efficacious as possible while not being too harmful to the body or fatal. Because of this tradeoff between efficacy and safety relative to tumor type, location, and stage, often the efficacy of treatment must remain at reduced levels in order to not be overtly toxic to surrounding tissue or organs near the tumor mass.</p>
<p>Nanotechnology-specific research has been focusing on radiotherapy as a treatment modality that could greatly benefit from nanoscale materials&rsquo; properties and increased tumor accumulation. The primary mechanisms by which these nanoscale platforms rely are either enhancement of the effect of the radiotherapy, augmentation of the therapy, and/or novel externally applied electromagnetic radiation modalities. More specifically, most of these nanotechnology platforms rely on the interaction between X-rays and nanoparticles due to inherent atomic level properties of the materials used. These include high-Z atomic number nanoparticles that enhance the Compton and photoelectric effects of conventional radiation therapy. In essence, increasing efficacy while maintaining the current radiotherapy dosage and its subsequent toxicity to the surrounding tissue. Other platforms utilize X-ray triggered drug-releasing nanoparticles that deliver drug locally at tumor site or to sensitize the cancer cells to radiotherapy in combination with the drug.  </p>
<p>Another type of therapy that relies upon external electromagnetic radiation is photodynamic therapy (PDT). It is an effective anticancer procedure for superficial tumor that relies on tumor localization of a photosensitizer followed by light activation to generate cytotoxic reactive oxygen species (ROS). Several nanomaterials platforms are being researched to this end. Often made of a lanthanide- or hafnium-doped high-Z core, once injected these can be externally irradiated by X-rays allowing the nanoparticle core to emit the visible light photons locally at the tumor site. Emission of photons from the particles subsequently activate a nanoparticle-bound or local photosensitizer to generate singlet oxygen (1O2) ROS for tumor destruction. Furthermore, these nanoparticles can be used as both PDT that generates ROS and for enhanced radiation therapy via the high-Z core. Although many of these platforms are initially being studied <i>in vivo</i> by intratumoral injection for superficial tumor sites, some are being tested for delivery via systemic injection to deep tissue tumors. The primary benefits to the patient would be local delivery of PDT to deep tissue tumor targets, an alternative therapy for cancer cells that have become radiotherapy resistant, and reduction in toxicity (e.g., light sensitivity) common to traditional PDT. Finally, other platforms utilize a form Cherenkov radiation to a similar end, of local photon emission to utilize as a trigger for local PDT. These can be utilized for deep-tissue targets as well.</p>
</section>
<section id="gene-therapy">
<h2>Delivering Gene Therapy</h2>
<p>The value of nanomaterial-based delivery has become apparent for new types of therapeutics such as those using nucleic acids, which are highly unstable in systemic circulation and sensitive to degradation. These include DNA and RNA-based genetic therapeutics such as small interfering RNAs (siRNAs), and microRNAs (miRNAs). Gene silencing therapeutics, siRNAs, have been reported to have significantly extended half-lives when delivered either encapsulated or conjugated to the surface of nanoparticles. These therapeutics are used in many cases to target &lsquo;undruggable&rsquo; cancer proteins. Additionally, the increased stability of genetic therapies delivered by nanocarriers, and often combined with controlled release, has been shown to prolong their effects.</p>
<p>Members of the Alliance are exploring nanotechnology-based delivery of nucleic acids as effective treatment strategies for a variety of cancers. In particular, the <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1051519" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1051519" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="6654362">Nucleic Acid-Based Nanoconstructs for the Treatment of Cancer Center at Northwestern University</a> is focused on the design and characterization of spherical nucleic acids for the delivery of RNA therapeutics to treat brain and prostate cancers. Project 1 of the Nano Approaches to Modulate Host Cell Response for Cancer Therapy Center at UNC-Chapel Hill targets vemurafenib resistant melanoma for direct suppression of drug resistance through delivery of siRNA using their polymetformin nanoparticles. Among the Innovative Research in Cancer Nanotechnology awardees, the Ohio State project (Guo), is focused on systematic characterization of <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i> RNA nanoparticle behavior for optimized delivery of siRNA to tumor cells, as well as cancer immunotherapeutics.</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1077041" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<section id="upcoming">
<h2>Upcoming Events with&nbsp;NSDB Participation</h2>
<p><strong><a href="https://www.nimhd.nih.gov/programs/edu-training/hd-research-institute/">NIMHD Health Disparities Research Institute</a></strong><br />August 14-18, 2017<br />NIH<br />Bethesda, MD</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://rnanano.osu.edu/Guo/Biomotor2017/Biomotor2017.html">First Conference on Biomotors, Virus Assembly, and Nanobiotechnology Applications</a></strong><br />August 16-19, 2017<br />Columbus, OH</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://www.acs.org/content/acs/en/meetings/fall-2017.html">254th American Chemical Society National Meeting and Expo</a></strong><br />August 20-24, 2017<br />Washington, DC</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.glma.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=Page.ViewPage&amp;PageID=1063">2017 GLMA Annual Conference on LGBT Health</a></strong><br />September 13-17, 2017<br />Doubletree Philadelphia City Center<br />Philadelphia, PA</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://expertevents.eventsair.com/QuickEventWebsitePortal/cvb/website">12th International Conference on Cerebral Vascular Biology</a></strong><br />Nov 28-Dec 1, 2017<br />Melbourne, Australia</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://sensorsglobalsummit.com/">Biological + Chemical Sensors Global Summit 2017</a></strong><br />Dec 5-7, 2017<br />San Diego, CA</p>
</section>
<h2>Past Events with&nbsp;NSDB Participation</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.imagingin2020.com/"><strong>Imaging in 2020: Molecular Imaging for Diagnosis and Surgery/Therapy</strong></a><br />September 18-22, 2016<br />Moran, WY</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wmis.org/meetings/"><strong>2016 World Molecular Imaging Congress</strong></a><br />September 7-10, 2016<br />New York, NY</p>
<p><a href="http://spie.org/conferences-and-exhibitions/optics-and-photonics"><strong>SPIE Optics + Photonics</strong></a><br />August 28-Sept 1, 2016<br />San Diego, CA</p>
<p><a href="http://www.acs.org/content/acs/en/meetings/fall-2016.html"><strong>252<sup><span style="font-size: small;" size="2">nd</span></sup> American Chemical Society National Meeting &amp; Exposition</strong></a><br /> August 15-21, 2016<br />Philadelphia, PA</p>
<p><a href="http://www.grc.org/programs.aspx?id=16492"><strong>Drug Carriers in Medicine &amp; Biology (GRS): Leveraging Drug Carrier Design and Mechanistic Insight of Nanoparticle Therapeutics to Optimize Clinical Efficacy</strong></a><br />August 6-7, 2016<br />Waterville Valley, NH</p>
<p><a href="https://www.fusion-conferences.com/conference47.php"><strong>RNA Nanotechnology Conference</strong></a><br /> August 1-4, 2016<br /> Wokefield Park<br />Berkshire, UK</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://www.clinam.org/">CLINAM 9, Clinical Nanomedicine and Targeted Medicine</a><br /></strong>July 26-29, 2016<br />Basel, Switzerland</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.grc.org/programs.aspx?id=12961">In vivo Magnetic Resonance (GRC)</a><br /></strong>July 17-22, 2016<br />Proctor Academy, Andover, NH</p>
<p><strong><span><a href="http://www.ucdenver.edu/academics/colleges/pharmacy/AboutUs/NewsEvents/Pages/Mechanisms-and-Barriers-in-Nanomedicine-.aspx">Mechanisms and Barriers in Nanomedicine Workshop</a></span></strong><br /><span>July 15-16, 2016<br /> Beaver Run Resort<br /> Breckenridge, CO</span></p>
<p><a href="http://www.grc.org/programs.aspx?id=14444"><strong>2016, Barriers of the CNS (GRS): Involvement of the CNS Barriers in Health, Drug Discovery &amp; Disease</strong></a><br />June 18-19, 2016<br />Colby-Sawyer College, New London, NH</p>
<p><a href="http://www.snmmi.org/AM2016?navItemNumber=581"><strong>SNMMI 2016 Annual Meeting</strong></a><br />June 11-15, 2016<br />San Diego, CA</p>
<p><span><strong><a href="https://pharmacy.unc.edu/events/nanoformulation-workshop/">2016 Trans-Agency Blood Brain Interface Workshop</a></strong></span><br /><span>June 8-9, 2016<br /> National Heart, Lung Blood Institute, National Cancer Institute, Department of Defense<br /> Bethesda, MD</span></p>
<p><span><a href="http://www.medicalinformaticsworld.com/sensors/"><strong>5th Annual Medical Informatics World Conference</strong></a><br />May 22-23, 2017<br />Renaissance Waterfront Hotel<br />Boston, MA</span></p>
<p><span><strong><a href="http://www.techconnectworld.com/Nanotech2016/about/">Nanotech 2016</a></strong><br />May 22-25, 2016<br />Washington DC</span></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://www.grc.org/programs.aspx?id=14891">GRC: Multimodal Nano-Therapies Against Cancer</a></strong><br /> May 18-23, 2017<br /> Mount Snow <br /> West Dover, VT</p>
<p><strong><span><a href="http://www.aacr.org/Meetings/Pages/MeetingDetail.aspx?EventItemID=63#.VvQHcGffOfA">AACR Annual Meeting 2016</a></span></strong><br /><span>April 16-20, 2016<br /></span>New Orleans, LA<span><br /></span></p>
<a href="https://pharmacy.unc.edu/events/nanoformulation-workshop/"><strong>Carolina Nanoformulation Workshop</strong></a><br /> March 14-18, 2016<br /> Center for Nanotechnology in Drug Delivery in the Eshelman School of Pharmacy<br /> Chapel Hill, NC
<section id="other-past-events">
<p><a href="http://www.uab.edu/nanobiosummit/"><strong>4<sup>th</sup> Annual Alabama 2016 NanoBio Summit</strong></a><strong><br /></strong>October 13-14, 2015<br />Alabama State University<br />Birmingham, AL</p>
</section>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1077648" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</h2>
<p><strong>Principal Investigator:</strong> Alexander Kabanov, Ph.D., D. Sc.</p>
<p><strong>Training Focus and Objectives</strong></p>
<p>The goal of the program is to make a major contribution to the growth of the cancer nanotechnology workforce by providing training and research experiences to a highly select cohort of postdoctoral fellows. We have assembled a team of 22 outstanding Program faculty from 11 departments and 3 schools at the UNC-Chapel Hill with expertise in physical and material sciences, biomedical engineering, drug delivery, computational modeling as well as basic biomedical research and clinical science, all of whom have demonstrated strong interests, capabilities and collaborations at the interface between nanoscience and cancer. The objectives of the C-CNTP are to:</p>
<ul>
<li>recruit an elite group of talented postdoctoral fellows from diverse backgrounds with PhD or MD and provide them with outstanding postdoctoral experience including focused didactic training and co-mentored research experience with faculty mentors from complementary fields;</li>
<li>provide each trainee with Intensive Integrated Learning Accelerating Module training in conjunction with flipped classrooms followed by workshops and didactic courses to remediate differences in their backgrounds and to deepen the knowledge and understanding in the key areas of cancer nanotechnology; and</li>
<li>facilitate transition of trainees to independence by providing them with opportunities to:
<ul>
<li>conduct original cancer nanotechnology research projects;</li>
<li>apply for the individual cancer nanotechnology Pilot Grants within C-CNTP, and</li>
<li>acquire written and oral communications skills needed to publish manuscripts, report results, and write successful individual extramural support applications focused on problems of cancer nanotechnology.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091270" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6655257">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091270&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://pharmacy.unc.edu/academics/fellowships/carolina-cancer-nanotechnology-t32-training-program/">Visit the University of North Carolina CNTC website.</a></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1077649" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>Northwestern University</h2>
<p><strong>Principal Investigator:</strong> Gayle Woloschak, Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Training Focus and Objectives</strong></p>
<p>The goal of this program is to train MD- and PhD-level investigators (up to 4 per year) in the principles and tools of nanotechnology, cancer biology, and clinical oncology with the eventual goal of applying these skills to translational research that impacts cancer patients. The training program offers a well-rounded curriculum with basic courses, career development programs, and research-based experiences that is designed around the needs of each of the trainees. Training includes many nanotechnology resources including NU's International Institute for Nanotechnology, the Institute for BioNanotechnology, and the NU CCNE. Faculty from each of these centers participate in our T32 program. Fellows enrolled in the training program will acquire the skills and knowledge to design cancer nanomaterials, to investigate their biological properties, and to evaluate their safety and efficacy.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091269" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6655259">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091269&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<p><a href="http://cancer.northwestern.edu/research/training_travel/training_programs/programs/nanotechnology.cfm">Visit the Northwestern CNTC website.</a></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1077650" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>Stanford University</h2>
<p><strong>Principal Investigator:</strong> Jianghong Rao, Ph.D., and Dean Felsher, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Training Focus and Objectives</strong></p>
<p>The Stanford Cancer-Translational Nanotechnology Training (Cancer-TNT) Program is a diverse and synergistic 3-year training program bringing together 25 faculty in 9 departments from three schools to train the next generation of interdisciplinary leaders who will pursue challenges in cancer research and clinical translation. During the proposed 5-year cycle, we will recruit a total of 12 postdoctoral trainees to provide them with education and cross-disciplinary training to develop interdisciplinary researchers in cancer nanotechnology translation. Our trainees' skill sets will bridge multiple disciplines such as chemistry, molecular biology, bioengineering, nanoengineering, molecular imaging, and clinical cancer medicine. Trainees will be able to advance cancer research, diagnosis, and management. The 3-year program includes coursework and research with two complementary mentors. The course work will be selected in cancer biology, cancer immunology, molecular imaging, molecular pharmacology, and gene therapy, nanomedicine, micro/nanofabrication, biochips, electrical engineering, and materials science, in consultation with the program director and research advisor. In addition, hands-on training activities in Nanocharacterization and a clinical component including Stanford Oncology Clinical Lecture Series will be offered. In their second year trainees will prepare a mock grant proposal to help them gain experience and confidence in the grant application process. A Training Committee will oversee trainee progress, with an Advisory Committee monitoring the entire program.</p>
<p></p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1093979" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6675479">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=661037&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1093979" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p>
<p><a href="http://med.stanford.edu/ctnt.html">Visit the Stanford CNTC website.</a></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1077662" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p></p>
<h2>University of Texas at MD Anderson Cancer Center</h2>
<p><strong>Principal Investigator:</strong> Konstantin Sokolov, Ph.D., Sunil Krishnan, M.D., and Rebecca Richards-Kortum, Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Training Focus and Objectives</strong></p>
<p>Currently, there is a growing gap between new discoveries coming from academic labs and their translation into clinic. To address this problem, we have designed a training program to educate future leaders in the field of nanotechnology with specific interests in cancer translational research. Our program is based on collaboration between The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center and Rice University and it combines multidisciplinary mentorship of translational research projects with hands-on coursework and seminar experiences. The program provides predoctoral and post-doctoral training. All trainees will work with at least two program faculty mentors (one from Rice and one from MD Anderson) to carry out an independent research project. In addition, fellows will write a research fellowship grant as an essential part of their preparation for independent careers. Didactic coursework will help T32 fellows to develop the skills needed to define and lead research projects that address barriers to translation of cancer nanotechnology. Incoming trainees will participate in a unique boot camp in "Cancer Management and Nanotechnology" that provides an overview of current opportunities and barriers in the field. Trainees will be introduced to federal resources in cancer nanotechnology by taking a trip to the NCI Nanotechnology Characterization Lab. Finally, trainees will gain lab management skills in an introductory course in laboratory and project management. At completion of the program, fellows will have a deep understanding of translational research in cancer nanotechnology with the demonstrated ability to carry out independent research in this multidisciplinary field.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091055" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6655261">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091055&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://www.mdanderson.org/education-training/clinical-research-training/postdoctoral-training/postdoctoral-fellowships/cancer-nanotech-t32.html">Visit the MD Anderson CNTC website.</a></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1077666" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>On September 13, 2004, the National Cancer Institute (NCI) announced a major commitment to develop and apply nanotechnology to cancer research. To carry out this initiative, the NCI, formed the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer, a comprehensive, integrated initiative encompassing researchers, clinicians, and public and private organizations, to develop and translate cancer-related nanotechnology research into clinical practice.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091598" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6655265">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091598&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Focus for this research has included several areas, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Molecular imaging and early detection</li>
<li>In vivo nanotechnology imaging systems</li>
<li>Reporters of efficacy</li>
<li>Multifunctional therapeutics</li>
<li>Prevention and control</li>
<li>Research enablers</li>
</ul>
<div class="accordion" data-otp-selector="">
<h2>Centers of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence (2010-2015)</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Carolina Center of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence</strong><br />&nbsp;University of North Carolina<br /> &nbsp;Principal Investigators: Joseph DeSimone, Ph.D., and Joel Tepper, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Center for Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence and Translation</strong><br />&nbsp;Stanford University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Sanjiv Sam Gambhir, M.D., Ph.D., and Shan Wang, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Center for Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence at Johns Hopkins</strong><br />&nbsp;Johns Hopkins University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Peter Searson, Ph.D., and Martin Pomper, M.D., Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Center for Translational Cancer Nanomedicine</strong><br />&nbsp;Northeastern University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Vladimir Torchilin, Ph.D., D.Sc. and Nahum Goldberg, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dartmouth Center for Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence</strong><br />&nbsp;Dartmouth College<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Ian Baker, Ph.D., and Keith Paulsen, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>MIT-Harvard Center of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence</strong><br />&nbsp;MIT and Harvard University, Massachusetts General Hospital<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Robert Langer, Ph.D., and Ralph Weissleder, M.D., Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanomaterials for Cancer Diagnostics and Therapeutics</strong><br />&nbsp;Northwestern University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Chad Mirkin, Ph.D. and Steven T. Rosen, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanosystems Biology Cancer Center (NSBCC)</strong><br />&nbsp;California Institute of Technology<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: James Heath, Ph.D., Leroy Hood, M.D., Ph.D. and Michael Phelps, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Texas Center for Cancer Nanomedicine</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Texas Health Science Center<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: David G. Gorenstein, Ph.D., Mauro Ferrari, Ph.D., Anil Sood, M.D., G. Lopez-Berestein, M.D. and Jennifer L. West, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Centers of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence (2005-2010)</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Carolina Center of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence</strong><br />&nbsp;University of North Carolina<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Rudolph Juliano, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Center for Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence Focused on Therapy Response</strong><br />&nbsp;Stanford University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Sanjiv Sam Gambhir, M.D., Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Center of Nanotechnology for Treatment, Understanding, and Monitoring of Cancer (NANO-TUMOR)</strong><br />&nbsp;University of California, San Diego<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Sadik Esener, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Emory-Georgia Tech Nanotechnology Center for Personalized and Predictive Oncology</strong><br />&nbsp;Emory University and Georgia Institute of Technology<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Shuming Nie, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>MIT-Harvard Center of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence</strong><br />&nbsp;MIT and Harvard University, Massachusetts General Hospital<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Robert Langer, Ph.D., and Ralph Weissleder, M.D., Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanomaterials for Cancer Diagnostics and Therapeutics</strong><br />&nbsp;Northwestern University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Chad Mirkin, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanosystems Biology Cancer Center (NSBCC)</strong><br />&nbsp;California Institute of Technology<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: James Heath, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Siteman Center of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence</strong><br />&nbsp;Washington University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Samuel Wickline, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Cancer Nanotechnology Platform Partnerships (2010-2015)</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Combinatorial-designed Nano-platforms to Overcome Tumor Resistance</strong><br />&nbsp;Northeastern University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Mansoor Amiji, Ph.D., and Zhen-feng Duan, M.D., Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>High-Capacity Nanocarriers for Cancer Therapeutics</strong><br />&nbsp;University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Alexander Kabanov, Ph.D., D.Sc.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Magnetoresistive Sensor Platform for Parallel Cancer Marker Detection</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Utah<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Marc Porter, Ph.D., and Sean J. Mulvihill, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanobioconjugate Based on Polymalic Acid for Brain Tumor Treatment</strong><br />&nbsp;Cedars-Sinai Medical Center<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Julia Ljubimova, M.D., Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanoscale Metal-Organic Frameworks for Imaging and Therapy of Pancreatic Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Chicago and University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Wenbin Lin, Ph.D., and Jen Jen Yeh, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Peptide-Directed Protocells and Virus-like Particles: New Nanoparticle Platforms for Targeted Cellular Delivery of Multicomponent Cargo</strong><br />&nbsp;University of New Mexico<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Cheryl Willman, M.D., and C. Jeffrey Brinker, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Preclinical Platform for Theranostic Nanoparticles in Pancreatic Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;Rice University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Naomi Halas, Ph.D., D.Sc., Amit Joshi, Ph.D., and Sunil Krishnan, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>RNA Nanotechnology in Cancer Therapy</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Kentucky<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Peixuan Guo, Ph.D., and John Rossi, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Targeting SKY Kinase in B-Lineage ALL with CD-19 Specific C-61 Nanoparticles</strong><br />&nbsp;Children&acirc;&euro;&trade;s Hospital Los Angeles<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Fatih Uckun, M.D., Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Theranostic Nanoparticles for Targeted Treatment of Pancreatic Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;Emory University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Lily Yang, M.D., Ph.D., and Hui Mao, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Toxicity and Efficacy of Gold Nanoparticle Photothermal Therapy in Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;Emory University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Dong Shin, M.D., and Mostafa El-Sayed, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tumor Targeted Nanobins for the Treatment of Metastatic Breast and Ovarian Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;Northwestern University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Thomas O'Halloran, Ph.D., and Vincent Cryns, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Cancer Nanotechnology Platform Partnerships (2005-2010)</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Detecting Cancer Early with Targeted Nano-probes for Vascular Signatures</strong><br />&nbsp;University of California<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Douglas Hanahan, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>DNA-linked Dendrimer Nanoparticle Systems for Cancer Diagnosis and Treatment</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Michigan<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: James Baker Jr., M.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hybrid Nanoparticles in Imaging and Therapy of Prostate Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Missouri<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Kattesh Katti, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Integrated System for Cancer Biomarker Detection</strong><br />&nbsp;Massachusetts Institute of Technology<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Scott Manalis, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Metallofullerene Nanoplatform for Imaging and Treating Infiltrative Tumor</strong><br />&nbsp;Virginia Commonwealth University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Panos Fatouros, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multifunctional Nanoparticles in Diagnosis and Therapy of Pancreatic Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;State University of New York<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Paras Prasad, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanotechnology Platform for Pediatric Brain Cancer Imaging and Therapy</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Washington<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Miqin Zhang, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanotechnology Platform for Targeting Solid Tumors</strong><br />&nbsp;The Sidney Kimmel Cancer Center<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Jan Schnitzer, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanotherapeutic Strategy for Multidrug Resistant Tumors</strong><br />&nbsp;Northeastern University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Mansoor Amiji, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Near-Infrared Fluorescence Nanoparticles for Targeted Optical Imaging</strong><br />&nbsp;The University of Texas M. D. Anderson Cancer Center<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Chun Li, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Novel Cancer Nanotechnology Platforms for Photodynamic Therapy and Imaging</strong><br />&nbsp;Roswell Park Cancer Institute<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Ravindra K. Pandey, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Photodestruction of Ovarian Cancer: ErbB3 Targeted Aptamer-Nanoparticle Conjugate</strong><br />&nbsp;Massachusetts General Hospital<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Tayyaba Hasan, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Cancer Nanotechnology Training Centers (2010-2015)</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Boston University Cross-Disciplinary Training in Nanotechnology for Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;Boston University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Bennett B. Goldberg, Ph.D., and Douglas Faller, M.D., Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Integrative Cancer Nanoscience and Microsystems Training Center</strong><br />&nbsp;University of New Mexico<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Janet M. Oliver, Ph.D., and Abhaya Datye, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Midwest Cancer Nanotechnology Training Center (M-CNTC)</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Rashid Bashir, Ph.D., and Ann Nardulli, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Johns Hopkins Cancer Nanotechnology Training Center</strong><br />&nbsp;Johns Hopkins University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Denis Wirtz, Ph.D., and Hai-Quan Mao, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>The University of Kentucky Cancer Nanotechnology Training Center</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Kentucky<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Bradley D. Anderson, Ph.D., and B. Mark Evers, M.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>UCSD Cancer Nanotechnology Training Center</strong><br />&nbsp;University of California, San Diego<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigators: Robert F. Mattrey, M.D., and Andrew Kummel, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Pathway to Independence Awards in Cancer Nanotechnology Research (2010-2015)</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enzyme-Responsive Nanoemulsions as Tumor-Specific Ultrasound Contrast Agents</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Colorado, Boulder<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Andrew P. Goodwin, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inhibition of Metastasis-Initiating Cells by Chimeric Polypeptide Nanoparticles</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Utah<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Mingnan Chen, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanoplatform Based, Combinational Therapy against Breast Cancer Stem Cells</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Georgia<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Jin Xie, Ph.D.<br /><br />&bull;<strong>Nanotechnology for Minimally Invasive Cancer Detection and Resection</strong><br />&nbsp;Wake Forest University Health Sciences <br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Aaron M. Mohs, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Next-Generation Quantum Dots for Molecular and Cellular Imaging of Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Andrew M. Smith, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Theranostic Nanomedicine for Breast Cancer Prevention and Image-Guided Therapy</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Massachusetts, Lowell<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Prakash R. Rai, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tumor Targeting and Diagnostic Applications of Glycosylated Nanotubes</strong><br />&nbsp;Wake Forest University School of Medicine<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Ravi N. Singh, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Multidisciplinary Research Training and Team Development (2005-2010)</h2>
<p>Multidisciplinary Research Training and Team Development Fellowship Awards were granted to the following postdoctoral trainees:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Design of Affinity Capture Agents for Akt1 Using in situ Click Chemistry</strong><br />&nbsp; California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Steven W. Millward, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geldanamycin-Mediated Uptake of Nanoparticle Probes</strong><br />&nbsp;Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Giselle M. Knudsen, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Liposomal Delivery of High LET Emitters to Cell Nuclei</strong><br />&nbsp;Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Yah-El Har-El, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanolabels of Active Proteases for Cancer Detection</strong><br />&nbsp;University of California, San Francisco, California<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Mark D. Lim, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanoparticle-Bioconjugates as Cancer-Treating Agents</strong><br />&nbsp;Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, Texas<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Sofi Bin-Salamon, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanoprobes and Integrated Nanodevices for Cancer Detection and Treatment</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Colorado Health Services, Superior, CO<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Wounjhang Park, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanoscale Mechanisms of Hsp90 and Its Co-chaperones</strong><br />&nbsp;Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Ivo P. Doudevski, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Short-Interfering RNA-Gold Nanoparticle Bioconjugates: A New Cancer Therapy</strong><br />&nbsp;Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Adam B. Braunschweig, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Single Walled Carbon Nanotube Based Tumor Vaccines, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Institute for Cancer Research</strong><br />&nbsp;New York, New York<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Rena J. May, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Targeted Delivery Via Protein-Carbohydrate Interactions</strong><br />&nbsp;Liquidia, Inc., Research Triangle Park, North Carolina<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Ashley L. Galloway, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Targeted Photoactivated Nanopartcicles for the Treatment of Ovarian Cancer</strong><br />&nbsp;Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, MA<br />&nbsp;Trainee: Daniel Neuman, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<p>NCI-NSF Training Grants were awarded in 2005 to establish training programs for U.S. science and engineering doctoral students through the Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship Program (IGERT). The awarded programs were:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Building Leadership for the Nanotechnology Workforce of Tomorrow</strong><br />&nbsp;University of Washington<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Marjorie Olmstead, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Integrative Nanoscience and Microsystems,</strong><br />&nbsp;University of New Mexico<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Diana Huffaker, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nanomedical Science and Technology</strong><br />&nbsp;Northeastern University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Srinivas Sridhar, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>NanoPharmaceutical Engineering and Science</strong><br />&nbsp;Rutgers University<br />&nbsp;Principal Investigator: Fernando Muzzio, Ph.D.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1077669" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Over the years, many investigators in the Alliance have transferred their technologies in the form of patents and start-up companies.&nbsp; The Alliance model for translational research is that discoveries made in academic laboratories are handed off to for-profit partners for efficient development into research and clinical products. Alliance members have been eager to bring their technology to the clinic, forming over 100 start-up companies and partnerships with existing biotechnology firms. Many of these start-ups are thriving and now offer products, research or consulting services to the academic and clinical communities. Others have attracted significant investment from large pharmaceutical companies and venture capital funds.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1090634" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6655268">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090634&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--> <a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1518&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090634&amp;sys_command=edit" target="_blank" class="article-image-enlarge no-resize">Enlarge</a></div>
<figcaption>
<div class="caption-container no-resize">
<p>Numerous companies have been formed by Alliance PI's over the years of the program. These are listed in this graphic by type of product being developed and company name.</p>
<div class="image-photo-credit">Credit: National Cancer Institute</div>
</div>
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Companies listed are either directly started due to Alliance PI R&amp;D, IP that was commercialized to other companies (not owned or begun by Alliance PIs), or companies originated by Alliance PIs prior to receiving awards and used to commercialize IP generating from Alliance funded research. Not all companies still exist, roughly 15% have been purchased by other companies, were renamed, or are no longer in operation.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1077670" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><span>Cancer remains one of the most difficult diseases to both diagnosis and treat. Although great strides have been made for some cancers, the incidence and death rate for many other cancers continues to plague the population. In an effort to help advance the clinical translation of novel nanomedicines designed to improve therapeutic outcomes and enhance diagnostic capabilities, the National Cancer Institute, in concert with the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), created the <a href="http://ncl.cancer.gov/">Nanotechnology Characterization Laboratory</a>&nbsp;(NCL).</span></p>
<p><span>The NCL has been pursuing preclinical characterization and development of these oncology-directed therapies and diagnostics for more than ten years now. In this time, NCL&rsquo;s multi-disciplinary team has worked with more than 100 of the world&rsquo;s foremost nanotechnology research organizations and evaluated more than 300 different nanomaterials. Nearly a dozen NCL collaborators are now in human clinical trials with novel treatment strategies afforded through nanotechnology. NCL&rsquo;s unique setup has afforded an extraordinary opportunity to explore the biocompatibility trends and advantages and disadvantages of a vast array of nanoplatforms, cytotoxics, and targeting strategies in a relatively limited time span. Through sustained research and extensive educational outreach, the NCL strives to continually improve the pursuit of these much needed therapies, speeding their progression to clinical trials</span>.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1078433" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>Johns Hopkins University</h2>
<p><strong>Principal Investigator:</strong> Denis Wirtz, Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Training Focus and Objectives</strong></p>
<p>The interface between nanotechnology and medicine is a new frontier for scientific exploration and for the creation of new and improved diagnostic and therapeutic tools to detect, treat, cure, and prevent human diseases. We offer an integrated predoctoral and postdoctoral training program in nanotechnology for cancer research (NTCR) that is positioned at this interface. This program fosters predoctoral and postdoctoral fellows who are trained across disciplines to lay foundations for technologies that enable an inside-view of cancer cell functions as opposed to the limited black-box input-output techniques currently used, introduce new modalities for molecular imaging, develop new high-throughput diagnostic tools, and engineer novel drug/antibody/siRNA viral and non-viral delivery systems to treat human cancers. NTCR fellows develop novel cancer diagnostics to evaluate each individual patient's prognosis and optimal treatment, based upon the patients' genetic and epigenetic markers and disease phenotype and therapeutics that are selected and optimized for each individual patient. NTCR trainees take one of two core courses depending on their background, as well as a lab course in cancer nanobiotechnology. They participate in a journal club and a dedicated annual symposium, as well as clinical conferences and tumor boards. The NTCR program recruits outstanding trainees every year with MD and/or PhD degrees and diverse backgrounds in either biochemistry, physics, molecular / cellular / cancer biology, or an engineering/physics discipline for a steady state number of 2 postdoctoral and 6 predoctoral fellows. NTCR fellows take advantage of research and clinical resources at the NCI-designated Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center, the Ludwick Center for Cancer Genetics and Therapeutics, The Sol Goldman Pancreatic Cancer Center, and the In Vivo Cellular and Molecular Imaging Center, as well as the unique educational resources and experimental facilities of the recently established Johns Hopkins Institute for NanoBioTechnology (INBT), which houses the center for cancer nanotechnology excellence (CCNE) and the physical sciences-oncology center (PSOC).</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091247" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6655263">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091247&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1090847" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Ralph Weissleder, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> Mikael Pittet, Ph.D., Cesar Castro, M.D., and Claudio Vinegoni, Ph.D.</p>
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>Well over a thousand patients have now received chemically distinct, nano-encapsulated chemotherapeutics, generally showing lower toxicity, increased tumoral accumulation of payloads and occasionally improved progression free survival. Experimentally, an even larger number of new constructs and approaches have been pioneered by the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in cancer members, as well as other groups. Testing in mice usually involves measuring tumor sizes, survival or the use of histopathology and other molecular diagnostics. Yet, despite these advances, much less is known in the in vivo setting, as to how these nanomaterials actually work or fail, what the spatial and temporal heterogeneity is and how efficacy can be improved. Armed with new biological insight from recent feasibility studies leading to this application and the recent developments of new in vivo imaging technologies we are now able to address these important cancer nanotechnology questions in ways that were not previously possible.</p>
<p>The goal of this project is to perform in vivo imaging analyses of therapeutic nanoparticles (TNP), addressing key questions on nanoparticle distribution (pharmacokinetics, PK) and cellular response (pharmacodynamics, PD). Specifically, we will elucidate the following questions i) why aren't current clinical TNP more efficient (aim 1); ii) how much does tumor targeting with affinity ligands help to improve efficacy (aim 2) and iii) can we select responders from non-responders by nanoparticle enhanced MR imaging (aim 3)? We hypothesize that a considerable proportion of tumor cell accumulation is mediated by tumoral myeloid cells (macrophages) rather than by cancer cells, offering a new strategy to further enhance efficacy. Furthermore, the project is complementary to existing Alliance projects and will be useful to other Alliance members across the consortium through future interactions. It will also provide a much needed biological understanding of nanoparticle enhanced MR imaging findings to interpret clinical data.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1091250" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6652612">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1091250&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>The project team includes expertise in nanomedicines, chemistry, multimodality imaging, and molecular / cell / cancer biology.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1090849" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Peixuan Guo, Ph.D., William Carson, M.D., Jianhua Yu, Ph.D., and Daniel Pack, Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> Chris Richards, Ph.D.</p>
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>The overall goal of this project is the systematic characterization of RNA nanoparticle behavior, in vitro and in vivo, to optimize its delivery to triple negative breast cancer (TNBC). RNA nanoparticles are unique in that their scaffold, ligand, and therapeutic components can all be composed of RNA. They are formed by the bottom up self-assembly, are biocompatible, water soluble, and thermodynamically stable. As such, RNA derived nanoparticles have been shown to be non-toxic therapeutic delivery systems with favorable biodistribution and pharmacokinetic profiles. The particles themselves are readily manipulated to create varying shapes and sizes with attachments ranging from those feasible for gene therapy to targeting moieties with facile chemical processing. This project proposes to perform thorough and systematic studies on nanoparticle size, shape, and targeting moieties, on cell targeting, internalization/intracellular trafficking, endosomal escape, favorable biodistribution (e.g., without entrapment in liver), immunogenicity, and tumor regression. Once deciphering the factors that constitute the 'ideal' RNA nanoparticle for its efficient therapeutic delivery via the optimum shape, size, and targeting, the investigators will develop two optimized therapeutic systems; one non-immunogenic for the efficient in vivo delivery of siRNA to tumor cells and one that is highly immunogenic for use as a cancer immunotherapy.</p>
<div sys_dependentvariantid="2084" sys_dependentid="1090984" inlinetype="rxvariant" rxinlineslot="105" sys_siteid="305" class="rx_ephox_inlinevariant mceNonEditable" contenteditable="false" rxselectedtext="" sys_relationshipid="6654537">
<figure class="image-center-full centered-set">
<div class="centered-element"><img src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=1&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_folderid=1052690&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_contentid=1090984&amp;sys_command=edit" alt="" /><!--Comment--></div>
</figure>
</div>
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>The project team includes expertise in nanomaterials, biophysics, bioengineering, immunology, surgical oncology, and molecular / cell / cancer biology.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1090850" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Dmitri Lapotko, Ph.D., and Mien-Chie Hung, Ph.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators:</strong> Ann Gillenwater, M.D., Lie Nie, M.D., Vladimir Torchilin, Ph.D., and Jack Phan, M.D., Ph.D.</p>
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>The goal of this project is to develop a new therapeutic approach to triple negative breast cancer (TNBC) which is based on intracellular mechanical impact generated by plasmonic nanobubbles. The latter are non-stationary vapor bubbles produced around intracellular gold nanoparticle clusters upon their exposure to a short laser pulse. Following absorption of a laser pulse, a gold cluster instantaneously converts optical energy into localized heat and then vapor, generating mechanical impact and killing the host cell. In this project, gold nanoparticles will be co-administered with liposome-encapsulated drugs and/or radiotherapy to assess the synergy among the three modalities: 1) mechanical impact, 2) chemotherapy aided by drug release from nanobubble-disrupted liposomes, and 3) radiation, which will be enhanced due to the presence of gold nanoclusters. EGFR targeting of nanoparticles will enable accumulation of larger gold clusters in EGFR-expressing cancer cells. This, in turn, will lead to a lower plasmonic bubble generation threshold and higher selectivity of the treatment, so a low-energy laser pulse will be sufficient to kill cancer cells while sparing normal cells.</p>
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>The project team includes expertise in nanomaterials, bio/chemistry, physics, surgery, radiation oncology, and molecular / cell / cancer biology.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1090909" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>The NCI Nanodelivery Systems and Devices Branch, which manages the NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer, encourages you to download the Alliance Factsheet located here.&nbsp; In an easily digestible format, highlights of the goals and outcomes of the Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer are presented.</p>
<p><a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1088997&amp;sys_revision=3&amp;sys_variantid=955&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_dependentvariantid="955" sys_dependentid="1088997" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="6894002"><img alt="Download the Factsheet" src="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1482&amp;sys_contentid=819366" inlinetype="rximage" sys_dependentvariantid="1482" sys_dependentid="819366" rxinlineslot="104" sys_siteid="305" sys_relationshipid="6893992" /></a></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1091315" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p><strong>Principal Investigators:</strong> Gabriel Lopez-Berestein, M.D.</p>
<p><strong>Co-Investigators: </strong>Anil Sood, M.D., Bulent Ozpolat, M.D., Ph.D., David Volk, Ph.D., Vittorio Cristini, Ph.D., Zhihui Wang, Ph.D., Lokesh sRao, Ph.D., and Sunila Pradeep, Ph.D.</p>
<h2>Project Summary</h2>
<p>Ovarian cancer, especially high-grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSOC), is the deadliest gynecological cancer with 50-70% five-year mortality rates. Traditional therapy for ovarian cancer has included surgery followed by chemotherapy with platinum/taxane-based regimens. Although most ovarian cancer is initially chemosensitive, recurrence of the disease is common due to development of resistance and significant intra-tumoral heterogenity, both of which contribute to poor prognosis and high mortality rates in patients. Recent clinical and experimental evidence indicate that the monocyte-macrophage axis and tumor-associated macrophages (TAMs), which make up a portion of the tumor microenvironment, play a significant role in tumor growth and progression by contributing to angiogenesis, invasion and metastasis, and drug resistance, particularly in ovarian cancer and especially in HGSOC. Overall our data indicate that in contrast to conventional drugs that target only tumor cells, targeting the tumor microenvironment is required to achieve maximal anti-tumor efficacy. The use of nanoparticles incorporating specific gene silencing molecules (i.e., siRNA) targeting the tumor or its microenvironment is a particularly attractive approach for overcoming obstacles and reprogramming the tumor microenvironment by silencing critical molecular targets. In this study, we will test the hypothesis that the blockade of tumor and tumor microenvironment interactions by therapeutic nanoparticles will provide significant antitumor activity and enhance the efficacy of current regimens in ovarian cancer. Thus, we will determine the mechanism of TAM regulation. We will also determine the biological and therapeutic efficacy of targeting MMA/TAMs using highly targeted dual effect nanoparticles in ovarian cancer models. These include (1) long-acting, slow-release dual assembly NPs (DANPs), and (2) serum resistant highly specific AXL-receptor binding aptamers.</p>
<p>The proposed approaches offer nanotherapeutic formulations targeting multiple components of the tumor and its microenvironment. Specifically, in aim 1 we are focusing on reprograming the tumor microenvironment by eliminating tumor-promoting TAMs using long-acting, slow release DANPs encapsulating an siRNA for a validated target. This will affect the regulatory cascade of these cells and their impact on inflammation, stromal reactions, and eventual tumor growth. In aim 2, we will develop a multiscale 3D mathematical model to evaluate therapeutic efficacy of the nanoparticles with or without AXL aptamers on the nanoparticle surface, and with or without chemotherapy. The model will be used to understand and predict the effects of this nanoparticle-based treatment on MMA cell accumulation, angiogenesis, and tumor progression in HGSOC models. Finally, in aim 3 we will identify specific AXL aptamers and optimize their chemical modifications to determine which ones enhance nanoparticle effects will maintaining good selectivity and targeting. We will also use multipronged dosing schedules to determine optimal dosing regimens that provide effective pharmacological and efficacy profiles.</p>
<h2>Project Expertise</h2>
<p>The team has expertise in nanomedicine, cancer biology, RNA-based therapeutics, liposomes, aptamer development, and mathematical modeling.</p>
<p></p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1091366" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051465" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906301" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051465" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Cancer and Nanotechnology</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1074439" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906302" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1074439" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Benefits of Nanotechnology for Cancer</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1074443" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906303" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1074443" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Earlier Detection and Diagnosis</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1074446" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906304" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1074446" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Treatment and Therapy</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1051490" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906305" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051490" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Current Nanotechnology Treatments</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1073910" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906306" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1073910" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Safety of Nanotechnology Cancer Treatment</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1051476" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906307" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051476" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Clinical Trials</a></li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051491" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906308" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051491" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Funded Research</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051623" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906312" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051623" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">NCI Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051493" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906313" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051493" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Centers of Cancer Nanotechnology Excellence (CCNEs)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051494" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906314" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051494" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Innovative Research in Cancer Nanotechnology (IRCNs)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1077637" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906315" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1077637" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">Cancer Nanotechnology Training Centers (CNTCs)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1077666" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906316" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1077666" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Previous NCI Alliance Grantees</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1064730" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906317" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1064730" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Research Published by NCI Alliance</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1077669" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906318" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1077669" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Companies Formed by PIs of the NCI Alliance</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1051475" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906319" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051475" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Data Sharing</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1077670" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906320" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1077670" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">Nanotechnology Characterization Laboratory (NCL)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1051471" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906321" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051471" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Cancer Nanotechnology Plan</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1051489" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906322" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051489" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">NSDB Partners and Collaborators</a></li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1051499" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906309" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051499" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">NSDB Grants and Training</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=4&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1064733" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906323" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1064733" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Apply for the Alliance</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=2&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1063327" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906324" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1063327" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Related NCI Funding and Initiatives</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1063349" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906325" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1063349" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Training Grants</a></li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2317&amp;sys_contentid=1064646" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906310" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1064646" sys_dependentvariantid="2317">News and Events</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=9&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1064640" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906326" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1064640" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">NSDB News</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=3&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1077041" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906327" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1077041" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">NSDB Events</a></li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=7&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_contentid=1051622" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906311" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051622" sys_dependentvariantid="2297">About NSDB</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1051459" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906328" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051459" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Related NCI Initiatives</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1051460" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906329" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051460" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Publications and Presentations</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=6&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1051457" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906330" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1051457" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Contact and Staff</a></li>
<li><a href="http://percussion.cancer.gov/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_revision=5&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_variantid=1764&amp;sys_contentid=1090909" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" sys_relationshipid="6906331" sys_siteid="305" rxinlineslot="103" sys_dependentid="1090909" sys_dependentvariantid="1764">Alliance Fact Sheet</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
  <row para_id="1091717" langcode="en">
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<h2>University of California, San Diego</h2>
<p><strong>Principal Investigator:</strong> Dong-Er Zhang, Ph.D., and Andrew Kummel, Ph.D.</p>
<h2>Training Focus and Objectives</h2>
<p>This training program seeks to address two issues (1) In spite of all of the research advances in cancer biology and application of these discoveries to the clinic, cancer therapies have had limited success in prolonging life.&nbsp; Engineering approaches have begun to show promise, but there is a dearth of investigators who are trained in both cancer research and engineering/materials science. (2) Current PhD and postdoctoral training in cancer research focuses on preparing trainees to be independent researchers, but it doesn&rsquo;t provide a comprehensive set of skills for young scientists who, when starting their careers in academia, will be working closely with small/startup pharmaceutical or device companies or who may even work in a small firm before reentering academia.&nbsp; There is a synergy in addressing both issues since young scientists with cross training in nanotechnology and cancer biology are well positioned to work in collaboration with or work in small pharmaceutical or medical device companies focused on cancer.&nbsp; The program provides trainees with a balanced combination of (a) a comprehensive cancer biology, engineering, and entrepreneurship didactic training, (b) laboratory experience mentored by both a basic science cancer researcher and clinical/translational cancer faculty (&ldquo;dual&rdquo; academic mentors), and (c) practical skills learned by having the trainees work directly with small business entrepreneurs and for trainees choosing an academic career path, they were present research proposals as well as make oral presentations at conferences.</p>
</div>]]></content>
  </row>
</rows>