<rows>
  <row>
    <term_id>154</term_id>
    <name>Cancer Risk</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>cancer-risk</field_pretty_url>
    <description>News about research on factors that affect cancer risk, including inherited genetic mutations, smoking/tobacco use, obesity, and infectious agents like HPV.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>155</term_id>
    <name>Childhood Cancer</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>childhood-cancer</field_pretty_url>
    <description>News about childhood cancer research, with context from leading experts. Topics include new treatments, issues facing childhood cancer survivors, and findings on the biology of cancer in children.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>164</term_id>
    <name>Survivorship and Supportive Care</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>survivorship-and-supportive-care</field_pretty_url>
    <description>News on research that affect cancer patients and survivors. Topics include managing treatment side effects, fertility preservation, and cancer’s long-term effects.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>158</term_id>
    <name>FDA Drug Approvals</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>fda-drug-approvals</field_pretty_url>
    <description>News on recent approvals of cancer therapies by the Food and Drug Administration. Includes expert comments on how the approval will influence patient care and future research.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>162</term_id>
    <name>Prognosis</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>prognosis</field_pretty_url>
    <description>Reports on cancer prognosis-related research, including articles on doctor–patient communication and approaches to determine patient prognosis more accurately, among others.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>156</term_id>
    <name>Clinical Trial Results</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>clinical-trial-results</field_pretty_url>
    <description>Reports on findings from cancer clinical trials, with commentary from leading researchers on how the trial results will affect patient care.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>166</term_id>
    <name>Treatment</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>treatment</field_pretty_url>
    <description>Cancer treatment related news, with context from leading experts. Includes articles on new therapies, treatment side effects, and important trends in treatment-related research.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>159</term_id>
    <name>Global Health</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>global-health</field_pretty_url>
    <description>News and expert commentaries about the impact of cancer around the world and efforts to improve global health, including new initiatives and research findings.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>157</term_id>
    <name>Disparities</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>disparities</field_pretty_url>
    <description>News and commentaries about cancer-related racial/ethnic and socioeconomic disparities. Includes stories on factors that influence disparities and efforts to address them.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>163</term_id>
    <name>Screening and Early Detection</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>screening-and-early-detection</field_pretty_url>
    <description>News about research on cancer screening and early detection. Includes stories on the impact of screening, new technologies, and approaches to improving the safety and efficacy of screening.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>165</term_id>
    <name>Technology</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>technology</field_pretty_url>
    <description>News and commentaries on technology used to conduct cancer research, deliver cancer treatment, improve patient care, and screen for cancer, as well as other topics.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>160</term_id>
    <name>Leadership and Expert Views</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>leadership-and-expert-views</field_pretty_url>
    <description>Commentaries from scientific leaders at NCI and other institutions about cancer research topics, programs, and initiatives.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>153</term_id>
    <name>Biology of Cancer</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>biology-of-cancer</field_pretty_url>
    <description>Cancer biology research news, with context from experts at NCI and elsewhere. Topics include cancer metastasis, the tumor microenvironment, and new targets for cancer therapies.</description>
  </row>
  <row>
    <term_id>161</term_id>
    <name>Prevention</name>
    <field_owner_blog>860259</field_owner_blog>
    <langcode>en</langcode>
    <field_pretty_url>prevention</field_pretty_url>
    <description>Cancer prevention news, with comments from leading scientists. Topics include preventive interventions for those at increased risk of cancer, protective behaviors, and more.</description>
  </row>
</rows>
