  <rows>
  <row para_id="45393" langcode="en">
    <heading><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>What causes cancers of the head and neck?</p>
</div>]]></heading>
    <content><![CDATA[<div class="rxbodyfield">
<p>Alcohol and tobacco <a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1139566&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1139566" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7267902"></a>use (including smokeless tobacco, sometimes called &ldquo;chewing tobacco&rdquo; or &ldquo;snuff&rdquo;) are the two most important risk factors for head and neck cancers, especially cancers of the oral cavity, oropharynx, hypopharynx, and larynx (<a href="#r2">2</a>&ndash;<a href="#r5">5</a>). At least 75% of head and neck cancers are caused by tobacco and alcohol use (<a href="#r6">6</a>). People who use both tobacco and alcohol are at greater risk of developing these cancers than people who use either tobacco or alcohol alone (<a href="#r6">6</a>&ndash;<a href="#r8">8</a>). Tobacco and alcohol use are not risk factors for salivary gland cancers.</p>
<p>Infection with cancer-causing types of <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045714&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="../../Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045714&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">human papillomavirus</a> (HPV), especially HPV type 16, is a risk factor for some types of head and neck cancers, particularly oropharyngeal cancers that involve the tonsils or the base of the tongue (<a href="#r9">9</a>&ndash;<a href="#r11">11</a>). In the United States, the incidence of oropharyngeal cancers caused by HPV infection is increasing, while the incidence of oropharyngeal cancers related to other causes is falling (<a href="#r9">9</a>). More information is available at&nbsp;the <a href="/Rhythmyx/assembler/render?sys_contentid=1139566&amp;sys_revision=1&amp;sys_variantid=2297&amp;sys_context=0&amp;sys_authtype=0&amp;sys_siteid=305&amp;sys_folderid=" sys_dependentvariantid="2297" sys_dependentid="1139566" inlinetype="rxhyperlink" rxinlineslot="103" sys_siteid="305" sys_folderid="" sys_relationshipid="7267903">HPV and Cancer</a>&nbsp;page.</p>
<p>Other risk factors for cancers of the head and neck include the following:</p>
<p><b>Paan (betel quid)</b>. Immigrants from Southeast Asia who use paan (betel quid) in the mouth should be aware that this habit has been strongly associated with an increased risk of oral cancer (<a href="#r12">12</a>, <a href="#r13">13</a>).</p>
<p><b>Preserved or salted foods</b>. Consumption of certain preserved or salted foods during childhood is a risk factor for nasopharyngeal cancer (<a href="#r14">14</a>, <a href="#r15">15</a>).</p>
<p><b>Oral health</b>. Poor oral hygiene and missing teeth may be weak risk factors for cancers of the oral cavity (<a href="#r16">16</a>, <a href="#r17">17</a>). Use of mouthwash that has a high alcohol content is a possible, but not proven, risk factor for cancers of the oral cavity (<a href="#r16">16</a>, <a href="#r17">17</a>).</p>
<p><b>Occupational exposure</b>. Occupational exposure to wood dust is a risk factor for nasopharyngeal cancer (<a href="#r14">14</a>, <a href="#r15">15</a>). Certain industrial exposures, including exposures to asbestos and synthetic fibers, have been associated with cancer of the larynx, but the increase in risk remains controversial (<a href="#r18">18</a>). People working in certain jobs in the construction, metal, textile, ceramic, logging, and food industries may have an increased risk of cancer of the larynx (<a href="#r19">19</a>). Industrial exposure to wood or nickel dust or <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000269439&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="../../Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000269439&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">formaldehyde</a> is a risk factor for cancers of the paranasal sinuses and nasal cavity (<a href="#r20">20</a>&ndash;<a href="#r22">22</a>).</p>
<p><b>Radiation exposure</b>. Radiation to the head and neck, for noncancerous conditions or cancer, is a risk factor for cancer of the salivary glands (<a href="#r16">16</a>, <a href="#r23">23</a>, <a href="#r24">24</a>).</p>
<p><b>Epstein-Barr virus infection</b>. Infection with the <a class="definition" onclick="javascript:popWindow('defbyid','CDR0000045684&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English'); return false;" href="../../Common/PopUps/popDefinition.aspx?id=CDR0000045684&amp;version=Patient&amp;language=English">Epstein-Barr virus</a> is a risk factor for nasopharyngeal cancer (<a href="#r25">25</a>) and cancer of the salivary glands (<a href="#r26">26</a>, <a href="#r27">27</a>).</p>
<p><b>Ancestry</b>. Asian ancestry, particularly Chinese ancestry, is a risk factor for nasopharyngeal cancer (<a href="#r14">14</a>, <a href="#r15">15</a>).</p>
</div>]]></content>
    <sortrank>1</sortrank>
  </row>
  </rows>